<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De non temerandis ecclesiis, churches not to be violated. A tract of the rights and respect due unto churches. Written to a gentleman who having an appropriate parsonage, imployed the church to prophane uses, and left the parishioners uncertainely provided of divine service, in a parish neere there adjoyning. / Written and first published thirty years since by Sir Henry Spelman knight.</title>
            <author>Spelman, Henry, Sir, 1564?-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E335_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861432</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861432</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E335[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>De non temerandis ecclesiis, churches not to be violated. A tract of the rights and respect due unto churches. Written to a gentleman who having an appropriate parsonage, imployed the church to prophane uses, and left the parishioners uncertainely provided of divine service, in a parish neere there adjoyning. / Written and first published thirty years since by Sir Henry Spelman knight.</title>
                  <author>Spelman, Henry, Sir, 1564?-1641.</author>
                  <author>Spelman, Clement, 1598-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition with a new epistle.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[30], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hall printer to the Universitie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" ("a long preface on the history of sacrilege"--Madan) is signed "Clem: Spelman" (Sir Henry Spelman's son).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church discipline --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church --  Authority --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and the world --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>De non temerandis Eccleſiis,</hi> CHVRCHES NOT TO BE VIOLATED.</p>
            <p>A Tract of the Rights and Reſpects Due unto CHURCHES: Written to a Gentleman who having an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Parſonage imployed the Church to prophane uſes, and left the Pariſhioners uncertainly provided of Divine Service in a Pariſh neere there adjoyning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVritten and first publiſhed thirty years ſince By</hi> Sir HENRY SPELMAN Knight.</p>
            <p>The third Edition with a new Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by HENRY HALL Printer to the UNIVERSITIE. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmall Tract, now above two yeares paſt, was by mee printed for that worthy Knight the Authour thereof, with no intent to have it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: and being hitherto by mee ſuppreſſed from reprinting here at home; I find it to be of late time printed in Scotland (contrary both to the Authours and my expectation) and Dedicated by another man to the Biſhops and Clergy there, and ſo made more publique, being of it ſelfe private, then was firſt intended: which (I ſuppoſe) had the Authour knowne, or once miſdoubted the ſequel, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>De non temerandis Eccleſiis,</hi> he would have ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another Title, <hi>De non temerandis Scriptis alienis:</hi> that his writings might not be imprinted, when Benefices are made proper. Wherefore finding many ſlips in it from his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, I have (as well in the right of the Authour as of my ſelfe, (to whom the right of the ſole Printing belonged) cauſed it to be reprinted. And though at the time of the putting it to the Preſſe, I could not conferre with the Authour, he being then in the Country, yet hath it pleaſed him ſince his coming home to adde ſomething more unto it, as his leaſure would permit him; which I have annexed to the end thereof. And thus have I attempted to make a private worke publique, leſt the faults of other men, ſhould unjuſtly be caſt upon him, that deſerved ſo well in ſo rare an Argument.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the veſſels of the Kings Houſe are not gold, or ſilver, or for uſes of <hi>Honour.</hi> Some be common ſtuffe, and for meane ſervices, yet profitable. Of the firſt ſort, I am ſure this <hi>Tract</hi> is not. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the other or no, I leave that to thy judgement. To deale plainely; my ſelfe have no great opinion of it; as finding mine owne imperfections, and writing it onely upon a private occaſion to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate freind, without curious obſervation of matter or <hi>method.</hi> But having alſo written a greater <hi>worke</hi> (much of the ſame Argument) and intending to publiſh, or ſuppreſſe it, as I ſee cauſe: I thought it not unfit (upon ſome encouragement) to ſend this forth (like a <hi>Pinneſſe</hi> or <hi>Poſt of Advice</hi>) to make a diſcovery of the <hi>Coaſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I adventure my greater <hi>Ship.</hi> If I receive good advertiſement, I ſhall grow the bolder. Howſoever, take this I pray thee, as it is: and let my <hi>zeale</hi> to the cauſe, excuſe me in medling with matters beyond my ſtrength.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:3"/>
            <head>A Letter ſhewing the occaſion of this Treatiſe to the Worſhipfull his moſt loving unkle FR. SA. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good Vncle, the ſpeeches that paſt caſually betweene us at our laſt parting, have runne often ſince in my minde; and ſo (perhaps) have they done in yours. You complained (as God would have it) that you were much croſt in the building you were in hand with, upon a peice of gleabe of your <hi>Appropriate Parſonage</hi> at <hi>Congham.</hi> I anſwered, that I thought God was not pleaſed with it, inſomuch as it tended to the defrauding of the Church, adding (amongſt ſome other words) that I held it utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to keepe <hi>Appropriate Parſonages from the Church. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our talke proceeding, I perceived that as God had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his portion in your heart, ſo in this, though it concerned your profit, you ſeemed tractable. It much rejoyced me, and therefore apprehending the occaſion, I will be hold to adde a continuance to that happy motion: (ſo I truſt, both you and I ſhall have cauſe to terme it) and beſides, to give you ſome tribute of the love and duty I long have ought you. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (good Vncle) as your heart hath happily conceived theſe bleſſed ſparkes, ſo in the name and bleſsing of God, cheriſh and enflame them. No doubt they are kindled from heaven, like the fire of the Altar, and are ſent unto you from God himſelfe, to be a light to you in your old daies (when your bodily eyes faile you) to guide your feete into the way of peace, that is, the way and place from whence they came. So alwaies I pray for you, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving and faithfull Nephew HENRY SPELMAN.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Weſtminſt.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 17. 1613.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:4"/>
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, this ſmall Treatiſe was 30 yeares ſince written and publiſhed by my Father now deceaſed; his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was to diſſwade a prophanation of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and to perſwade a reſtitution of Tithes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations to the Church; Wherein although he was not ſo happy as with Saint <hi>Peter</hi> at once to convert thouſands, yet was he not with him ſo inſucceſſefull, as to fiſh all might and catch nothing; for ſome were perſwaded with what is written, nor can I ſay that others beleeved not; but rather thinke, that like the young man in the Goſpell, they went heavy away, becauſe they had too great poſſeſſions to reſtore.</p>
            <p>Miſcheifes are with more eaſe prevented then cured, men ſooner diſſwaded from a reception, then perſwaded to a reſtitution. While therefore the great diſſolution of <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> and <hi>Deanaries</hi> is onely threatned not acted, I have cauſed a reimpreſſion of this Tract, hopeing that (as at firſt) it will finde ſome beleevers, and the rather becauſe written long ſince, by one, no <hi>Levite,</hi> himſelfe and children as his Anceſtours meere Lay-men, not having nor hopeing for any Eccleſiaſticall preferrement, and therefore I am confident he tooke his motives ſolely from the dictates of religion and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, himſelfe practiſing what he would perſwade thee. I know thy argument for retaining impropriations, Abbeys &amp;c. is, the Law hath made them lay-fees, thou didſt legally buy them, and therefore mayeſt lawfully keepe them.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe our Statutes of Diſſolution have changed the courſe of the fee, from a politicke ſucceſſion to a naturall deſcent; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily put a lay man in to the Preiſts place. But tell me if any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or humane Law doth or can take away the Dedication or the Conſecration of Abbeys, Monaſteries &amp;c. diſcharge or annull the intereſt which God and his Church hath in them, and for which they were founded, as that hoſpitality, ſicke and feeble men may be maintained, Almes given, and other Charitable deedes be done,
<pb facs="tcp:113568:4"/>and prayers be there ſaid, as is declared in the Statute. 35. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">35: <hi>Edw:</hi> 1. <hi>ca:</hi> 1.</note> or can any Statute divert, and diſpence with the many and heavy curſes of the Church, upon the violators of Church liberties, to which the whole Kingdome hath not onely cried Amen, but by Act of Parliament hath enjoyned the Biſhops to curſe the violaters. If theſe be not removed, then remaine they ſtill dedicated, ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to God; and then ſeeke and ſatisfie thy ſelfe, whether thou having the appropriation and Tithes but as the Abbot had them, and receiving the profit as the Abbot did, art not as the Abbot, tyed in Law and Conſcience or one of them to performe the duties: for that he was, appeares by the opinion of all Judges 18. <hi>Eliz:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plow. fol. <hi>496.</hi>
               </note> where it is ſaid by the Judges, that none is capable of an appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (for ſo the Law calls them) but onely bodies politicke not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and the reaſon is becauſe he that hath the appropriation is to be perpetuall incumbent, which a naturall body that muſt dy could not be. And that body politicke (to have the rectory, the glebe, and tithes) muſt be Spirituall not Lay. For in that he is made Parſon (ſaith the booke) he hath the cure of the ſoules of the pariſhioners, and therefore muſt be Spirituall, for by the ſame reaſon that a patron cannot preſent a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to his Church, by the ſame reaſon a Lay-man cannot be an Appropriator; For they are both Parſons of the Church, the preſented Parſon for life, the Appropriator for ever. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Plowden</hi> ſaith, that the Appropriator, be he Abbot or Prior &amp;c. is as fully incumbent Parſon, as if he had beene preſented, inſtituted and inducted: and as Parſon ſhall have his Actions, and that he that is duely made Parſon is thereby made poſſeſſor of the Parſonage for the ſpirituall Office,<note place="margin">plow. fo. <hi>500.</hi>
               </note> attracts the poſſeſſions of the things belonging to the Office, and in that he is Parſon, he receives the Tithes not as granted to him, but as things annexed to the Office of a Parſon. And Tithes are frequently in our Common Law termed ſpirituall things becauſe annext to the ſpirituall Office. By theſe Bookes and reſolutions of the Judges it is cleare that the appropriatour was the incumbent Parſon, and had the cure of the ſoules of the Pariſhioners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 33, 35.</note> and that upon the preſentation of the appropriatour or upon the diſſolution of the Abbey, the Church became voide, and preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as other Churches upon reſignation or death of the incumbent.</p>
            <p>For appropriations (as thou now ſeeſt) were but Parſonages
<pb facs="tcp:113568:5"/>with cures of ſoules, annext and appropriated to a particular Abbey or Religious houſe. For when their Fraternities became numerous, &amp; their annuall charge greater then their yearely revenue; providence to provide for their family made them thinke how to increaſe their income; And themſelves being patrons of many rich parſonages, obtained ſeverally (as occaſion ſerved) licence from the King, and conſent from the ordinary to annex or appropriate that parſonage to their Abbot and his ſucceſſours for ever, whereby they became perpetuall incumbent parſon, and anciently did duely officiate the Cure by one of their Fraternity untill the Statute of <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the appropriating any Church,<note place="margin">15. <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 6.</note> unleſſe a Vicar be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently indowed by the diſcretion of the Ordinary to doe divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and keepe hoſpitality;<note place="margin">4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 12.</note> and the Statute of 4 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. ordained that no Religious (as Monkes and Fryers were) ſhould be made Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars to any Church appropriated, but Seculars (as our Miniſters now be) canonically inſtituted and inducted. Upon theſe Statutes it will concerne the owners of Churches appropriated ſince 15 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. to ſee, that out of the profits of the Church a convenient ſumme of money be yearly paid to the poore pariſhioners,<note place="margin">15 <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. <hi>ca</hi> 6.4. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>ca</hi> 12.</note> and a Vicar indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Statute of the 15. of <hi>R.</hi> 2. appoints, or elſe the Stat. 4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. avoids the appropriation, and then the Church becomes againe preſentative.</p>
            <p>But ſome will object, that impropriate Churches with their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Tythes (the fat of impropriations) are made Lay and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and as Lay and Temporall things diſpoſable at the will of the owner: a doctrine which ſo nearly concernes the eſtates and lively-hood of ſo many men in this kingdome as I ſhall not averre the contrary, leaſt ſome <hi>Demetrius</hi> with his fellowes tumuit about it; yet give me leave to offer thee ſome oppoſite conſiderations, but leave them, and their reſult to thy judgement and conſcience.</p>
            <p>Conſider firſt that while God ſaith, that ye have robbed me of my Tithes and offerings, God claimes the title and intereſt of them to be in him, not in the Preiſt nor in the Levite, they being but the <hi>uſu-fructuarii,</hi> God the owner.</p>
            <p>Remember too,<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca:</hi> 20. 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap:</hi> 7.</note> that our Statutes have declared Tithes to be due to God and holy Church, and thy with-drawing thy Tythes a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting thy duty to Allmighty God, and then conſider that if the Tithes be Gods, it matters not whether his title be by Divine right
<pb facs="tcp:113568:5"/>(as our<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dier.</hi> 28. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ſo</hi> 43. tithes are due by the Law of God. <hi>ex debito. Co.</hi> 2. <hi>Wiocheſt.</hi> caſe. <hi>ſo.</hi> 45. <hi>b.</hi> tithes are due by Divine Right.</note> Law and Lawyers) not to preſſe that with the reſolution of Councells and opinions of Canoniſts, Fathers, and Divines, quoted by the Author) have taken them to be, or by humane Conſtitution; for what Statute, what Law, can conclude God, or bind his right? Then weigh how the King (from whom thou claimeſt) had the Tithes, thou haſt, and to what intent he had them.</p>
            <p>The Statute of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. gives the King the ſmaller Abbyes and houſes of Religion with their Appropriations and Tithes. To the greater, <hi>H.</hi> 8. makes his title by grant and ſurrender of the Abbots, Priors: which between the 27 and 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8. had been laboured by <hi>Cromwell;</hi> with ſome he prevailed by intreaty and good Annuities; with others by the Kings Power &amp; Sword for the Abbots of<note n="b" place="margin">R. Whiting.</note> 
               <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenbury,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Hugh Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</note> 
               <hi>Reading,</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Iohn Bech. Goodw. <hi>167.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> whoſe innocency had made them regardleſſe of Threats, and their piety abhorre rewards to betray their Churches; were therefore (ſaith <hi>Goodwin</hi>) tenderd the<note n="e" place="margin">There was no Oath of Supremacy, untill 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> but theſe that denyed <hi>H.</hi> 8. to be ſupream Head of the Church, were indicted upon the Statute 26. <hi>H.</hi> 8, <hi>c</hi> 12. ſince repealed, for that they <hi>malitioſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare Domin: Regem de dignitate titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo &amp; nominee ſtatus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> regal.</hi> Said that the King was not Supreame Head of the Church. And upon this were <hi>Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas More, Exmew,</hi> and divers others indicted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, and executed, by vertue of a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> directed to <hi>Audley</hi> Lord <hi>Chancellour,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and other Lords, and all the Judges, as appeares by the Reports under the hand of Sir <hi>Iohn Spelman,</hi> who was then a Judge of the Kings bench.</note> Oath of Supremacy, which they refuſing, are, as enemies to the State, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and hanged, others terrified by their examples, leaves all to the diſpoſe of the King, who not reſting on that title, procures the Statute of 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 13. which reciting (how truly doe thou judge) the <hi>Grants, Surrenders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to have been made freely, voluntarily, and without compulſion,</hi> gives all the Religious houſes, with their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances and Tithes, to the King his Heires and Succeſſors (as the Statute 27. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. did) <hi>in as large a manner as the Abbot had the ſame to dispoſe thereof at his will and pleaſure</hi> (but) <hi>to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and pleaſure of Almighty God:</hi> nor is there any one word ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Statute of the 31. or that of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. to alter or change the primative nature and uſe of Tithes. And therefore the Statute of the 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. calls the withdrawing of thy Tithes, whether pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate or impropriate, a neglecting of thy duty to Almighty God, thereby inferring, that the Tithes are ſtill due to God.</p>
            <p>Conſider that thy impropriate Tithes are yet even in Law called Eccleſiaſtick, and ſolely recoverable in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts; and
<pb facs="tcp:113568:6"/>that the Statute of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.</note> gives one and the ſame remedy both for the preſentative and impropriate Tithe, and therefore muſt make both, or neither, Lay and Temporall.</p>
            <p>Inquire too, whether the Impropriater hath the <hi>Cure of Soules,</hi> the Abbot had, (eſpecially where no Vicar is endewed) if thou doſt find he hath not, know who hath, for the Sheep muſt not be without a Shepheard, nor he without the milke of the Flock.</p>
            <p>Learne by what Statute, what Law, the Impropriator, if freed of the Cure, is yet tyed to repaire the Chancell, as the Abbot did, and as the Abbot (where no Vicar is endew'd) tyed to provide one to officiate divine Service and Sacraments. If impropriate Tithes be temporall things, why doth the impropriator in all Courts make his title in the Churches right? if lay and temporall, why weare they theſe Eccleſiaſtique badges?</p>
            <p>I cannot for my part think that Statutes which declares Tithes to be <hi>due to God and holy Church,</hi> which directs (among other things, even impropriate Tithes) to be diſpoſed to <hi>the pleaſure and honour of Almighty God,</hi> which calls the withdrawing thy impropriate Tithes, <hi>a neglecting of thy duty to Almighty God.</hi> I cannot think that theſe Statutes did either alter, or intended to alter the Eccleſiaſtique primative nature and uſe of Tithes, and the rather becauſe I find that the Lawyers, who likely had the penning of them did hold Tithes due by divine Right, and annext to the ſpirituall office of the Parſon, &amp; conſequently not alterable. And then thou that juſtly condemneſt this Parſon, or that Vicar, for ſometimes neglecting his duty, think with thy ſelfe what account will be exacted of thee that receiveth the ſame Salery and wages with the Parſon and Vicar; yet doſt totally neglect the duty and miſpendeſt all the Church Revenue up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy owne private occaſions,<note place="margin">39. Canon.</note> while the Canon of the Apoſtles would not permit the Biſhop to challenge ought to himſelfe, or to <hi>dispoſe among his kindred or friends,</hi> but <hi>to adminiſter them, Tanquam Deo intuente, to the poore and Fatherleſſe.</hi> And conſonant to that is that in<note n="f" place="margin">Cook. <hi>5.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. fol. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caudris</hi> caſe in the 5th <hi>Report,</hi> where the Abbot might not <hi>dispend the</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Free almes were the rents and revenues, as appeares by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. <hi>E.</hi> 1.24.14. <hi>E.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>free almes of the Abbey</hi> (much leſſe thou Tithes) <hi>upon his ſecular friend, but in hospitality upon the poore, the Fatherleſſe, the Stranger, &amp;c.</hi> and if ſo, then the Abbots were but Gods truſtees, and as his Almners diſpenced them to Gods Pentioners, the poore, the Fatherleſſe and Widdow. And doe thou inquire how thou haveſt
<pb facs="tcp:113568:6"/>them and<note n="h" place="margin">Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> in his <hi>Mag. Charta. f.</hi> 649. in his <hi>Comment</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. touching tithes, quotes the Text in <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. And the <hi>Levite</hi> ſhall come, &amp; the ſtranger, the fatherles, and widdow, within thy Gates ſhall eate thereof. Here is (ſaith he) the right uſe whereto tithes ſhould be imployed; &amp; ſurely had they been lay or temporall, then they, no more then other tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things are tyed to Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtique uſes. And he wrote long after our Statutes, and beſt knew the power &amp; operation of them.</note> oughteſt to diſpoſe them. For I feare that at the laſt and generall Audit, thou wilt find them great Cloggs to thy accompt, and in the <hi>interim,</hi> ruines to thy Family; yet I doubt not but thou wilt find probable reaſons as well as Law for reteining of Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations and Abbies which thou haſt bought, or thy Friends left thee: yet read this enſuing Treatiſe, the reaſons may perſwade thee, if not, with me view the inſucceſſe of Sacrilegious perſons.</p>
            <p>But before thou canſt judge of Sacrilegious perſons, thou muſt know, what is Sacriledge, for ſuch there is, elſe the Apoſtle erred, who whilſt thou ſayeſt, <hi>that thou ſhalt not commit Idolatry,</hi> upbraides thee with, <hi>and committeſt thou Sacriledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacriledge</hi> is the diverſion of holy and Eccleſiaſtique things to prophane and ſecular uſe: as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi;</hi> Theft and Sacriledge, be evill Brethren, <hi>Theft</hi> robs thy Neighbour, <hi>Sacriledge</hi> thy God. Tithes are ſo undoubtedly Gods inheritance, as though ſome have curiouſly diſputed his title to them, as how due; yet none but the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriator</hi> denies his right to them, as not due: but <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations</hi> are the ſubject of the enſuing <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> therefore I will offer thee my Conceipt, how <hi>Abbies</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries</hi> are conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, and ought not to be prophaned by ſecular uſe.</p>
            <p>It is noted that in all <hi>Ages,</hi> in all <hi>Religions,</hi> the Temples of their Gods were accounted holy, and not to be prophaned by ſecular ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: and this being ſo univerſally obſerved in ſeverall <hi>Ages,</hi> in differing <hi>Empires,</hi> contrary <hi>Religions,</hi> it muſt needs be by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the univerſall <hi>Monarch</hi> God.</p>
            <p>Reaſon taught a Heathen to conclude, <hi>Quod ab omnibus gentibus obſervatum eſt, id non niſi a Deo ſancitum eſt.</hi> Did God by the Law of Nations teach <hi>Heathens</hi> to keep the Temples of their falſe Gods as ſacred; And doth he not by the ſame Law Command thee a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to preſerve his owne holy and unviolated?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Divell,</hi> that (to his greater Condemnation) beſt knowes God, and is therefore his beſt <hi>Counter-fait,</hi> gets himſelfe among the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Temples, Prieſts, Oblations,</hi> and to theſe the <hi>Attributes of holy,</hi> and <hi>ſacred;</hi> he knew them to belong to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> and therefore, to be like the moſt high, uſurpes them to him and his.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Divell</hi> knew that the <hi>Temple of God</hi> which ſanctifies the gold that is upon it, muſt needs be <hi>holy</hi> it ſelfe, and <hi>ſanctifie the ground</hi> on which it ſtands, and therefore the <hi>Divell</hi> taught his Diſciples that
<pb facs="tcp:113568:7"/>doctrine,<note place="margin">Plin. Epiſt. l. <hi>10.</hi> f. <hi>615.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Licet aedes ſacra Claudij Caeſaris collepſa ſit, religio tamen occupat ſolum.</hi> Profit could not tempt <hi>Trajan</hi> to permit publique bathes to be made where once <hi>Caeſars</hi> Temple ſtood, the <hi>holy ground</hi> muſt not be prophaned by ſecular imployment. Yet thou a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an doſt not ſpare the very <hi>Temple of God himſelfe.</hi> Shall it not (in this point) be eaſier at the laſt day for <hi>Trajan,</hi> then for thee, for if he a <hi>Heathen</hi> thus eſteemed a <hi>falſe God,</hi> that muſt come to be judged, how would he have reverenced, the <hi>true and ever living God</hi> (had he, as thou) knowne him? but this only argues, and doth not prove a <hi>ſanctity in Temples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God himſelfe hath told us in <hi>Leviticus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 27.</note> that <hi>Lands and houſes may be ſanctified to the Lord,</hi> but they are redeemable at the value eſtimated by the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and a fifth part more. But God there tells us that things <hi>devoted are most holy to the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 28.</note> and not redeemable, the reaſon given by Divines is, <hi>becauſe it was given with a Curſe,</hi> &amp; if that be the reaſon; doe thou then peruſe the <hi>Charters of Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Monaſteries and Abbies,</hi> and tell me if they be not <hi>devoted and moſt holy to the Lord.</hi> And then, if not redeemable, much leſſe I thinke to be taken from the Church; without any ſatisfaction, or conſent of the <hi>Triests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Charters</hi> were uſually in theſe words, <hi>Conceſſi Deo &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae &amp;c. offero Deo &amp;c. confirmavi Deo &amp; Eccleſiae,</hi> and theſe <hi>Grants</hi> have in our <hi>Common Law</hi> been adjudged good and valid; our much reverenced <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſo oft confirmed by Parliament, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with <hi>Conceſſimus deo quod Eccleſia Anglicana libera ſit &amp;c.</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in his <hi>Comment</hi> upon it, ſaith, <hi>What is granted for God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cook. Magna Charta. fol. <hi>2.</hi> quod datum Eccltſiae da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum deo. Lib. <hi>6.</hi> f. <hi>176.</hi> cap. <hi>285.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is in Law deemed to be granted to God, what is granted for his honour, what for maintenance of his ſervice of his Religion, is granted to and for God, and that antiently theſe Grants were good in Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Capituler of <hi>Charles</hi> the great ſaith, that the <hi>Dedications</hi> were on this ſort, the <hi>Founder</hi> mentioning in a writing all he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to give, and holding it over the <hi>Altar,</hi> ſpake thus to the Prieſt: <hi>I here give unto God all things conteined in this writing, for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my ſinnes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and for them for whoſe good God will accept them, and by theſe to promote Gods ſervice in ſacrifice in Lights, in Suſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Clergy, the Poore, and in all things honourable to God, and profitable to his Church, and if any man ſhall take theſe away (which
<pb facs="tcp:113568:7"/>God forbid) let him for his Sacriledge give a moſt ſtrict account to God, to whom they are now dedicated, now devoted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Founders</hi> of <hi>Religious houſes,</hi> in the concluſion of their <hi>Deed,</hi> following the example of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ra.</hi> 6.12. And the God that cauſed his name to dwell there, deſtroy all Kings &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that put to their hands to alter or deſtroy this houſe of God.</note> 
               <hi>Darius,</hi> imprecates a moſt heavy <hi>Curſe</hi> on them that violate or withdraw their guift<note n="†" place="margin">Apostolatus Benedictin. in Angl: Apend. ſecund. f. <hi>60.13.</hi> E. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Venientibus contra haee &amp; diſtruentibus ea occurrat Deus in gladio irae &amp; furoris &amp; vindictae &amp; maledictionis aeternae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here is to be remembred that <hi>Abbies</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries</hi> had in them <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Chappells</hi> which had from the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> a more particular dedication and conſecration, then from their <hi>Founders,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> uſing therein much <hi>Almes,</hi> many <hi>Prayers,</hi> and ſome decent <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and after, even to the <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> were there conſtantly adminiſtred, and our <hi>Ancestors</hi> had ſo reverent an eſteeme of <hi>Churches,</hi> as following the example of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> would not permit <hi>buying</hi> and <hi>ſelling</hi> in the <hi>Church-yard,</hi> but by Parliament prohibites it.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, that if under the <hi>Leviticall Law,</hi> which in this was morall and not taken away, the ſingle act of <hi>devoting thy houſe to the Lord,</hi> conferred ſuch a <hi>Sanctity,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Holineſſe</hi> upon it, that it could never be redeemed, but at a fifth part more then the worth, and that valued by the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> ſhall the <hi>Founders guift,</hi> (which was the dedication in the <hi>Leviticall Law</hi>) the <hi>fervent Prayers</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> the long and frequen <hi>adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Service</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> under the <hi>Gospell,</hi> ſhall theſe adde nothing of <hi>Sanctity,</hi> nothing of <hi>Reverence</hi> to it; But even where thy <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Grandfathers</hi> for many hundreds of yeares reverently on their <hi>knees</hi> received <hi>myſtically</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there thou (to avoyd <hi>ſuperſtition</hi>) doſt ſacrilegiouſly feed thy <hi>Oxe,</hi> and thy <hi>Aſſe,</hi> and not permitting <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as at firſt, to lye between them, but more uncivill then the <hi>Jewiſh hoſt,</hi> turneſt him out to make roome for them.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay theſe <hi>Abbies,</hi> theſe <hi>Monaſteries</hi> were Founded and dedicated by <hi>Idolatrous Perſons,</hi> Conſecrated by <hi>Popiſh Biſhops,</hi> and for <hi>ſuperſtitious uſes,</hi> and therefore not <hi>ſacred,</hi> nor acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>For the unworthineſſe of their Perſons, and their act, conſider <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, who as God himſelfe ſaith, were <hi>ſinners</hi> againſt their owne <hi>Soules,</hi> nor canſt thou thinke the <hi>ſinne ſmall,</hi> where
<pb facs="tcp:113568:8"/>thou findeſt their <hi>puniſhment ſo great;</hi> for God ſmites them not as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziha</hi> with <hi>leproſie,</hi> nor with <hi>withered hands</hi> as <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> nor with <hi>death</hi> like <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza,</hi> but to make their <hi>puniſhment</hi> anſwerable with their <hi>offence,</hi> God doth a new thing in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> fire from above con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes theſe, and the earth from beneath, ſwallowes up thoſe men; and although <hi>Moſes</hi> be commanded to ſcatter the fire <hi>(for Civill Magiſtrates may quench the fire of Rebellion)</hi> yet <hi>Aaron</hi> the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtique hand muſt firſt gather up the <hi>Cenſers,</hi> for they were <hi>holy,</hi> and God gives there the reaſon why <hi>holy,</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>they offered them to the Lord.</hi> And if ſo bad men by a ſingle, and ſo bad an act, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate their <hi>Cenſers to the Lord,</hi> needs muſt the <hi>Pious guift</hi> and <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the <hi>Founders,</hi> with the often <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> dayly uſed for many yeares, needs muſt they <hi>ſanctifie</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Chappell</hi> where uſed.</p>
            <p>While God ſpake once from the <hi>Buſh</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> he Commands him <hi>not to draw nigh,</hi> and yet at that diſtance bids him <hi>put off his ſhooes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſhua. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>for the ground was holy.</hi> And <hi>Joſhua muſt be barefoot while he ſpake with the Captaine of the Lords Hoſt, becauſe the ground was holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider then that if the places be <hi>holy,</hi> where God ſpake once to <hi>Moſes,</hi> once to the <hi>Captaine of the Lords Hoſt,</hi> needs muſt the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Chappell</hi> be <hi>holy,</hi> where God hath ſo often ſpoken to thy <hi>Fathers</hi> in <hi>Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Sermons,</hi> and where they to him ſo often in <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Thankeſgiving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If publique <hi>holy actions</hi> doe not <hi>ſanctifie</hi> the place where acted, <hi>David</hi> (though he would not offer to God that which coſt him nought) needed not to buy that which he did not offer, the <hi>Threſhing-floore</hi> of <hi>Araugna,</hi> it had been ſufficient for <hi>David</hi> to pay for the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> and <hi>threſhing inſtruments,</hi> that muſt be burnt not reſtored. The <hi>floore</hi> remained, but not for <hi>Araughnas</hi> uſe, (ſaith a Learned <hi>Divine</hi>) for by <hi>Davids</hi> Sacrifice, the <hi>floore</hi> was <hi>devoted and ſanctified to the Lord,</hi> and might not return to worldly imployment, which <hi>David</hi> knew, and therefore bought it.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay, theſe are <hi>Dedications</hi> and <hi>Sanctions</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> not under the <hi>Gospell.</hi> 'Tis true theſe were <hi>Sanctions</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> and were <hi>Morall,</hi> not <hi>Cerimoniall,</hi> and therefore remaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Gospell.</hi> Chriſt that ſends thee from the <hi>Altar,</hi> to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to thy <hi>Brother,</hi> commands thee to leave thy <hi>Guift</hi> behind thee at the <hi>Altar,</hi> and the reaſon given by <hi>Divines</hi> is, <hi>becauſe thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted
<pb facs="tcp:113568:8"/>it to the Lord,</hi> the <hi>guift</hi> remaines <hi>holy,</hi> and might not return to the world, for though thy perſon be not accepted, yet thy <hi>guift</hi> by thy <hi>devoting, is holy to the Lord,</hi> as were the <hi>Cenſers,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Corah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſeeſt that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who would not <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould ſtrike to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue him, his Maiſter from violence, yet he himſelfe ſtrikes to free the <hi>Temple</hi> from <hi>Sacrolege,</hi> and thou canſt not think that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtroke this day to preſerve, what he would <hi>aboliſh</hi> the next day, the <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dee but conſider that of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphirah,</hi> and thou wilt conclude, that the <hi>Devoting</hi> any thing to God, is under the <hi>Gospell, a ſanctifying it to the Lord,</hi> and the withdrawing it, muſt then be <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge,</hi> which was <hi>Ananias</hi> ſinne, agreed by all <hi>Diviner,</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> in his notes upon it ſaith, <hi>predium Conſecrâſſent Eccleſiae,</hi> they had <hi>Conſecrated</hi> it to the <hi>Lord;</hi> to conclude, thou canſt not <hi>violate</hi> or <hi>irreverently</hi> uſe a <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Temple,</hi> but thou muſt diſrationate S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> argument, who diſwades the pollution of thy <hi>Body,</hi> becauſe it is the <hi>Temple of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou mayſt obſerve our Law books to have held <hi>Tythes</hi> due by <hi>divine right,</hi> our <hi>Parliaments</hi> in their <hi>Statutes</hi> too, have acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Tythes</hi> due to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>holy Church</hi> and this both before &amp; after the <hi>Statutes</hi> of <hi>Diſſolution;</hi> &amp; that at this day the Law reckons <hi>tythes</hi> of impropriate, as well as of preſentative <hi>Churches</hi> to be Eccleſiaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ique things, and if this will not perſwade a reſtitution of ſuch as thou haſt, yet let it diſſwade a reception of more: For I know thou would'ſt not buy a Title litigious between thee and thy neighbour; and why wilt thou that which (at beſt) is queſtionable between thee and thy God, that muſt judge the Title, and in a Court where thou canſt have no advocate but his <hi>Sonne,</hi> whom thou would'ſt diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit.</p>
            <p>But the deſtruction of <hi>Corah</hi> perſwades more with the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> then the ſoft voyee of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Oratory</hi> may take thee, <hi>Hell</hi> hath frighted ſome to <hi>Heaven;</hi> view then the inſucceſſe of <hi>Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons</hi> in all ages, that will prevaile with thee, for had <hi>Corah</hi> and his <hi>Complices</hi> been viſited after the viſitation of other men, thou and I, nay perhaps the whole Congregation of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> would have beleived what they ſaid is truth, it ſounded ſo like reaſon, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what they did as pious, it looked ſo like <hi>Religion,</hi> but their end
<pb facs="tcp:113568:9"/>otherwiſe inform'd them, and better inſtructed us: I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee with preſidents of forraign Nations, as <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinat,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> where under colour of <hi>Reformation,</hi> the ruine of <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> and <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> mightily inriched for the preſent both publique and private <hi>Coffers,</hi> and now the <hi>Ravenous</hi> War hath both exhauſted the <hi>wealth,</hi> and almoſt <hi>unpeopled the Country; hoc o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Deus avertat.</hi> I will therefore tye my ſelfe to our owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſtory, unhappily plentifull in miſerable examples.</p>
            <p>I will begin with <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerer;</hi> In the firſt year of his raigne, he fires by his <hi>Normaines,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Holl. fol. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Yorke.</hi> In the 4th, he rifles the<note n="b" place="margin">Holl. fol. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> and about the<note n="c" place="margin">Speed. f. <hi>429</hi> Camb. But. <hi>259.</hi>
               </note> 18th year of his raigne deſtroyed 36 <hi>Mother Churches</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> to make his <hi>New-Forreſt,</hi> takes all their <hi>Plate,</hi> all their <hi>Treaſure,</hi> even the <hi>Chalices.</hi> In the<note n="d" place="margin">Holl. <hi>12.</hi> Speed. <hi>428.</hi> Matt. Par. fol. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his raign, the Sonne out of his own loynes <hi>(Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert of Normandy)</hi> Rebels againſt him, and in <hi>Battaile</hi> beates his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> from his Horſe, wounds his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and (which to him is worſe) his <hi>honour.</hi> About the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year, <hi>Richard</hi> his ſecond (but firſt beloved) Sonne, ſporting in his Fathers <hi>New-Forreſt,</hi> is there ſtrangely killed by the goaring of a Stagge, ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Speed. <hi>429.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Speed,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Camb. <hi>259.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Camden,</hi> by a peſtilent Ayre. In the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his raigne, he burnt the City of<note n="g" place="margin">Holl. <hi>14.</hi> Speed. <hi>431.</hi> Matth. Par. fol. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mannts,</hi> &amp; Church of S. <hi>Maries,</hi> with to <hi>Anchorites;</hi> and comming too nigh the flame, the heat of the fire and his Armes attracts a diſſeaſe, and his Horſe leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, breaks his <hi>Riders belly,</hi> whereof he dies, and his <hi>Body</hi> (forſaken of his Nobles and Servants) lyes three dayes neglected, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the courteſy of a Country gentleman, his <hi>Corps</hi> is brought to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Speed. <hi>434.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stephens Church</hi> in <hi>Cane</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> but in the paſſage the Town <hi>Fires</hi> and his bearers leave him, and run to quench that, ſo that dead he goes not quietly to his <hi>Grave,</hi> whither brought at laſt is there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed <hi>Buriall</hi> by one who claimed the ground as his inheritance, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from him by the <hi>Duke,</hi> all <hi>Ceremonies</hi> ſtay untill a compoſition was made, and an <hi>Annuall</hi> rent (ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">Daniel. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Daniell</hi>) paid for his <hi>Grave,</hi> in which before he could be laid, his body ſwelling, burſt to the great annoyance of the Company, he is offenſive dead and living, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the towne being taken by an Enemy, his <hi>Bones,</hi> as unworthy to be inſhrined in a Church, are digged up and ſcatrered like <hi>Chaffe before the winde,</hi> death denies him reſt.</p>
            <p>His<note n="k" place="margin">Speed. <hi>429.</hi>
               </note> Grand-child <hi>Henry</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Robert,</hi> hunting in the <hi>New-Forreſt,</hi> is ſtrucke throw the <hi>Jawes</hi> with a bough of a <hi>Tree,</hi> and like
<pb facs="tcp:113568:9"/>
               <hi>Abſalom,</hi> found <hi>hanging</hi> in the <hi>thicket of an Oake.</hi> His <hi>Grandchild William</hi> (ſecond Sonne to <hi>Robert</hi> Dake of <hi>Normandy</hi>) was made Earle of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and in a Warre againſt his Vncle <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, received a ſmall<note n="l" place="margin">Speed. <hi>462.</hi> Mat. Par. <hi>71.</hi> Milles lat. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>wound</hi> in his <hi>hand,</hi> and thereof dyed the laſt of the <hi>Conquerors Grand-children</hi> by his eldeſt Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> the <hi>Conquerors</hi> eldeſt ſonne, diſinherited by his <hi>Father,</hi> is taken<note n="m" place="margin">Stow.</note> 
               <hi>priſoner</hi> by his brother <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, who puts out both his <hi>Eyes,</hi> and after 26 yeares impriſonment, <hi>Robert</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ma. Par. <hi>73.</hi> Speed. <hi>467.</hi>
               </note> dyes ſtarved in the Goale at <hi>Cardaffe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Rufus</hi> ſucceeded his Father in his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Curſe,</hi> in his firſt yeare his Nobles<note n="o" place="margin">Speed <hi>440.</hi> Mat. Par. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rebell,</hi> in his ſixth, a great <hi>Famine</hi> rageth, and ſuch a <hi>mortality,</hi> as the <hi>quick</hi> can ſcarce bury the <hi>dead.</hi> About the<note n="p" place="margin">Holl. <hi>22.</hi> Speed. <hi>445.</hi>
               </note> 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeare of his Raigne, his <hi>Treaſury</hi> is ſtored by ſale of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices</hi> and <hi>Church-Jewells.</hi> In his 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeare, while Sir<note n="q" place="margin">Speed. <hi>448.</hi> Mat. Par. <hi>54.</hi> Cervus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus cum ante eum (regem) tranſiret dis Rex cuidem mi liti. Wal. Tirrel. trahe Diabole. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ijt ergo telum volatile, &amp; obstante ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum reflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſaciens per medium cordis ſaucia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit qui ſubitò mortuus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit.</note> 
               <hi>Walter Tir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> ſhoots at a <hi>Deare</hi> in the <hi>New-Forreſt,</hi> he kills the <hi>King,</hi> (in the ſame place where a Church ſtood) who dyes (<hi>beaſt</hi> like) not ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mills</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Arrow</hi> glanced from the Deare, <hi>Speed,</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris,</hi> from a Tree, and killed the <hi>King,</hi> but both agree his <hi>death</hi> to be (as his <hi>Fathers</hi>) by accident. He dead, his <hi>followers</hi> (as did his <hi>Father's</hi>) leave his <hi>body</hi> and fled; his <hi>Funeralls</hi> are as his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> interrupted, for his<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. Par. ib. Speed <hi>449.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Corps</hi> were laid in a <hi>Colyers Court</hi> drawne by one <hi>ſilly leane Beaſt,</hi> (ſaith the Book) in his paſſage the Cart brake in foule and filthy wayes, leaving his <hi>body</hi> a <hi>miſerable ſpectacle, pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully goared,</hi> and <hi>filthily bemired,</hi> ſo, as his <hi>Father,</hi> he paſſeth not qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly to his <hi>Grave,</hi> yet at laſt he is brought bleeding to <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and there buryed unlamented. <hi>Speed</hi> ſaith his<note n="ſ" place="margin">Speed, ibid.</note> 
               <hi>bones</hi> were after ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up and laid in a <hi>Coffer</hi> with <hi>Canutus</hi> his <hi>bones;</hi> but there they reſt not, for in <hi>December</hi> 1642. <hi>Wincheſter</hi> being entered by the <hi>Parliament forces,</hi> the <hi>Organes, Windows,</hi> and <hi>Cheſts,</hi> wherein the <hi>bones</hi> of many our <hi>ancient Kings</hi> were <hi>preſerved,</hi> were by the <hi>fury</hi> of the <hi>souldiers broken,</hi> and among others <hi>his,</hi> and as his <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> as not worthy <hi>buriall.</hi> And this was the third of the <hi>Conquerours</hi> Iſſue that was <hi>murdered</hi> in the <hi>New Forreſt,</hi> where the <hi>Doggs</hi> licked the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Naboth,</hi> there they muſt licke the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Ahab,</hi> where the <hi>sacriledge</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, muſt be the place of the <hi>puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugh</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewsbery</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Wil. Ruſin</hi> commanding againſt
<pb facs="tcp:113568:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:113568:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:113568:11"/>the <hi>Welchmen</hi> in <hi>Angleſey,</hi> kenneled his <hi>Doggs</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of S. <hi>Frydance,</hi> where in the morning they were found <hi>madd,</hi> the <hi>Earle</hi> ſhortly after fighting with the <hi>enemy,</hi> was with an <hi>Arrow</hi> ſhot<note n="t" place="margin">Holl. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dead</hi> in the <hi>eye,</hi> the reſt of his <hi>body</hi> being ſtrangely armed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, the <hi>Conquerours</hi> fourth <hi>Sonne,</hi> is his brothers <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor,</hi> he had ſeverall <hi>Children,</hi> whereof his eldeſt <hi>William,</hi> with his brother <hi>Richard</hi> and Siſter <hi>Mary,</hi> in a calme day are<note n="u" place="margin">M. Pa f <hi>69.</hi> Speed <hi>459.</hi> Holl. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>drowned</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh ſhore,</hi> himſelfe eating <hi>Lampreis</hi> dies on a <hi>ſurfet,</hi> and being opened, the <hi>ſtinck</hi> of his <hi>body</hi> and <hi>braines</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">M Par. <hi>73.</hi> Speed <hi>467.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>poyſon</hi> his <hi>Phyſitions,</hi> one other of his <hi>Daughters</hi> mournes her <hi>virginity</hi> in a <hi>Nunnery,</hi> and dyes <hi>Childleſſe,</hi> and in the next Generation is his name forgot, <hi>Plantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> takes the Crowne.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable, that the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> all his Sonnes and all their Sonnes, dyed <hi>untimely deaths,</hi> (unleſſe thou reckoneſt the <hi>Lamprey Surfet</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> 2. to be naturall) &amp; what the<note n="x" place="margin">Fol. <hi>20.</hi> in margine.</note> Author notes of <hi>Nabuc.</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 8. is alſo true of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> (for in the 68. after his <hi>deſtroying</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> Church at <hi>Yorke,</hi> which was in his ſecond yeare) his <hi>Name</hi> is extinct, and his <hi>Kingdome</hi> is devolved to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation,<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed. f.</hi> 46. that the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> time, held 69 year.</note> 
               <hi>Plantaginet</hi> takes his <hi>Crowne,</hi> &amp; upon ſearch (I feare) thou ſhalt find very few <hi>Families</hi> (among the many thouſands) in <hi>England,</hi> who enjoy their Sacrilegious poſſeſſions of <hi>Abbies</hi> and <hi>Impropriations</hi> beyond the 68 yeare, and very many that hold them not halfe the time, and none almoſt but with ſome notable <hi>misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot omit the Sacriledge and puniſhment of King <hi>John,</hi> who in the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeare of his Raigne, among other <hi>Churches,</hi> rifled the <hi>Abbies</hi> of<note n="z" place="margin">Hol. <hi>194.</hi> Par. f. <hi>287.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peterborough</hi> and <hi>Croyland;</hi> and after attempts to carry his <hi>ſacrilegious wealth</hi> from <hi>Lynne</hi> to <hi>Lincolne,</hi> but paſſing the <hi>Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> in the midſt of the <hi>waters</hi> opens her <hi>mouth</hi> (as for <hi>Korah</hi> and his company) and at once <hi>ſwallowes</hi> up both <hi>Carts, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and <hi>Horſes,</hi> all his <hi>Treaſure,</hi> all his <hi>Regalities,</hi> all his <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoyle,</hi> and all the <hi>Church-spoylers,</hi> not one<note n="a" place="margin">Matt. Par fo. <hi>287.</hi> nec pes unas eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit qui regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſam nunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aret.</note> eſcapes to bring the <hi>King</hi> word; the <hi>King</hi> himſelfe paſſes the <hi>Waſhe</hi> at another place, and lodges that night in <hi>Swinſteed Abbey,</hi> where the <hi>newes</hi> and <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> (whereof he dyed) together met him, ſome ſay he was <hi>poyſoned</hi> by a <hi>Munke</hi> of <hi>Swinſteed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Math Par. fo. <hi>687.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marſhall</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> the great <hi>Protecter</hi> both of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> having in the <hi>Iriſh warre</hi> forceably taken
<pb facs="tcp:113568:11"/>from the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Furnes</hi> two <hi>Mannors</hi> belonging to his <hi>Church,</hi> was by him much ſolicited to reſtore them; but the <hi>Earle</hi> refuſing, was by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> excommunicate, and ſo <hi>dying,</hi> was <hi>buried</hi> in the <hi>Temple Church</hi> at <hi>London.</hi> The <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſues to the <hi>King</hi> to returne the <hi>Lands,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> requires the <hi>Biſhop</hi> to abſolve the <hi>Earle,</hi> and both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> goes to the <hi>Earles grave;</hi> where the <hi>Biſhop</hi> in the <hi>Kings</hi> preſence uſed theſe words, <hi>Oh</hi> William, <hi>which lyes here ſnared in the bonds of Excommunication, if what thou haſt injuriouſly taken from my Church, be with cempetent ſatisfaction reſtored either by the King, thy heires, or friend; I then abſolve thee otherwiſe, I ratifie my ſentence, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t tuis ſemper peccatis involutus in inferno ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas condemnatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> blames the <hi>Biſhops</hi> rigour, and perſwades the Sonnes to a reſtitution, but the Eldeſt <hi>William</hi> anſwered, <hi>He did not beleeve his Father to have got them unjuſtly, becauſe poſſeſſions got in Warre, becomes a lawfull inheritance, and therefore if the doting old Biſhop hath judged falſely, upon his owne head be the curſe, my Father dyed, ſeized of them, and I lawfull inherit them, nor will I leſſen my eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which the <hi>Biſhop</hi> hearing, was more grieved at the ſonnes contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, then the Fathers injury, and going to the <hi>King,</hi> told him, <hi>Sir, what I have ſaid, ſtands immutable; the puniſhment of Malefactors is from the Lord. And the curſe written in the Pſalmes, will fall heavy upon Earle</hi> William, <hi>in the next Generation ſhall his name be forgot, and his ſonnes ſhall not ſhare the bleſſing of</hi> increaſe and multiply, <hi>and ſome of them ſhall dye miſerable deaths, and the inheritance of all be disperſed and ſcattered, and all this my Lord, O King, you ſhall ſee even in your dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With what ſpirit the <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſpake it, doe thou judge, for in the ſpace of 25 yeares, all the five Sonnes of the <hi>Earle</hi> ſucceſſively, according to their <hi>Birth,</hi> inherits his <hi>Earldome,</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi> and all dye <hi>Childleſſe,</hi> the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>Family</hi> is extinct, and the <hi>Lands</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and diſperſed; and that nothing might faile of what the <hi>Biſhop</hi> foretold<note n="c" place="margin">Matth. Par. <hi>400.</hi> &amp; <hi>403.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Richard</hi> his ſecond ſonne is ſore <hi>wounded,</hi> and taken <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and there dyes of his hurts.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Matt. Par. f. <hi>565.</hi> Aune Dom. <hi>1241.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gilbert</hi> the third ſonne juſting at <hi>Hertford</hi> breaks the <hi>Reynes</hi> of his <hi>Bridle,</hi> and falling from his <hi>Horſe</hi> one <hi>foot</hi> hangs in the <hi>ſtirrop,</hi> and he thereby <hi>dragged</hi> about the <hi>field,</hi> till <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>torne,</hi> and ſo by a miſerable <hi>death</hi> ſatisfied the <hi>Curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:12"/>
            <p> But theſe examples are at too great a diſtance and not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, but through the perſpective of <hi>Antient Hiſtory,</hi> I will therefore come nigher and view Cardinall <hi>Woolſey,</hi> who from a m ane and obſcure root grew to <hi>over ſhaddow</hi> all the ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> eminent for Wit as Learning, great in the eſteeme and favour of his <hi>Prince,</hi> laden with <hi>home</hi> and <hi>Forraigne dignities,</hi> full of <hi>wealth</hi> as yeares; in briefe he was, while free from <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> the great and ſucceſſefull <hi>Counſellor</hi> of his <hi>Prince,</hi> and indeed the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue</hi> of humane bleſſings: but about the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, <hi>Woolſey</hi> by conſent and licence of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,<note n="e" place="margin">Holl. f. <hi>891.</hi> Stow. Good. f. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> diſſolves forty ſmall <hi>Monaſteries</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> to erect two <hi>Colledges,</hi> the one in <hi>Oxford,</hi> the other in <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> thou and I may think this a work of <hi>Piety,</hi> to deſtroy the <hi>poor Idolatrous Cells</hi> of <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> and <hi>ignorant Monkes,</hi> to erect <hi>ſtately Cottages</hi> for learned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious <hi>Divines,</hi> this God muſt accept, and proſper both the <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Acter.</hi> No, thou art deceived, he that would not that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe evill, that good may come thereof, will not accept an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> commenced by <hi>Sacriledge</hi> in the ruine of 40 <hi>Religious Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Woolſey</hi> layes the foundation of his <hi>Colledges,</hi> but never ſets up their <hi>Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About three yeares after the <hi>King</hi> poſſeſſeth his <hi>Pallace</hi> at<note n="f" place="margin">Good f. <hi>104.</hi> Holl. <hi>909.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, (Whitehall,)</hi> the <hi>Great Seale</hi> is taken from <hi>him,</hi> his great <hi>wealth</hi> ſeiſed, and <hi>himſelfe</hi> confined to a poore houſe at <hi>Aſſure,</hi> where he remained a time (ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">God. f. <hi>106.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Godwin</hi>) without neceſſaries dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to borrow <hi>furniture</hi> for his <hi>houſe,</hi> money for his <hi>expences,</hi> ſo as in his <hi>ſpeech</hi> to the <hi>judges</hi> he complained, that he was <hi>driven</hi> as it were to <hi>begge</hi> his <hi>bread,</hi> from <hi>doore</hi> to <hi>doore:</hi> 21. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. he is convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in a <hi>Premunire,</hi> all his <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Eſtate</hi> ſeiſed by the<note n="h" place="margin">Holl. <hi>909.</hi> Good. f. <hi>67.</hi> Good. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>King,</hi> his <hi>Colledge</hi> at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> deſtroyed before built, that at <hi>Oxford</hi> receives ſome indowment and a new name from the <hi>King,</hi> but is never to be finiſhed. In the 22. <hi>H.</hi> 8. at his <hi>Caſtle</hi> at <hi>Caywood,</hi> he is by the Earle of<note n="i" place="margin">Holl. <hi>915.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Northumberland</hi> arreſted of <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and fent towards <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Leceſter</hi> the <hi>Lievtenant</hi> of the <hi>Tower</hi> met him, at whoſe ſight he was much <hi>affrighted,</hi> and to prevent a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and ignominious death which he feared, he gave himſelfe (ſaith<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mart.</hi> 304.306.</note> 
               <hi>Martin</hi>) a <hi>Purge,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. Pont. Rom. &amp; Card. f. <hi>1408.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Venenum recepiſſe,</hi> (ſay they that write the lives, of the <hi>Popes</hi> &amp; <hi>Cardinalls</hi>) whereof he dyed, and was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely buried in <hi>Leceſter Abby</hi> without other memory then his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:12"/>
            <p> The <hi>Cardinall</hi> in diſſolving his forty <hi>Monaſteries</hi> had uſed the help of five men (beſides <hi>Cromwell</hi>) whereof two afterwards<note n="l" place="margin">Good. f <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> fought a <hi>Duell,</hi> in which one is <hi>ſlaine,</hi> and the ſurvivor <hi>hanged</hi> for the <hi>murther,</hi> ſo each dyed guilty of his own and the others <hi>blood;</hi> a third becomes <hi>Judas</hi>-like his own executioner, for <hi>throwing</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into a <hi>well,</hi> he is there <hi>drowned;</hi> the fourth a great <hi>Richman</hi> (to whom nothing is ſo terrible as <hi>poverty</hi>) lives to <hi>begge</hi> his <hi>bread</hi> from <hi>doore</hi> to <hi>doore;</hi> the fift, a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> cruelly <hi>murthered</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by<note n="m" place="margin">Stow. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg. f. <hi>498.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thomas Fitz. Garret,</hi> ſonne to the Earle of <hi>Kildare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might here remember how <hi>Tope Clement</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, after his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary conſent to deſtroy <hi>poore Religious Houſes,</hi> is himſelfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of his<note n="n" place="margin">Speed. fol. <hi>996.</hi> Hiſt. Pont. Rom. &amp; Card.</note> 
               <hi>ſtately Pallace</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and being <hi>beſieged</hi> at <hi>his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Angelo,</hi> is there conſtrained to eate <hi>Aſſes Fleſh,</hi> and taking ſuch conditions as a <hi>Victorious Enemy</hi> would give, is driven to <hi>plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> his own <hi>Church</hi> to pay his <hi>Enemies</hi> Army, and at laſt <hi>dyes wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly</hi> of a miſerable <hi>diſeaſe:</hi> but this is <hi>Forraign,</hi> and I tyed to home examples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Lord Audley,</hi> received the firſt fruits of <hi>H.</hi> 8 his <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> for in the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his <hi>Raigne,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> diſſolved (by what meanes I finde not) the <hi>Priory</hi> of <hi>Chriſt. Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and gave, ſaith<note n="o" place="margin">Stow. <hi>24.</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stow,</hi> the <hi>Church Plate</hi> &amp; <hi>Lands</hi> to Sir <hi>Thomas Audley,</hi> who upon the diſſolution of <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> got that of S. <hi>James</hi> in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Walden</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and made it both his <hi>Seate,</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> of his <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony,</hi> and after left it to <hi>Margaret</hi> his <hi>Daughter</hi> and <hi>Heire,</hi> firſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Henry Dudley,</hi> Sonne to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> ſlaine at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Quintynes,</hi> and dyed without Iſſue, and after ſhe was ſecond Wife to <hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi> who had iſſue, <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> created Lord <hi>Walden,</hi> being his <hi>Grandfathers Title,</hi> and to credit his <hi>Mothers Inheritance</hi> upon the <hi>Scite</hi> of the <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> he began a goodly<note n="p" place="margin">Audly Inne.</note> 
               <hi>Structure</hi> (but attended with the fate of <hi>ſacrilegious foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi>) for that much impaires him, and he never perfects that, he met alſo with other <hi>misfortunes,</hi> which betiding ſo Noble a <hi>Family,</hi> and not yet publiſhed to the <hi>World,</hi> are fitter for thy <hi>inquiry,</hi> then my <hi>Penn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardinall Woolſey</hi> being dead, his ſervant <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſucceeds him in his <hi>Court, Favour,</hi> and <hi>Fate,</hi> as their <hi>birthes</hi> were alike <hi>obſure,</hi> their <hi>riſe,</hi> alike <hi>eminent,</hi> ſo alike <hi>miſerable</hi> were their <hi>downefall,</hi> wonder not at the firſt part of their <hi>fortune,</hi> but contemplate the
<pb facs="tcp:113568:13"/>later; <hi>Policy</hi> in <hi>Kings,</hi> preferres <hi>able men</hi> to high <hi>places</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> for <hi>authority, power,</hi> and <hi>eſteeme</hi> of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> advantages their actions; of which wiſe <hi>Princes</hi> reap the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> the <hi>Actors</hi> get but <hi>gleanings,</hi> while the <hi>King</hi> makes <hi>Cromwell</hi> a <hi>Baron,</hi> his <hi>Seere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> Lord <hi>Privy Seale,</hi> his <hi>Vicegerent</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſticis,</hi> he doth but faciliate his owne <hi>great work</hi> of diſſolving<note n="q" place="margin">Speed. <hi>10.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> a buſineſſe wherein <hi>Cromwell</hi> was too much verſed, and unhappily too ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull. Report ſpake him a great <hi>Stickler</hi> for the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and that although the <hi>Gospell</hi> had loſt a <hi>Pillar</hi> in Queene <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> yet was another raiſed in<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed</hi> 1016.92.</note> 
               <hi>Cromwell,</hi> for he had cauſed the <hi>Bible</hi> to be read, the <hi>Creed, Pater Noſter,</hi> and <hi>Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to be learned in Engliſh, and expounded in every<note n="ſ" place="margin">Good. f. <hi>146.</hi>
               </note> Church, ſome thought that <hi>Cromwell</hi> hoped to bury <hi>Popery</hi> in the ruines of the <hi>Abbyes,</hi> and thereby give the better growth to the more pure <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> how pious ſoever his intents were in reforming <hi>Religion,</hi> yet was not the manner of effecting them, it ſeemes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to <hi>Heaven,</hi> for by <hi>Parliament</hi> in the 31 of H. 8. he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected his Diſſolutions, and in <hi>April,</hi> in the 32 of H. 8. he is made<note n="t" place="margin">Holl. <hi>950.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Lord Great Chamberlaine</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> high in the <hi>Kings favour</hi> and <hi>eſteeme,</hi> yet inſtantly, while ſitting at the <hi>Councell-Table,</hi> he is ſuddainly apprehended and ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> whence he comes not forth, untill to his<note n="u" place="margin">Goodw. fol. <hi>174.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Execution,</hi> for in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> he is preſently accuſed of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and unheard, is <hi>attainted.</hi> Some do obſerve that he<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Edward Cook, <hi>in his</hi> Iurisdiction of Courts, f. <hi>37. ſaith,</hi> that Sir <hi>Tho. Gaudy,</hi> then a grave Judge of the Kings Bench, after told him, that <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvell</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to attend the Chiefe Iuſtices, to know whether a man that was forth comming <hi>(as being in Priſon)</hi> might be attainted of high Treaſon by Parliament, and not called to anſwer. <hi>The Judges anſvvered,</hi> It was a dangerous queſtion, and they thought a Parliament would never doe it. <hi>But being by the expreſſe command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment of the King and they preſſed by the ſaid Earle</hi> (Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Earle of Eſſex) <hi>to anſvver directly, ſaid,</hi> That if he was attainted by Parliament, it could not be queſtioned, whether the Party was called to anſwer or not; <hi>but the Party, againſt whom this was intended, (ſaid he)</hi> was never queſtioned, but that the first man that ſuffered by that procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, was the ſaid <hi>Cromvvell</hi> himſelfe.</note> 
               <hi>procured</hi> that Law of <hi>Attaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> by <hi>Parliament,</hi> without hearing the <hi>Party,</hi> and that <hi>himſelfe</hi> was the firſt, that by that <hi>Law dyed unheard,</hi> for in <hi>July</hi> following, he was thereupon <hi>beheaded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next conſider, that King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, who ingroſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge,</hi> and retailed it to <hi>Poſterity,</hi> what the <hi>Pope</hi> permitted <hi>Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cambden</hi>) <hi>H.</hi> 8. with the aſſent of his <hi>Parliament,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits <hi>himſelfe;</hi> the firſt to catch the <hi>Pope,</hi> pretends <hi>charity,</hi> and <hi>good
<pb facs="tcp:113568:13"/>workes</hi> (<hi>Colledges</hi> ſhall be built) the later to winne the <hi>Layety</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> was offered with the <hi>revenue</hi> of <hi>religious houſes</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain 40<note n="y" place="margin">M. <hi>Howes</hi> his Preface to <hi>Stowes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</hi> Sir <hi>Ed Cooks</hi> Juriſdiction of Courts. <hi>fol.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>Earles,</hi> 60 <hi>Barons,</hi> 300 <hi>Knights,</hi> 40000 <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and for ever eaſe the <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>Taxes,</hi> and <hi>Subſidies,</hi> both obtained their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in diſſolving, neither perform the ends promiſed. <hi>H.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> had firſt furthered <hi>Woolſey</hi> in his diſſolution, and thereby found the way to ruine all the reſt.</p>
            <p>In the<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Acts. 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.31.</note> 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his <hi>raign,</hi> by <hi>Parliament</hi> he diſſolves the <hi>leſſer houſes</hi> &amp; in the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> 31<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the <hi>great ones,</hi> in the<note n="b" place="margin">37. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 37<hi rend="sup">th</hi> all the <hi>Colledges, Hospitalls,</hi> and <hi>Free-chappells,</hi> except ſome few, and <hi>poſſeſſeth</hi> all their <hi>lands, goods,</hi> and <hi>treaſure.</hi> For the firſt halfe of his <hi>Raigne,</hi> (while free from <hi>Sacriledge</hi>) he was <hi>honoured</hi> of his <hi>Allies</hi> abroad, <hi>loved</hi> of his <hi>ſubjects</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> ſucceſſefull in his <hi>actions,</hi> and at peace, as it were, with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> but after his <hi>Sacriledge</hi> (as in disfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with both) his <hi>Subjects Rebell,</hi> firſt in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> after in <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, Somerſet, Yorkeſhire,</hi> and the <hi>Northerne</hi> parts, as alſo in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſuch dearth of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Corne</hi> in <hi>England</hi> (the <hi>Grainery</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi>) that many dye <hi>starved,</hi> which hath not been ſince the 40 of <hi>H.</hi> 3. And now (like <hi>Saul</hi> forſaken of God) he falls from one ſinne to another. Queen <hi>Katherine</hi> (the Wiſe of his <hi>Boſome</hi> for 20 years) muſt now be put away, the <hi>marriage</hi> declared voyd, and he deſirous of <hi>ſonnes,</hi> rather then <hi>Pillars</hi> to bear his name, marryes the Lady<note n="c" place="margin">Speed. fol. <hi>1040.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> and by her had the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp; in the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his <hi>Raigne,</hi> a <hi>ſonne</hi> borne dead (to his great affliction) the 19 of <hi>May,</hi> 1536. The 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his <hi>Raigne</hi> ſhe is beheaded, and the next day he<note n="d" place="margin">Speed. <hi>1039.</hi>
               </note> marryes the <hi>Lady Jane Seymore,</hi> who being with Child by him, ſhe (nature unwilling to give birth to the <hi>ſonne</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>) wants ſtrength to bring forth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Father</hi> Commands<note n="e" place="margin">Speed. <hi>1040.</hi>
               </note> her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeition, and the <hi>Mother</hi> the 12 of <hi>Octob.</hi> dyes to give a ſhort life to her <hi>ſonne,</hi> and the fixt of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> in the 31<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year, the King weds the Lady <hi>Anne</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Speed. <hi>1039.</hi> Ibid.</note> of <hi>Cleve,</hi> and in <hi>July</hi> after is divorced: and in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> following he marries the Lady <hi>Katherine Howard,</hi> and in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> in the 33 of his <hi>Raign</hi> ſhe is <hi>attainted,</hi> and dyes on the <hi>block;</hi> and in <hi>July</hi> in the 35<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his <hi>Raigne,</hi> he marryes the Lady <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Parre.</hi> Here's <hi>Wives</hi> enough to have peopled another <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> had he had <hi>Jacobs bleſſing;</hi> but his three laſt are <hi>childleſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Children</hi> of the two firſt are by <hi>Statute</hi> declared<note n="g" place="margin">28. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>illegitimate,</hi> and not <hi>inheritable</hi> to the <hi>Crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:14"/>
            <p> But himſelfe growing <hi>aged</hi> and <hi>infirme,</hi> hopeleſſe of more <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and not willing to venture the ſupport of his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> upon a <hi>ſingle</hi> and ſo <hi>weake</hi> a propt, as was his Sonne <hi>Prince Edward.</hi> In the<note n="h" place="margin">35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 35 year of his <hi>Raign</hi> he <hi>intailes</hi> the <hi>Crowne</hi> upon his <hi>Children,</hi> after his <hi>death</hi> they all ſucceſſively ſway his <hi>Scepter,</hi> and all dye <hi>Childleſſe,</hi> and his <hi>Family</hi> is extinct, and like <hi>Heroſtratus</hi> his name not mentioned, but with his <hi>Crimes.</hi> His <hi>Crowne</hi> happily deſcends to the <hi>iſſue</hi> of his <hi>eldest Siſter,</hi> and a <hi>Forraign Nation</hi> (like <hi>Cyrus</hi> his) fill his <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the many great and <hi>active men</hi> ayding <hi>H.</hi> 8. in his diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> &amp; receiving great reward out of his <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spoyle, Charles Brandon, Duke of Suffolke</hi> was the <hi>cheife,</hi> he had four <hi>wives,</hi> his firſt the daughter of <hi>Nevile,</hi> Marqueſte <hi>Mounteagle,</hi> who dyed without iſſue. By His ſecond <hi>wife</hi> he had one <hi>Daughter,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to <hi>Stanly,</hi> Lord <hi>Mountague,</hi> but dyed without iſſue. His third <hi>wife</hi> was <hi>Mary</hi> Queen <hi>Dowager</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Siſter</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. by her he had one <hi>ſonne, Henry,</hi> and two <hi>Daughters, Francis</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianor.</hi> His <hi>ſonne</hi> was created Earle of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> but dyed a Child; his <hi>Daughter Francis</hi> marryed <hi>Gray,</hi> Marqueſſe <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and after Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> who had one ſonne <hi>Henry</hi> who dyed young, <hi>Jane Gray</hi> his eldeſt <hi>Daughter</hi> marryed to<note n="i" place="margin">Speed. <hi>1111.</hi> Holl. <hi>1099.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Guilford Dudley,</hi> and was with him <hi>Beheaded</hi> about 5 <hi>Mary. Katharine</hi> his ſecond <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was marryed to <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Seymore,</hi> Eldeſt Sonne to the Duke of <hi>Somerſet, Mary</hi> his third <hi>Daughter</hi> marryed to <hi>Martin Keyes,</hi> and dyed without <hi>Iſſue.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">God. f. <hi>244.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ellenor,</hi> ſecond <hi>Daughter</hi> to <hi>Charles Brandon,</hi> marryed to <hi>Clifford</hi> Earle of <hi>Cumberland</hi> a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <hi>Family,</hi> lately extinct.</p>
            <p>The Queen <hi>Dowager</hi> dying, <hi>Charles Brandon</hi> Marryed the <hi>Daughter</hi> and <hi>Heire</hi> of the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Ereſby,</hi> who <hi>inrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> him with two ſonnes, <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Charles:</hi> but the Duke dying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 36. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. left his <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Eſtate</hi> to his ſonne <hi>Henry,</hi> who enjoyed it untill 5. <hi>E.</hi> 6. then <hi>dying</hi> of the <hi>Sweating ſickneſſe,</hi> left them to his brother<note n="l" place="margin">Holl. f. <hi>1066.</hi> God. f. <hi>244</hi> Speed. <hi>1100.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Charles,</hi> who only lived to be his brothers <hi>Heire,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Suffolke;</hi> and the ſame day, and of the ſame <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe</hi> which his brother dyed, and with him the <hi>Title, Name,</hi> and Family of <hi>Brandon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 13. gives the <hi>Monaſtery</hi> of <hi>Sibeton</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and the <hi>Chauntry</hi> of <hi>Cobham</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:113568:14"/>
               <hi>Kent,</hi> to the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> ſince which time how heavy the <hi>hand of Juſtice</hi> hath fallen upon theſe <hi>Noble Families,</hi> informe thy ſelfe from our <hi>Annalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider next the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Somerſet, Protector</hi> to <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, <hi>Godwin</hi> in his <hi>Annalls</hi> ſaith,<note n="m" place="margin">Godwin. fo. <hi>252.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He was a juſt and pious man, a zealous Reformer of Religion, a faithfull preſerver of the King and Common-wealth, ſave that with the common Error of the time, his hands were deep in ſacriledge.</hi> In the firſt yeare of<note n="n" place="margin">Stat. <hi>1.</hi> E. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> the 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, he procured the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of ſome <hi>Chantryes, Free-Chappells,</hi> and <hi>Hospitalls,</hi> left undiſſolved by <hi>H.</hi> 8. In the third yeare, he permits (if not procures) his Brother <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Seymore,</hi> untri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (ſaith<note n="o" place="margin">Godwin. fo. <hi>227.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Goodwin</hi>) to be <hi>attainted</hi> by <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſhortly after, (not <hi>unblamed</hi>) ſigned a <hi>Warrant</hi> for his <hi>Execution,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Brother loſt his <hi>Head,</hi> and he a <hi>friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare his <hi>zeale</hi> to <hi>Reformation,</hi> addes new <hi>ſacriledge</hi> to his former; for he <hi>defaces</hi> ſome part of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Stowes Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls.</note> 
               <hi>Church,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the <hi>Charnell-houſe,</hi> and a <hi>Chappell</hi> by it, into dwelling <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>demoliſhing</hi> ſome <hi>Monuments</hi> there, he turnes out the <hi>old bones</hi> to ſeek new <hi>Sepulchers</hi> in the <hi>Fields:</hi> next he <hi>deſtroyes</hi> the <hi>Steeple,</hi> and part of the Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Johns</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and with the <hi>ſtone</hi> beginneth to <hi>build</hi> his <hi>houſe</hi> in the<note n="*" place="margin">Somerſet Houſe.</note> 
               <hi>Strand,</hi> but as the <hi>leproſie</hi> with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> with us the <hi>curſe</hi> of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> cleaves to the <hi>Conſecrated ſtone,</hi> and they become <hi>inſucceſſefull,</hi> ſo as the <hi>Builder</hi> doth not finiſh his <hi>Houſe,</hi> nor doth his Sonne inherit it. In the fifth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, the <hi>Duke</hi> was <hi>indicted,</hi> and found <hi>guilty</hi> of <hi>Felony,</hi> which was (ſaith <hi>Hollinſhead</hi>) upon a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made the third and fourth of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and ſince <hi>repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> whereby to attempt the <hi>death</hi> of a <hi>Privy Councellour,</hi> is <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony,</hi> (<hi>Godwin</hi> ſaith) upon the Statute of 3. <hi>H.</hi> 7. but erroniouſly that not extending to <hi>Barons;</hi> it is obſervable that this <hi>Law</hi> was but the yeare before paſſed by <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>himſelfe</hi> the only <hi>man</hi> that ever <hi>ſuffered</hi> by it. The Statute being ſince repealed;<note n="q" place="margin">Godwin. fo. <hi>247.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Godwin</hi> obſerves and wonders that he omitted to pray the benefit of his <hi>Booke,</hi> as if <hi>Heavens</hi> would not that he that had ſpoyled his <hi>Church,</hi> ſhould be ſaved by his <hi>Clergy;</hi> and it is obſervable that in the Raigne of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, none of the <hi>Nobility</hi> dyes under the <hi>Rod of Juſtice,</hi> but the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Somerſet</hi> and his Brother the <hi>Lord Admirall,</hi> all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles</hi> the <hi>King</hi> had, and their Crimes comparatively were not <hi>haynous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did theſe men <hi>dye</hi> the common <hi>death</hi> of all <hi>men,</hi> or are they
<pb facs="tcp:113568:15"/>viſited after the <hi>manner</hi> of all <hi>men?</hi> if not, beleeve they <hi>provoked the Lord,</hi> and conſider, that if they <hi>ſinned</hi> in the firſt <hi>prophanation,</hi> thou that continueſt their <hi>act,</hi> can'ſt not be <hi>innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here thou mayeſt ſee God obſerving a <hi>Decorum</hi> in his <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> the Iſſue of the <hi>Conqueror</hi> are ſtrangely (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt miraculouſly) <hi>ſlaine</hi> in the <hi>New-Forreſt,</hi> where their <hi>Father</hi> committed the Sacriledge. <hi>Woolſey,</hi> that by the <hi>Kings licence</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> had deſtroyed 40 <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> is by the <hi>Kings power</hi> rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and at laſt driven to ſeek <hi>entertainment,</hi> and an obſcure <hi>grave</hi> in a <hi>Monaſtery;</hi> his <hi>Agents</hi> that had thruſt themſelves into his <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious imployment,</hi> are themſelves their owne <hi>Executioners,</hi> guilty of their owne <hi>Blouds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, that willingly permitted the <hi>ſpoyle of</hi> 40 <hi>poore Monaſteries,</hi> to erect two <hi>Rich Colledges,</hi> is himſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to <hi>Plunder</hi> his owne <hi>rich Church,</hi> to preſerve his poore decayed <hi>Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> commit their <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge</hi> by Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and by Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> they periſh every one by the <hi>Sword,</hi> wherewith he ſtrikes.</p>
            <p>And ſince in the <hi>Acts of Parliament for diſſolution</hi> of <hi>Monaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> was involved either by their <hi>Perſonall conſent</hi> as <hi>Barons,</hi> or their <hi>implicite conſent</hi> in the <hi>repreſentative body</hi> in the Houſe of Commons, we have juſt cauſe to <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>pray,</hi> leaſt <hi>God</hi> ſtill obſerving his <hi>order,</hi> and turning our <hi>Artillery</hi> upon our ſelves, ſhould make uſe of a <hi>Parliament</hi> (whereby our <hi>Fathers</hi> robbed him) to deſtroy us their Children.</p>
            <p>I have here given thee inſtance only of ſuch as were the firſt <hi>Actors</hi> in the <hi>Violation</hi> and <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> leaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou ſhouldeſt thinke the <hi>crime</hi> and <hi>puniſhment</hi> endeth with them. Conſider with me the <hi>condition</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> both of our <hi>Common-wealth</hi> in generall, and of <hi>Private Families</hi> in particular before the <hi>Diſſolutions,</hi> and obſerve them after, and we ſhall find juſt cauſe to thinke there is a <hi>curſed thing</hi> amongſt us; For while our <hi>Religious houſes</hi> ſtood, they (imploying their <hi>Revenues</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their <hi>Donors</hi> direction) opened wide their <hi>Hospitable gates</hi> to all <hi>Commers,</hi> and without the charge of a <hi>Reckoning,</hi> welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all <hi>Travailers,</hi> untill the Statute of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. reſtrained and limited them, and caſting their <hi>Bread</hi> upon the <hi>Waters,</hi> they relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the <hi>Neighbouring poore</hi> without the care of the two next <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:113568:15"/>of Peace,</hi> or the <hi>curſe of a Penall Law;</hi> while they ſtood, the <hi>younger Children</hi> both of Lords and Commons were provided; for without the <hi>ruine</hi> of their <hi>Fathers Eſtate,</hi> or (almoſt) a charge to their <hi>Parents,</hi> and not left (as now) often to an <hi>unworthy, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous,</hi> and <hi>vitious</hi> courſe of <hi>life:</hi> we had then no <hi>new Lawes,</hi> (the off-ſpring of <hi>new Vices</hi>) to erect <hi>Houſes</hi> of <hi>correction</hi> for <hi>lewd</hi> and<note n="r" place="margin">Vid. <hi>43.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vagrant Perſons,</hi> to provide ſtock to bind poore Children <hi>Prentiſes,</hi> or to make <hi>weekly Leavyes,</hi> to maintaine the <hi>weake, lame, indigent,</hi> and <hi>impotent People,</hi> to our new charge of an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Subſidie</hi> at leaſt, for theſe were provided for, thoſe preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>charity</hi> of our <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> and then the <hi>Families</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> of our <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> continued long through very many <hi>deſcents.</hi> But when <hi>covetous ſacriledge</hi> got the upper hand of <hi>ſuperstitious charity,</hi> and deſtroyed all our <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> all our <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> the preſervers of <hi>Learning,</hi> both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane,</hi> by their <hi>Learned workes</hi> and <hi>laborious Manuſcripts,</hi> the <hi>ſuppreſſors</hi> of <hi>Vice,</hi> by their <hi>ſtrict, regular,</hi> and <hi>exemplar life:</hi> though ſome, nay many among them Sonnes of <hi>Ely,</hi> made the <hi>offerings of the Lord to ſtinck before the People.</hi> Then all their <hi>Houſes,</hi> all their <hi>Lands, Appropriations, Tithes,</hi> and <hi>Oblations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Par. Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es 9232. <hi>Cam. Brit fo.</hi> 162. 9284. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. 3845.</note> comming into the <hi>Kings hands,</hi> Policy (to prevent a <hi>reſtitution</hi>) diſtributes them among the <hi>Layety,</hi> ſome the <hi>King exchanges,</hi> ſome he <hi>ſells,</hi> others he <hi>gives away;</hi> and by this meanes, (like the <hi>duſt flung up by Moſes</hi>) they preſently diſperſe all the <hi>Kingdome</hi> over, and at once becomes <hi>curſes</hi> both upon the <hi>Families</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the <hi>owners;</hi> they often <hi>vitiouſly</hi> ſpending on their <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate occaſions,</hi> what was <hi>piouſly</hi> intended for <hi>publique Devotion;</hi> inſomuch that within <hi>Twenty yeares</hi> next after the <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> more of our <hi>Nobility</hi> and their Children have been <hi>attainted,</hi> and <hi>dyed</hi> under the <hi>Sword of Juſtice,</hi> then did from the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> to the <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> being almoſt five hundred yeares; ſo as if thou examine the <hi>Liſt</hi> of the <hi>Barons</hi> in the <hi>Parliament</hi> of the 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. thou ſhalt find very few of them, whoſe Sonne doth at this day <hi>inherit</hi> his <hi>Fathers Title</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and of theſe few, many to whom the <hi>Kings favour</hi> hath reſtored what the <hi>rigorous Law</hi> of <hi>attainder</hi> took both <hi>Dignity, Lands,</hi> and <hi>Poſterity.</hi> And doubleſſe the <hi>Commons</hi> have drunke deep in this <hi>Cup of deadly Wine,</hi> but they being more <hi>numerous,</hi> and leſſe <hi>eminent,</hi> are not ſo obvious to obſervation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:16"/>
            <p> Thou haſt ſeen the inſucceſſe of <hi>H.</hi> 8. and his <hi>Family,</hi> and mayeſt obſerve his <hi>ſacrilegious wealth</hi> not to thrive better.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>den. fo. <hi>163.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cambden</hi> in his <hi>Britannia,</hi> ſaith, that in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 8. after the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the leſſer <hi>Houſes,</hi> there were remaining 645 <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> (<hi>Monuments</hi> of our <hi>Anceſtors piety</hi>) built to the <hi>honour of God,</hi> and <hi>propagation</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and the <hi>releefe of the Poore,</hi> as alſo 96 <hi>Colledges,</hi> (beſides thoſe in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi>) 110 <hi>Hospitalls,</hi> and 2374 <hi>Chantryes</hi> and <hi>Free-Chappells.</hi> All which, except ſome few <hi>Colledges, Free-Chappells,</hi> and <hi>Chantryes,</hi> with all their <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Wealth,</hi> came to <hi>H.</hi> 8. the <hi>Annuall value</hi> of the <hi>Lands</hi> then being very <hi>Vaſt,</hi> their <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Perſonall Eſtate exceeding great,</hi> beſides the <hi>Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of <hi>Shrine</hi> ineſtimable, when the <hi>Pearle, Gold,</hi> and <hi>pretious ſtones</hi> of one <hi>Shrine</hi> filled two<note n="t" place="margin">Godwin. fo. <hi>159.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cheſts</hi> ſo as each took eight <hi>ſtrong men</hi> (ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cambden</hi>) to carry it.</p>
            <p>And although the diſſolving of <hi>Chantryes, Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Free-Chappels,</hi> in the 37. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. his Raigne did not yeeld him a <hi>Crop</hi> equall to the <hi>Vintage</hi> of his former <hi>Reformations;</hi> yet was his <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest</hi> better then the <hi>Gleanings</hi> of <hi>Ruth,</hi> though among full <hi>ſheaves.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Speed fol <hi>1011.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Speed</hi> ſaith he had 12 <hi>Barrells</hi> filled with <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver,</hi> which <hi>Cardinall Woolſey</hi> provided for the <hi>Pope, Godwin</hi> remembers 118840<hi rend="sup">l</hi> he had of the <hi>Clergy</hi> for their <hi>Fine</hi> in a <hi>Premunire,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>great benefit</hi> of <hi>Forfeitures</hi> that accrued by the <hi>attainders</hi> of many <hi>great men,</hi> and the multitude of <hi>Lones, Taxes,</hi> and <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> he received from his Subjects, being more (ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cambden,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Howes</hi>) then all the <hi>Kings</hi> had in 500 yeares before; yet all this acceſſe of <hi>wealth,</hi> added to that <hi>Maſſe</hi> of 5300000<hi rend="sup">l</hi> left him in ready mony by his <hi>Father,</hi> as appeares by the <hi>Cloſe-Roll</hi> of 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. (ſaith Sir <hi>Edw.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cook.</hi> Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Courts. <hi>fol.</hi> 198.</note> 
               <hi>Cooke</hi>) could not preſerve him from <hi>want,</hi> (the certaine attendant on <hi>ſacrilegious wealth</hi>) wherewith he is ſo <hi>ſore preſſed,</hi> that about the 36 yeare of his Raigne, of all the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> he alone, Coynes not only baſe<note n="*" place="margin">Non tantum ſtanneam cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prinam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſed coreaceam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuaiam ſolus omni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regum Ang procude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs coactus est.</note> 
               <hi>Tinne</hi> and <hi>Coppar,</hi> but <hi>Lether mony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is obſerved that ſince the acceſſion of <hi>Abbies</hi> and <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations</hi> to the <hi>Crowne,</hi> even the <hi>Crowne Lands</hi> (which formerly have been thought ſufficient to ſupport the ordinary <hi>charge</hi> of the <hi>Crowne,</hi>) are now ſo waſted <hi>(abſit invidia dictis)</hi> as they will ſcarce defray the ordinary charge of the <hi>Kings houſhold.</hi> And while ſuch bitter <hi>ſtreames</hi> flow from <hi>ſacrilegious Wells,</hi> though digged by
<pb facs="tcp:113568:16"/>
               <hi>Kings</hi> Subjects, that fin their <hi>Ciſternes</hi> from thence, cannot expect to drinke <hi>ſweet Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reynerus</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Apoſtolatus Benedict. in Ang. fo. <hi>227.</hi> &amp; <hi>228.</hi>
               </note> tells us, and upon good credit, that at the <hi>diſſolution H.</hi> 8. divided part of the <hi>Church spoyles</hi> among 260 <hi>Gent.</hi> of <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> in one part of <hi>England,</hi> and at the ſame time <hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> rewards the ſervice of <hi>Twenty</hi> of his <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> with the grant of 40<hi rend="sup">l</hi> a yeare out of his own <hi>Inheritance,</hi> and that while not ſixty of the <hi>Kings Donees,</hi> had a <hi>Sonne</hi> owning his <hi>Fathers Eſtate,</hi> every one of the <hi>Dukes,</hi> hath the ſonne of his own <hi>Loynes,</hi> Flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in his <hi>Fathers Inheritance,</hi> and that he could have ſet downe their ſeverall names had conveniency required it.</p>
            <p>Thou maiſt here expect I ſhould obſerve the <hi>ill ſucceſſe</hi> of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular private men, <hi>poſſeſſors</hi> and <hi>owners</hi> of <hi>Impropriations</hi> and <hi>Scites</hi> of <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> but to ſet downe all, would make the <hi>porch</hi> much bigger then the <hi>Houſe,</hi> a diſproportion, I feare, among other <hi>Errors</hi> I am already <hi>guilty</hi> of, and to ſet downe but a few, would diſpleaſe thee, while I diſcover the nakedneſſe only of <hi>thee,</hi> thy <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> or <hi>Friends.</hi> But doe thou, and let every man obſerve, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Impropriations</hi> and <hi>Religious houſes;</hi> in a ſhort time <hi>change</hi> and <hi>ſhift</hi> their <hi>owners,</hi> like the <hi>Arke</hi> not reſting, either with the men of<note n="z" place="margin">Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Aſhdod, Gath,</hi> nor <hi>Eckron,</hi> but <hi>wearies</hi> them out with <hi>Emrods,</hi> and <hi>Mice; curſes</hi> upon their <hi>perſons</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſtates,</hi> but returned to <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemeth</hi> and <hi>Kiriahjearim</hi> to its own place, to the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Levite,</hi> not only <hi>Obed-Edom,</hi> but even all <hi>Iſrael</hi> is bleſſed.</p>
            <p>And that thou maiſt neither <hi>doubt,</hi> nor yet <hi>wonder,</hi> at the <hi>inſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe</hi> of <hi>Sacrilegious Perſons,</hi> firſt weighing what <hi>David</hi> prayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that did but ſay,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſalm. 83.</note> 
               <hi>Let us take to our ſelves the houſes of God into our poſſeſſion;</hi> next remember, the <hi>many</hi> and <hi>grievous Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> imprecated by <hi>Founders</hi> of <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> and thoſe ſeconded by their <hi>ſpirituall Mother</hi> the<note n="b" place="margin">17. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Church,</hi> ſhe injoyned it by the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Parent,</hi> in ſeverall <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and canſt thou hope good from their <hi>bleſſings,</hi> and not <hi>feare evill</hi> from <hi>their Curſes?</hi> If thou thinkeſt the <hi>Founders Idolatrous,</hi> the <hi>Church Popiſh,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>curſes</hi> not regardable, let that in<note n="c" place="margin">Ezra. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ezra</hi> rectify thy <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> where thou ſhalt finde <hi>Darius</hi> finiſhing what <hi>Cyrus</hi> began, the ſecond <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then reſtoring what <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had taken, all the <hi>Golden</hi> and <hi>Silver Veſſell,</hi> then he gives <hi>Cattell, Corne, Wine, Oyle,</hi> &amp;c. for <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> and addes this <hi>curſe</hi> upon the violators,<note n="d" place="margin">Ezra. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>And the God that hath cauſed his name to dwell there, destroy all, King and People, that put to their hand, to alter and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb facs="tcp:113568:17"/>this houſe of God,</hi> which is at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there thou maiſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve both an <hi>Idolater giving,</hi> and a <hi>Heathen curſing,</hi> yet is his <hi>guift</hi> acceptable, and his <hi>curſe</hi> prevalent, for thou ſhalt find <hi>Antiochus</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Mac. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanes</hi> his Armies <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> himſelfe <hi>dejected</hi> and <hi>complaining</hi> even to <hi>death,</hi> of his great <hi>tribulation</hi> and <hi>miſery,</hi> acknowledgeth that they <hi>befall</hi> him for his <hi>Evill</hi> done at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for he took thence the <hi>Golden Altar,</hi> the <hi>Table</hi> of the <hi>Shew-bread,</hi> the <hi>veſſells</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>ſilver,</hi> as thou maiſt read in the 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.<note n="f" place="margin">Mac. 1.1.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>Mac.</hi> and himſelfe <hi>dying</hi> of a moſt <hi>loathſome diſeaſe.</hi> And ſhortly after his ſonne<note n="g" place="margin">Mac. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>Antiochus Eupater</hi> is <hi>ſlaine,</hi> and in the ſame Chapter thou maiſt obſerve <hi>Nicanor</hi> threatning to burne up the <hi>Temple,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he firſt, &amp; after, all his <hi>Army</hi> is <hi>ſlain,</hi> not one <hi>eſcapeth,</hi> the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>right hand</hi> of <hi>Nicanor,</hi> which had been lift up againſt the<note n="h" place="margin">2. Mac. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> is <hi>cut off</hi> &amp; <hi>hung up</hi> towards <hi>Jeruſalem. Heliodorus</hi> is ſent to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> by <hi>Seleucus</hi> King of <hi>Aſia,</hi> to take the <hi>Treaſure</hi> out of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and while in the <hi>Temple</hi> diſpoſing the <hi>treaſure,</hi> he is ſmitten of <hi>God,</hi> and ready to <hi>dye,</hi> untill <hi>Onias</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> at the intreaty of <hi>Friends,</hi> offers <hi>ſacrifice</hi> for him, and obtaines his <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> returnes to the <hi>King,</hi> and declares what befell him, the <hi>King,</hi> yet thirſting for the <hi>Money</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> would ſend another, and demanding of <hi>Heliodorus</hi> whom; he anſwered, thy <hi>enemy</hi> or a<note n="i" place="margin">2. Mac. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> for if he eſcape with <hi>life,</hi> he ſhall be ſure to be <hi>ſcourged,</hi> ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of <hi>Sacriledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Ma. 8.33.</note> 
               <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> attempting to burne the <hi>Temple,</hi> ſet <hi>fire</hi> on the <hi>gates,</hi> and after is himſelfe <hi>burnt</hi> by the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="l" place="margin">2. Mac. 4.39.</note> 
               <hi>Lyſimacus,</hi> called the <hi>Church-Rober,</hi> commits many<note n="m" place="margin">2. Mac. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſaeriledges</hi> by the <hi>instigation</hi> of <hi>Menelaus;</hi> is <hi>ſlain</hi> by the<note n="n" place="margin">2. Mac. 13.5678.</note> 
               <hi>treaſury</hi> of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and his <hi>inſtigator,</hi> is by <hi>Antiochus</hi> put to a ſtrange <hi>Death.</hi> For in <hi>Berea</hi> was a <hi>Tower</hi> 50 <hi>Cubites</hi> high, full of <hi>Aſhes,</hi> with a <hi>Round in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> that went downe into the <hi>Aſhes,</hi> wherein they put <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious perſons,</hi> and <hi>Menelaus</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Text</hi>) having committed <hi>ſinnes</hi> againſt the <hi>Altar,</hi> whoſe <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Aſhes</hi> are <hi>holy,</hi> receives his <hi>Death</hi> by <hi>Aſhes,</hi> not having a <hi>Buriall</hi> in the <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alcimus</hi> even in his Act of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> while pulling downe the<note n="o" place="margin">1. Ma. 9.55.</note> 
               <hi>Temple</hi> walls, is ſtuck with a <hi>Palſie</hi> and dyes in torment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jaſon</hi> that burnt the <hi>Porch, Demetrius</hi> and other <hi>Sacrilegious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> all fall under the ſingle <hi>Curſe</hi> of one <hi>Heathen:</hi> and doeſt thou think to ſcape ſo many <hi>Curſes</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> which twice a yeare (being ſo directed by <hi>Parliament</hi>) curſes the violators of <hi>Churehes,</hi> and <hi>Church Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113568:17"/>
            <p> But if theſe judgements and examples cannot fright thy <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſoule</hi> from <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> but thy deſires of being <hi>rich</hi> ſway thee, then let thy provident <hi>good husbandry</hi> ſo far prevaile with thee, as not to meddle with <hi>God's</hi> and the <hi>Levites portion,</hi> the <hi>Church pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony;</hi> but even out of <hi>Temporall</hi> and <hi>Wordly</hi> reſpects for the good of thee, thy Children, Neighbours, and poſterity forbear (what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ſoever are made) the diſſolving <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> and <hi>Deaneries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember that of all the ſpecious <hi>pretences</hi> and large <hi>promiſes</hi> made both by <hi>Woolſey</hi> and <hi>H</hi> 8. upon their ſeverall <hi>Diſſolutions,</hi> not any one of them is performed; <hi>Woolſey</hi> neither ſettles his <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,</hi> nor <hi>H.</hi> 8. eaſe his Subjects of <hi>Loanes, Taxes</hi> and <hi>Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> maintaines no <hi>Souldiers</hi> for defence of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> nor diſpoſes the <hi>Lands,</hi> as the Statute directs, to the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> nor indeed to the <hi>profit</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> if thou weigheſt the <hi>profit</hi> and <hi>conveniency</hi> the <hi>Publique</hi> had before, with what they have now, the <hi>burdens</hi> and <hi>charges</hi> that we have ſince <hi>groaned under,</hi> and formerly not knowne; but that <hi>evill</hi> is only to be <hi>lamented,</hi> not <hi>cured,</hi> may we happily prevent the like for the future.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Revenue</hi> of <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> &amp; <hi>Deaneries,</hi> clogg'd with long <hi>Leaſes</hi> under ſmall <hi>Rents,</hi> can give but little help in Pay of the <hi>Vaſt Publique Debt;</hi> and that with greater <hi>damage</hi> to the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> then the draine of <hi>private Purſes</hi> can be, for this only wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens <hi>particulars,</hi> and for the preſent; that <hi>ruines generally,</hi> and for ever for the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is not with us (as with the <hi>Jewes</hi>) intayled upon <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sonnes: but <hi>thine, mine, his,</hi> the <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>Nobles, Gentlemen,</hi> and <hi>Peſants,</hi> while all alike able, are all alike intereſted in the <hi>Churches preferment,</hi> which in our <hi>Nation</hi> is the ſole <hi>Spure,</hi> the only <hi>reward</hi> for <hi>Learning,</hi> and happily provides for thoſe which otherwiſe would be <hi>burdens</hi> to their <hi>Parent,</hi> miſchiefes to the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> while <hi>Colledges, Biſhopricks,</hi> and <hi>Deaneries,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, thou and thy <hi>Neighbour</hi> continueſt thy Leaſe at ſmall Rents, thy Sonnes and Grand-child renues it at eaſie <hi>Fines,</hi> and by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed <hi>charity</hi> of thy Eccleſiaſtick <hi>Landlord,</hi> thy continued <hi>Leaſe,</hi> not clogged with <hi>Liveries, Primer ſeiſins,</hi> and <hi>Wardſhips</hi> (the <hi>curſe</hi> of <hi>Tenures</hi>) equalls, if not betters an <hi>Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Colledges, Biſhopricks,</hi> and <hi>Deaneries</hi> diſſolved, their <hi>Lands,</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> muſt be aſſigned (as were <hi>Monaſteries</hi> and <hi>impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>) to this <hi>Lord</hi> or that <hi>Courtier,</hi> or to that or this <hi>Committee-man,</hi> and then thy <hi>rent</hi> (if thou beeſt continued <hi>Tenant</hi>) muſt be <hi>racked</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113568:18"/>to the <hi>higheſt rate,</hi> 'till thou ruined by <hi>paying</hi> ſo great a <hi>Rent,</hi> thy <hi>Landlord,</hi> by receiving the <hi>Church-Revenue,</hi> and all wee, while under the <hi>rodde</hi> for the firſt, be guilty of a ſecond <hi>Nationall Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> for ſhall we not believe this <hi>Nationall Warre</hi> and <hi>generall ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine,</hi> to be for a <hi>generall</hi> and <hi>Nationall ſinne,</hi> which cannot be the <hi>acts</hi> of <hi>private</hi> and <hi>partisular</hi> men though infinitely <hi>multiplyed,</hi> but muſt proceed from the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>univerſall Nation,</hi> and ſuch I know none, but that <hi>Sacriledge</hi> of deſtroying ſome <hi>Churches,</hi> ſome <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells,</hi> and <hi>robbing</hi> others of their <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Indowments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> which is not only <hi>connived</hi> at, but made lawfull by our <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> to which even every one in the whole <hi>Kingdome,</hi> by our own <hi>Law,</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>privie</hi> and <hi>conſenting,</hi> and thereby <hi>guilty</hi> of the <hi>ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Sacriledge,</hi> and then doe thou <hi>judge,</hi> whether another <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>diſſolution</hi> (which God prevent) will not be a <hi>ſteppe</hi> to another <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Sacriledge,</hi> and that to another <hi>Scourge;</hi> therefore if <hi>Hophny</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi> have <hi>ſinned,</hi> and <hi>Eli</hi> not reproved them, let them all three <hi>dye,</hi> yea in one <hi>day,</hi> for we have <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>preſident</hi> for that, but neither, that the order ſhould <hi>periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, doe thou conſider, that while we deteine <hi>Tithes</hi> from the <hi>Church,</hi> and forbid <hi>Aaron</hi> to counſell <hi>Moſes,</hi> whether we <hi>trespaſſe</hi> not upon the <hi>Property</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſhall not <hi>God viſit for theſe things,</hi> when thou with thy <hi>Sword</hi> maintaineſt againſt thy <hi>Brother</hi> (If not againſt thy <hi>King</hi>) thy <hi>Property of Goods,</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Subject?</hi> But that God may withdraw his <hi>Viſitations,</hi> and thou <hi>ſheath</hi> thy <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> receive the <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Tribute</hi> due from His Subjects, His Subjects their <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> from the <hi>King;</hi> May <hi>King</hi> and Subject agree to returne <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> what is due to them, and may the firſt <hi>Acter,</hi> in reſtoring <hi>God</hi> his <hi>right,</hi> be by <hi>God</hi> firſt reſtored to his <hi>owne right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other things (and theſe more perfectly) I would have obſerved to thee, had not <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Records and I been at ſo great a diſtance. Let therefore thy goodneſſe excuſe, what is either omitted or miſtaken by not viewing the Records, and for my other Errors, I beg thy pardon, as I would have done for medling with this <hi>ſubject,</hi> fitter for a <hi>Pulpit</hi> then my <hi>Pen;</hi> but I have often heard it <hi>ſlighted</hi> from the <hi>Levite,</hi> as Preaching his owne <hi>profit,</hi> and therefore thought it might take better (though worſe delivered) from a <hi>Lay hand,</hi> no wayes concerned by it, but in the generall Calamity of our <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>CLEM: SPELMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113568:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>De non temerandis Eccleſiis.</hi> OF THE RIGHTS AND RESPECT DVE VNTO THE <hi>CHVRCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nſomuch as the rights and duties that belong to our Churches are in effect contained under the name of a Rectory or Parſonage: I will firſt define, what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Rectory or Parſonage to be, according to the uſuall forme and manner thereof.</p>
            <p>A Rectory or Parſonage, is a<note n="a" place="margin">Plowd. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Impedit per Grendom, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Spirituall living,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Rectory what it is.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of <hi>Land, Tythe,</hi> and other<note n="b" place="margin">Oblatio eſt omne quod ex. hihetur in cultu Det, Tho. Aq. <hi>2.7.</hi> q. <hi>85.3.3.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> Vrban <hi>in his epiſt.</hi> Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Concil. <hi>And Lands are ſo termed,</hi> Ezek. <hi>45.1. and Tythes,</hi> Num. <hi>18.24. So alſo the Caroniſts and Civilians expound them,</hi> Concil. Aurel. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Burcha. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>129.</hi> &amp; <hi>143.</hi> Et Lex. Jarid. in verb. oblatio.</note> 
               <hi>Oblations</hi> of the people,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.28.</note> ſeperate or dedicate to God in any <hi>Congregation,</hi> for the<note n="d" place="margin">Touching divine vvorſhip and works of charity.</note> ſervice of his Church there, and for the maintenance of the <hi>Governour</hi> or <hi>Miniſter</hi> thereof, to whoſe charge the ſame is committed.</p>
            <p>By this <hi>definition</hi> it appeares, that the ordinary living or revenew of a Parſonage, is of 3 ſorts: the one in Land, commonly called the Glebe: another in Tithe, which is a ſet and regular part of our goods rendered to God. The third, in other offerings and oblations beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon God and his Church, by the people, either in ſuch arbitrable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113568:19"/>proportion as their owne devotion moveth them, or as the lawes or cuſtomes of particular places doe require them.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Tithes how due.</note> Though I invert order a little, I will firſt ſpeake of Tithes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is Gods ancient demaine, and the nobler part of this his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, founded primarily, upon the Law of nature, (as the other be alſo after their manner,) For the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> teacheth us that God is to be honoured: and that the honour due unto him, cannot be performed without <hi>Miniſters,</hi> nor the <hi>Miniſters</hi> attend their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction without maintenance. And therefore ſeeing God is the ſupreme Lord and poſſeſſor of all,<note place="margin">Gen. 14.19.</note> and giveth all things unto us that we are maintained with; it is our duty both in point of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Gratui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> to render ſomething backe againe unto him, as acknowledging this his ſupremacy and bounty; as honouring him for his <hi>goodneſſe;</hi> as a teſtimony of the worſhip, love, and ſervice we owe him; and laſtly, as a meanes whereby theſe duties and ſervices may be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to him. This, I ſay, the very <hi>Law of Nature</hi> teacheth us to doe: and this the <hi>Law of GOD</hi> requireth alſo at our hands: but what the <hi>ſet</hi> portion of our goods ſhould be, that thus we ought to render backe unto God, I cannot ſay the Law of<note n="a" place="margin">Yet there be divers naturall reaſons that commend this number (for this purpoſe) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other.</note> 
               <hi>Nature</hi> hath determined that. But the wiſedome of all the Nations of the World, the practice of all Ages, the example of the Patriarches<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20.</note> ABRAHAM and<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22.</note> JACOB, the<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.30. <hi>and</hi> 32. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.6, <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>Malachy</hi> 3.10</note> approbation and commandement of Almighty GOD himſelfe, and the conſtant<note n="e" place="margin">Declared by the Fathers and Counſels.</note> reſolution of his CHVRCH univerſally, hath taught and preſcribed us to render unto him the <hi>Tenth part:</hi> and that this <hi>Tenth</hi> part or <hi>Tithe,</hi> being thus aſſigned unto him, leaveth now to be of the nature of the other <hi>nine parts</hi> (which are given us for our worldly neceſſities) and becometh as a thing dedicate and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate unto God. For it is ſaid, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. <hi>All the tythe of the land, both of the ſeed of the greund, and of the fruit of the trees, is the Lords:</hi> yea more then ſo, <hi>It is holy unto the Lord.</hi> And againe (v. 32.) <hi>Every Tithe of Bullocke, and Sheepe, and of all that goeth under the rodde, the tenth ſhall be holy unto the Lord.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>holy unto the Lord;</hi> not that they were like the <hi>ſanctified</hi> things of the <hi>Temple,</hi> which none might touch but the <hi>Anointed Prieſts</hi>) but <hi>Holy and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate</hi> from the uſe and injury of ſecular perſons, and to be diſpoſed onely, to and for the peculiar-ſervice and peculiar Servants of GOD. And therefore in the 28. verſe, it is ſaid, <hi>to be ſeperate from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, becauſe it is ſeperate, and ſet apart unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113568:19"/> 3. But ſome happily will ſay, that this uſe of <hi>Tithing</hi> riſes out of the <hi>Leviticall</hi> Law, and ſo ended with it.<note place="margin">Tithes original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not Leviticall</note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that it was received and practiſed by <hi>Abraham</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> vovvet to give tithes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. And <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhevveth he per formeth his vovv. <hi>Antiquit. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> divers hundred yeares before it came to the <hi>Levites.</hi> For it is ſaid that <hi>Abraham</hi> gave <hi>tithe</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedeck, Gen.</hi> 14.20. And that <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi</hi> himſelfe paid <hi>tithe</hi> alſo in the <hi>loines</hi> of <hi>Abraham, Heb.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck</hi> was the image of CHRIST, and his Church; <hi>Abraham</hi> of the congregation of the Faithfull. Therefore though <hi>Levi</hi> received tithes afterward, by a particular grant from GOD, for the time: yet now he paid them generally with the congregation, in the loines of <hi>Abraham</hi> unto the Prieſthood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> here perſonated by <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck:</hi> which being perpetuall, and an image of this of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> may well note unto us, that this duty of <hi>Tythe,</hi> ought alſo to be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall.</hi> And therefore<note n="b" place="margin">Hem <hi>35.</hi> in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Abraham herein was OVR tutor:</hi> not the <hi>tutor</hi> of the <hi>Jewes.</hi> And inſomuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> paid it not to a <hi>Prieſt</hi> that offered a <hi>Leviticall Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Bullocks</hi> and <hi>Goates:</hi> but to him that gave the <hi>Elements</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the Goſpell,<note n="c" place="margin">The Scripture onely mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by <hi>Melchi ſedeck</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham:</hi> But <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> ſhevveth, that he gave him alſo divers other rich gifts, <hi>Antr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine:</hi> it may alſo well intimate unto us, to what kinde of <hi>Prieſt</hi> we are to pay our <hi>tithes:</hi> namely to him that miniſtreth unto us the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine,</hi> which are onely thoſe of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and not the <hi>Leviticall Prieſts.</hi> So that our <hi>tythe</hi> paid in this kind, cannot be ſaid <hi>Leviticall:</hi> as alſo for that the <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall tythes,</hi> were onely of things<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 37.30, <hi>&amp;</hi> 31.</note> renewing and increaſing: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> paid them of <hi>all:</hi> as if they had followed the commandement of the <hi>Apoſtle; Let him that is taught in the Word, make him that hath taught him partaker of</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ALL his goods Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p>God alſo requireth this duty of <hi>tythe</hi> by his owne mouth, as of old belonging unto him, before the <hi>Levites</hi> were called to the ſervice of the <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> and before they were named in Scripture. For they are not named till <hi>Exodus.</hi> 38.21. And it is ſaid in <hi>Exodus</hi> 22.29. <hi>Thine abundance of thy liquor ſhalt thou not keepe backe:</hi> meaning <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> and therefore <hi>Hierome</hi> doubteth not ſo to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it; <hi>Thy Tithes</hi> and <hi>firſt Fruits ſhalt thou not keepe backe.</hi> And in this manner of ſpeech, the word <hi>Keepe backe,</hi> ſheweth that it was a thing formerly due unto GOD: for we cannot ſay, that any thing is <hi>kept backe,</hi> or <hi>with holden</hi> that was not due before. Therefore we finde <hi>no originall</hi> commandement of giving <hi>tithe</hi> unto GOD: but upon the firſt mentioning of them in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> they are poſitively
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113568:20"/>declared to be <hi>His,</hi> as a part of <hi>His</hi> Crowne, and ancient <hi>demaine;</hi> for it is there ſaid, <hi>Cap.</hi> 27.30. <hi>All the tithe of the Land is the Lords.</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> commandeth not the people a new thing: but declareth the <hi>Right</hi> that of old belonged to GOD: namely, that <hi>All the tithes of the land was his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other phraſes of Scripture doe confirme this; for afterward when <hi>tithes</hi> came to be aſſigned to the <hi>Levites:</hi> God doth not ſay, <hi>The children of Iſrael ſhall give their tithes to the Levites:</hi> but he ſaith, <hi>Behold I have given them to the Levites.</hi> And continuing this his claime unto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vum.</hi> 18.21, 14, <hi>&amp;</hi> 26.</note> againſt thoſe that many hundred yeares after diſſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him of them: he complaineth, <hi>Malachy,</hi> 3.8. <hi>That they that withheld their tythes from the Levites, ſpoiled him himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But having handled this argument more largely in a greater worke: I will here cloſe it up with oppoſing againſt theſe kindes of Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, not onely the reverend authority of thoſe ancient and moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Pillars of the Church SS.<note n="a" place="margin">Ambroſ. in Serm. quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. in Serm. de temp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>29.</hi> &amp; alias.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Hieron in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierome,</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Chryſoſt, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſt. ad Heb. Hom. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. <hi>35.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> (who though they runne violently with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> againſt ſuch ceremonies, as they conceived to be <hi>Leviticall;</hi> yet when they come to ſpeake of <hi>Tithes,</hi> admit, maintaine, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the uſe thereof:) But alſo the reſolution of many ancient<note n="e" place="margin">Roman Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. <hi>4.</hi> Aureli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. <hi>1.</hi> Tarracon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ub Horm. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iomatricis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oletan. Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. cap <hi>6.</hi> Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alenſ. Montiſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cluſ. <hi>2.</hi> Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entinum ſub Leone <hi>4.</hi> Rotho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mag. cap. <hi>3.</hi> Cauallon. cap. <hi>18.</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Counſels, and a multitude of other<note n="f" place="margin">Origen, Tertullian, Cyprian. Gregory, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Church in their ſeverall ages: all of them concurring in opinion, that <hi>Tithes</hi> belong juſtly unto GOD; and many of them commanding all men even upon perill of their ſoules not to withhold them: which Argument<note n="†" place="margin">See this Sermon in the end of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> himſelfe pathetically maintaineth, in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sermon of his to this purpoſe. And though it be a great queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the learned, whether they bee due <hi>in quot a parte, iure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino</hi> (which requireth a larger diſcourſe) yet I never read of many that impugned them abſolutely.<note n="*" place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er Hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lieutardus,</hi> who lived about 1000 yeares after Chriſt, taught the payment of them to bee ſuperfluous and idle, and then growing deſperate, drowned himſelfe, as it were to give us a badge of this Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Touching<note n="x" place="margin">Oblations and offering.</note> 
               <hi>oblations</hi> and <hi>offerings.</hi> The <hi>Fathers</hi> under<note n="g" place="margin">Viban. Epiſt. circi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Ann. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this name accounted all things, that were given or dedicated to the ſervice of God. And in the firſt ages of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> religion (after the great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions) the <hi>Church</hi> by this meanes began ſo to abound in riches.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113568:20"/>that the good Emperours<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſtantine and Valentins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> made lavves that rich men which vvere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſupport the charges of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvealth, ſhould not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and goods vvere thereby amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</note> themſelves, were conſtrained to make lawes (not unlike our ſtatutes of <hi>Mortemaine</hi>) to reſtraine the exceſſe thereof: for feare of impoveriſhing their <hi>temporall</hi> eſtate. In thoſe dayes, many Churches had <hi>Treaſuries</hi> for keeping theſe oblations (as the Storehouſes at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> appointed by<note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hezechias,</hi> for the Temple) but the ſucceeding Ages, contracted them into Cheſts: and in theſe later times, the <hi>Parſons</hi> pocket may well enough containe them. I ſhall not need, therefore, to ſpend many words in a ſmall matter: for all the <hi>Oblations</hi> now in uſe, are in effect the <hi>two-peny</hi> Eaſter Offerings, and a few other ſuch like: which becauſe the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Appropriate Parſonages</hi> ſhall not ignorantly convert unto their owne benefit: I will ſhew them why they were paied, and why they have them.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ordained in the churches of <hi>Galatia</hi> and <hi>Corinth,</hi> that every one upon the Lords day ſhould yeild ſomewhat to God for the <hi>Saints.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</p>
            <p>But this (being once a weeke) came too thicke and too often about. Therefore in<note n="c" place="margin">Tertullian. in Apologetico.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullians</hi> time the uſe was to doe it monethly, and (at laſt) at pleaſure. But it was ever the ancient uſe of the Primitive Church (as appeareth by<note n="d" place="margin">Juſtinus in Apol. <hi>21</hi> HIſt. Eccleſ.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi>) that <hi>all</hi> that come to the holy <hi>Communion,</hi> did according to their abilities, offer ſomething of their ſubſtance to God, for charitable uſes and maintenance of the <hi>Miniſters.</hi> Therefore.<note n="e" place="margin">Sermone <hi>1.</hi> de Eleemoſynis.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſharply taxeth a rich Matron, that received the Communion, and offered nothing. <hi>Locuples &amp; dives &amp; dominicum celebrare te credis, quae</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">He calleth the treaſury <hi>Corban,</hi> of that at the Temple of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Corban omnino non reſpicis &amp;c. What?</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>art thou able and rich? and doſt thou thinke that thou celebrateſt the Lords Supper, which bringeſt nothing to the Treaſurie?</hi> So <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith)<note n="g" place="margin">Novi Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments novam docuit (<hi>ſcil.</hi> Chriſtus) obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem: quam Eccleſia ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis accipiens in <hi>univerſo mundo</hi> offert Deo, ei qus aelimenta nobis praeſtat; primitiaes ſuorum munerum in no vo teſlamento.</note> 
               <hi>That it was the uſe of the Church through the world in his time, and received from the Apoſtles; to offer ſomething of the bleſſings that they lived by, as the firſt fruits thereof, to him that gave theſe things unto them.</hi> Which<note n="h" place="margin">Vide Zanchium lib. <hi>1.</hi> de cultu. Dei externe.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchius</hi> underſtandeth to be meant of offerings at the <hi>Communion: given to holy uſes, and for reliefe of the poore of the Church:</hi> commending it for an excellent cuſtome, and complaining that it is now diſcontinued. But to this end, and in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hereof, are our Eaſter and Communion offerings (as alſo thoſe, at, and for Chriſtnings, Burials, &amp;c. which I will not now ſpeake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113568:21"/>further of) at this day made, and therefore let <hi>Proprietaries</hi> conſider with what conſcience they can ſwallow and digeſt them.</p>
            <p n="5">.5 Touching the <hi>land, glebe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Glebe Land and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes belonging to Parſonages.</note> and <hi>houſes,</hi> belonging to Parſonages, (which I would have called <hi>Gods fixt inheritance,</hi> but that I ſee it is <hi>moveable:</hi>) I cannot ſay that they are Gods <hi>ancient demaines,</hi> in the ſame forme that tithes are, and as our Clergy enjoyeth them, but the warrant and ground thereof, riſeth out of the word of God; who not onely gave us a preſident thereof, when he appointed Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the <hi>Levites</hi> to dwell in, with a convenient circuit of fields for the maintenance of their Cattle, <hi>Num.</hi> 35.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but commanded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (and in them all the Nations of the world:) that in diviſion of their land, they ſhould offer an oblation to the Lord, an holy portion of the Land for the Prieſt to dwell on, and to build the houſe of GOD upon: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45.1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. So that the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and lands that our Anceſters have dedicated to God in this manner, for the Churches and Miniſters of this time: are now alſo his <hi>right</hi> and <hi>juſt inheritance,</hi> as well as thoſe which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> aſſigned for the <hi>houſe of God,</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> of that time; and commeth upon the ſame reaſon and in lien thereof. But becauſe it is uncertaine when and how they were brought into the <hi>Church,</hi> I will ſay ſomething touching that point.</p>
            <p>In the time of the Apoſtles the uſe was (as appeareth <hi>Acts</hi> 2.45. &amp; <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.34, <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.) to ſell their lands, and bring the money one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">How lands came to the Churches.</note> to the Apoſtles. For the Church being then in perſecution, and the Apoſtles not to remaine in any particular place, but to wander all over the world, for preaching the Goſpell: they could not poſſeſſe immoveable inheritances: and therefore received onely the money they were ſold for, diſtributing it as occaſion ſerved. But after when the Church obtained a little reſt, and began to be ſettled:<note n="a" place="margin">It appeareth by the Epiſtles of <hi>Pius</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved about the yeare of Chriſt 230. that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had then begun to retaine lands in this manner upon this reaſon: and it may well be, for that <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> ſhew, that Churches had then poſſeſſions.</note> it found much caſualty in pecuniary contributions, and chuſed therefore rather to retaine the Lands themſelves, given for the maintenance of Gods Prieſts and Miniſters: then (by ſuffering the ſame to be ſold) to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the time preſent with abundance, and leave the future time to hazard and uncertainty. Hereupon the Fathers in the<note n="b" place="bottom">Edicta Conſtantine &amp; Lucinis Impp. Euſ. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Primitive Church, as well before <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (as appeareth by his owne Edicts,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113568:21"/>and by<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ortgen</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of <hi>rents</hi> of the Church: <hi>Hom.</hi> 31. <hi>in Mar.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> of an houſe belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiech</hi> that <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Saemoſatenus</hi> in the time of <hi>Aurelianus</hi> the Emperour (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 30 yeares before <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>) wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invaded. <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and the Epiſtles of<note n="e" place="margin">Read the note (a) next afore.</note> 
               <hi>Pius,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Read the note (a) next afore.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi>) as after: began to accept and retaine the lands thus given, and to leave them over to their ſucceſſors for a perpetuall Dowry of the Church. And this upon experience was found to be ſo godly and worthy a courſe that it not onely received the applauſe of all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages: But commendeth for ever unto us their temperance, in deſiring no more then for preſent neceſſity, their zeale for providing for poſterity, and their great wiſedome, (or rather, Propheticall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) which fore-ſaw ſo long before hand, that devotion though it were at one time hot and fervent, yet, at another it might be cold e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: and therefore when time ſerved, they would by this meanes provide that the <hi>Church</hi> for ever, ſhould have of her owne, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine her ſelfe withall. Upon this enſued many godly proviſions for endowment of Churches, and for annexing their livings ſo unto them, as neither the variety of time, nor the impiety of man (if it were poſſible) ſhould ever have divorced them; as appeareth by a multitude of ancient Counſels, Canons, Statutes, and decrees of the<note n="g" place="margin">Synod. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. ſub Syma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho. <hi>103.</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> circiter An. Chriſt. <hi>503.</hi> tota contra in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſores Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum. Concil. Aurelianenſ. <hi>4.</hi> Ann. <hi>543.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> &amp; <hi>34.</hi> Conc. Meldenſ. cap. <hi>5.</hi> Burch. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> Concil. Gangrenſ. cap. <hi>8.</hi> Bur. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi> Concil. Mogunt. cap. <hi>3. 6. 7.</hi> &amp; plurima alia.</note> 
               <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="bottom">See the two Edicts of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> Empp. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. And the lawes of <hi>Conſtant: Theodoſ: Juſti Carel: Magn:</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other.</note> 
               <hi>Emperours,</hi> and<note n="i" place="bottom">To paſſe over forraigne Princes, our owne in former times have almoſt ſucceſſively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed thems</note> 
               <hi>Princes,</hi> to that purpoſe. Therefore whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the world burned ſo with that ſacred fire of devotion, towards the advancement of the glory of God: that every man deſired to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his hand, in the building of Churches, leſt ſuch holy monuments for want of due maintenance, ſhould in proceſſe of time becom, either contemptible, or unprofitable, It was at length ordained, in<note n="k" place="bottom">Si quis in agro ſuo, aut habet, aut poſtulat habere diaeceſim, trimùm &amp; terras ei depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet ſufficienter, &amp; clericos: qui ibidem ſua officia impleant, ut ſacratu locis reverentia condigna tribua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aur. Conc. c. <hi>23.</hi> in Conc. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> ubi nota quod dioeceſis accipitur pro libertate condendi oratoria vel Eccleſias itaque in argumento hutus capituli oratorium exponitur.</note> 
               <hi>Aurel. Concil.</hi> 4. (<hi>An.</hi> 545.) <hi>cap.</hi> 3, And<note n="l" place="bottom">Tom. Concil. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Concil. Valentin,</hi> (<hi>An</hi> 855) <hi>cap.</hi> 9, That, <hi>whoſoever builded a Church, ſhould aſſigne unto it a</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Coloniam veſtitam.</note> 
               <hi>Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, furniſhed for the maintenance of the Parſon thereof.</hi> By vertue of theſe <hi>Councels</hi> (as I take it) were the <hi>Founders</hi> of Churches in <hi>France</hi> firſt compelled to aſſure Livings to thoſe <hi>Churches.</hi> And it was alſo provided by the third <hi>Councell</hi> of<note n="m" place="bottom">Concil. Tolet. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tolledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> that no Biſhop might conſecrate any <hi>Church,</hi> till ſufficient maintenance (which<note n="n" place="bottom">Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>18.</hi> in Acta.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calleth the <hi>Dowry of the Bride</hi>) were aſſigned to it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113568:22"/>
            <p> But becauſe theſe were forraigne, and <hi>Provinciall Councels,</hi> not <hi>Generall:</hi> they bound not our Countrey, otherwiſe then by doctrine and example. Therefore it was here decreed afterward, to the ſame effect in a<note n="o" place="margin">Syn. Lond. ca <hi>16.</hi> Antiq. Britan. ca. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>London</hi> under <hi>Anſelme Arch-biſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Anno Domini</hi> 1105. <hi>H.</hi> 1.3. And though the lawes of our Church began then firſt (as farte as I yet can finde) to conſtraine our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men to give <hi>Endowments</hi> to the Churches that they builded; yet we were taught before (by the Cuſtome and Example of our prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Aunceſtors, as well as by our <hi>duty,</hi> out of the <hi>Word of God</hi>) to doe the ſame: as appeareth by many Preſidents, whereof I will onely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge one (but above others, that moſt famous) of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alias</hi> Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus.</note> ETHEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVULPHUS, <hi>King of Weſt-Saxony,</hi> who (in the yeare of our Lord 855.) as<note n="p" place="margin">Ingulf. in Hiſt. Croil.</note> 
               <hi>Ingulphus Saxo,</hi> and<note n="q" place="margin">Sim Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelm. citat. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquit. Brit. ca. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Simeon Dunelmenſ.</hi> report, by the advice and agreement of all his <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Nobility: Gave</hi> not onely the <hi>tithe</hi> of the <hi>goods,</hi> but the<note n="r" place="margin">Decimam manſionem ubi minimum ſit.</note> 
               <hi>tenth</hi> part of the <hi>Land</hi> through his Kingdome for ever, to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Churches,</hi> free from all ſecular ſervices, taxations, and impoſitions whatſoever: In which kind of religious magnificence, as our ſucceeding Kings have alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded: ſo have they from<note n="ſ" place="margin">As appeareth in their ſeverall lawes, and namely 15 times in <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. raigne.</note> time to time, as well by Parliament Lawes, as by their Royall <hi>Charters,</hi> confirmed theſe and other the Rights of the <hi>Church,</hi> with many ſolemne<note n="t" place="margin">See the Stat. of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. in <hi>Raſtals</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment <hi>tit. Confirmat.</hi> 3. And <hi>Sententia lata ſuper Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi>
               </note> vowes and imprecations againſt <hi>all</hi> that ſhould ever attempt to violate the ſame. Therefore if theſe things had not beene primarily due unto God by the rule of his word, yet are they now <hi>His.</hi> and <hi>ſeperate</hi> from us, by the voluntary gift and dedication of our ancient Kings and Predeceſſours: as was the<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehe.</hi> 10.32.</note> 
               <hi>tribute</hi> of a third part of a ſhekel, which <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the Jewes out of their <hi>free</hi> bounty covenanted yearely to give unto God <hi>for the ſervice of his houſe.</hi> For, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.4.</note> ſaith to <hi>Ananias: Whileſt theſe things remained, they appertained unto us, and were in our owne power:</hi> but now, when we have not onely vowed them, but delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them over into the hands and poſſeſſion of Almighty God (and that, not for ſuperſtitious and idle orders, but meerely for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his publike divine worſhip, and the Miniſters thereof, (they are not now arbitrable, nor to be revoked by us, to the detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Churches and their livings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate to God.</note> Churches being erected and endowed: they and their livings, were (as I ſay) dedicated unto God. Firſt, by the ſolemne vow and oblation of the Founders: then by the ſolemne act of the Biſhop,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113568:22"/>who to ſeperate theſe things from ſecular and prophane imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not onely ratified the vow and oblation of the Patron or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: but <hi>conſecrated</hi> alſo the Church it ſelfe: uſing therein great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, many bleſſings, prayers, workes of charity, and ſome Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, for ſanctifying the ſame to divine uſes. Therefore alſo have the ancient<note n="a" place="margin">See the 6. <hi>Syn. Rom.</hi> of 103 Biſhops (above 1000 yeares ſince) wholly againſt violaters of Churches and Church-rights. And ſee many to this purpoſe. <hi>Burchar. lib.</hi> 11.</note> Councels added many fearefull <hi>curſes</hi> againſt all ſuch as ſhould either violate it, or the Rights thereof.</p>
            <p>This <hi>conſecration,</hi> Maſter<note n="b" place="margin">Demonſt. problem. tit. Templum ſect. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Perkins</hi> calleth a Dedication, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth it to have been in uſe in this manner, about the yeare of Chriſt 300. (which is within the time of the Primitive Church) onely he admitteth not, that it was then performed with <hi>Ceremony</hi> and the ſigne of the <hi>Croſſe;</hi> which here I will not ſtand upon, nor to ſhew the greater antiquity thereof, (though I thinke it may well be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.) For<note n="*" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Conſtant Imp.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> being in thoſe daies accuſed by the <hi>Arians,</hi> of miniſtring the Communion in a Church not <hi>conſecrated,</hi> excuſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to have done it upon neceſſity. And<note n="c" place="margin">Hiſtor. ſuae lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi> &amp; Sozom. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> Niceph l. <hi>8.</hi> cap <hi>50.</hi> Hiſt. Triper l. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>331.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theodoret</hi> reporteth, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (then likewiſe) commanded, <hi>all thoſe that were at the Councell of Tyrus, ſhould come to</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hie aſalem. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. conſecrare.</note> 
               <hi>Aelia: and that others ſhould be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled from all parts, for</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. in orat. de laudib. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> 
               <hi>Conſecration of the Churches builded by him.</hi> Which ſheweth it to be ſo notorious and generall an uſe at that time, and to have ſuch univerſall approbation; as it could not, but have a root alſo from elder ages, though there cannot be many preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents found thereof, for that the Chriſtians being then in perſecution, might hardly build, or dedicate any Churches, but were conſtrained to uſe private houſes, and ſolitary places for their aſſemblies. Yet, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe <hi>houſes,</hi> had (as it ſeemeth) ſome <hi>conſecration,</hi> for they were moſt commonly called<note n="*" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>aedes ſacrae,</hi> Holy houſes, and have left that name, (to this day) amongſt us, for our Churches, as a teſtimony of their ſanctification, whereof I ſhall ſpeake more anon.<note n="*" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaith: that <hi>inſomuch as the Holy houſes and Temples of that time, were thus Dedicated and</hi> Conſecrated <hi>unto God, the univerſall</hi> Lord <hi>of all: therefore they received his name, and were called in Greeke</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (in Latin, <hi>Dominica</hi>) <hi>the</hi> Lords houſes: <hi>Which name,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was not impoſed upon them by man: but by himſelfe onely, that is Lord of all.</hi> Of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, cometh the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Cyric</hi> or <hi>Kyrk:</hi> and (by adding a double aſpiration to it) our uſuall word <hi>Chyrch</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> as it were to put us ever in mind, whoſe theſe <hi>Houſes</hi> are:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113568:23"/>namely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.22.</note> 
               <hi>the Lords houſes:</hi> like that, which JACOB dedicating un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to GOD, called <hi>(Bethel:)</hi> that is, <hi>the houſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But both Church and Church-livings were thus ſolemnely delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into Gods poſſeſſion; and therefore all ages, Councels and Fathers (that ever I yet have met with) account them holy and inviolable things.<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>18.</hi> in Act. Concil. Mogunt. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> And hereupon they are termed, <hi>Patrimonium Chriſti, Dos Eccleſiae, Dos ſponſae Chriſti,</hi> and <hi>Sacrata poſſeſſio,</hi> or <hi>Praedium ſanctum.</hi> For, <hi>Everything that a man doth ſeperate unto the Lord from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, whether it be man, or beaſt, or <hi>Land of his Inheritance,</hi> it is <hi>Holy</hi> to the Lord: Levit.</hi> 27.28. And in what ſort I underſtand the word <hi>Holy,</hi> I have before declared.</p>
            <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Holy rights and Temples how reſpected by Heathens.</note> As then the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> primarily taught all Nations in the world to give theſe things unto God: ſo the very ſame Law, alſo taught them that it was ſacriledge and impiety to pull them backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: yea, the very heathen counted the things thus ſevered unto their gods, to be <hi>Sancta &amp; inviolanda.</hi> And Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth, <hi>Sanctum illud eſſe, quod violare nefas eſt.</hi> It is execrable wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.22.</note> to violate that that is holy. <hi>Pharach</hi> would not abridge the Prieſts of their diet, or land: no not in the great famine. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Barbarous Nations of the world, even by the inſtinct of nature, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred this impiety.<note place="margin">Biblioth. hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> noteth of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> that though they were a people, above all others moſt covetous of gold: yet having abundance thereof, ſcattered in all parts of their Temples, to the honour of their gods, none was found ſo wicked amongſt them, as to meddle with any of it. I could alleadge a multitude of Heathen ſtories to this purpoſe. But I will not weave the woollen yearne of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> into the fine linnen garments of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> I meane, I will not mingle profane arguments, in a diſcourſe of Chriſtian piety. For the ſheepe that are of the fold of Chriſt, are tied onely <hi>to heare his voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 10.3.</note> and to follow that, which if they doe not, they are thereby knowne to be <hi>Goats,</hi> and not of his fold.</p>
            <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">How fearefull a thing it is to violate the Church.</note> The cauſe why I touched upon this one heathen Example, is to aggravate the manifold ſinnes of us Chriſtians, in this point. For if they that knew not God, were ſo zealous of the glory of their Idols: how much more is it to our condemnation, if we that know him, doe leſſe regard him? If it goe hard with <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sydon</hi> in the day of judgement that ſinned ignorantly; how much harder will it be with <hi>Coraſin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida</hi> that ſinne preſumptuouſly: Eſpecially with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113568:23"/>
               <hi>Capernaum</hi> that deſpiſeth her Lord God and Maſter, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelfe? What is it to deſpiſe him; if to robbe him of his honour, be not to deſpiſe him? Or what is it to robbe him of his honour, if to take from him the things given him for maintenance thereof, be not to robbe him? Therefore when the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> withheld their <hi>tithes</hi> and <hi>offerings</hi> from the <hi>Levites,</hi> he crieth out in <hi>Malachy</hi> 3.8. That <hi>himſelfe was robbed and ſpoiled:</hi> and was ſo highly offended therewith, that he curſed the whole Nation for it. And to make <hi>this</hi> ſinne appeare the more monſtrous, he convinceth the offenders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: not onely to be violaters of his <hi>Legall</hi> ordinances, but even of the very law of <hi>Nature,</hi> written in the heart of every man. For, ſaith he, <hi>Will any man ſpoile his gods?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay: Can ſuch a man be found as will, or dares commit that ſinne, that all the Nations of the world, even by the inſtinct of nature, account to be ſo horrible and impious? <hi>To ſpoile his gods: what his owne gods?</hi> Some were found, that now and then adventured to ſpoile the gods of other Nations, (yet not without puniſhment) but few or none that I reade of (till theſe latter daies) that ſpoiled their owne gods, in apparent and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> manner, as the Lawyers tearme it. I count it not overt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, when we doe as <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> did: pinch and detract from God, ſomewhat of that we vowed to give: Nor, when we doe as the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> here did withhold that which we ought to pay out of our owne goods, (yet both theſe were heinous ſinners, and dreadfully puniſhed.) But I call it overt and apparent, when we throw our ſelves into a more dangerous ſinne, by invading openly the devotions of other men, and taking that from God and from his Church, (as <hi>Athalia</hi> did) which we never gave unto it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Chron. <hi>24.</hi> verſ <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> even the lands and livings thereof: yea, the Churches themſelves.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Davids</hi> zeale for the houſe of God.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 Doubtleſſe we have much to feare in this point: For as it is a tranſcendent ſinne; ſo <hi>David</hi> labouring to match it with a tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent puniſhment, beſtoweth a whole Pſalme, (<hi>viz.</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">This Pſalme is alleadged to this purpoſe by <hi>Lucius</hi> (who was martyred about <hi>An Chr.</hi> 255.) in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Galli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Spaine. Tom. Concil.</hi> 1.</note> 83.) in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying particularly againſt theſe kind of ſinners: ſuch (expreſly) as <hi>would take to themſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion;</hi> for that onely is the very <hi>center</hi> of the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and therein doe all the lines and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections of the <hi>Prophets</hi> invectives, concurre. Firſt he maketh a flat oppoſition betweene God and them: and therefore calleth them his enemies. Then he deſcribeth the nature of theſe kind of enemies: namely, that they are <hi>murmuring</hi> enemies, as grudging, and envying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113568:24"/>at the proſperity of the Church: <hi>Malicious</hi> enemies: as hating or hurting the ſervice of God. <hi>Proud</hi> enemies, as <hi>lifting up their heads againſt God: verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Craftie</hi> enemies; as imagining how to beguile the Church. <hi>Conſpiring</hi> enemies; as taking <hi>Councell</hi> together againſt Gods <hi>ſecret ones</hi> (as the Prophet calleth them) that is, Gods ſervants and Miniſters: <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. And laſtly, <hi>Confederate</hi> enemies: as combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelves one by example of another, to perſevere in their courſe of wronging and violating the Church: <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. Yet for all this, thoſe againſt whom the Prophet thus inveigheth, did not that they deſired. They diſcovered their malitious purpoſe by word of mouth, ſaying: <hi>Let us take to our ſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion.</hi> But they onely ſaid it, they did it not. Their will was good, but their power failed. Our will and power have both prevailed: for we have got the <hi>houſes of God into our poſſeſſion:</hi> His Churches, his lands, his offerings, his holy rights. We have gotten them, and led them away captive, bound in chaines of iron: that is, ſo conveied and aſſured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, by Deed, by Fine, by Act of Parliament, as if they never ſhould returne againe unto the Church. But heare what <hi>David</hi> ſaith to thoſe of his time. Marke how he prayeth for them. Marke what ſtrange and exquiſite puniſhments he deſigneth to them: and that in as many ſeverall ſorts, as there are ſeverall branches in this kind of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he prayeth, that God would deale with them, as he did with the <hi>Madianites, verſ.</hi> 9. That is, that as <hi>Gedeon</hi> by Trumpets and Lampes, ſtrooke ſuch a terrour in the night time, into the hearts of the <hi>Madianites,</hi> that the whole army fell into confuſion, drew their ſwords one upon another, were diſcomfited, and 120 thouſand of them ſlaine. So that God by his trumpets, the Preachers of his word; by his Lamps, which is, the light of the Goſpell, would confound in like manner, the enemies and ſpoilers of his Church, that ſleepe in the night of their ſinne: And that he would make them like <hi>Oreb,</hi> and <hi>Zeb, like Zeba and Salmana: verſ.</hi> 11. All which were ſtrangely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowne, died violent deaths, and being glorious Princes of their nations, became like the filthy and loathſome <hi>Dung of the earth: verſ.</hi> 10. And <hi>Judges</hi> 7.25. <hi>and</hi> 8.21.</p>
            <p>But doth the Prophet ſtay here? no, he goeth on with them: <hi>O my God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>make them like a wheele, verſ.</hi> 13. that is, wavering and unſtable in their actions: ſo as they may never bring their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to an end. Yea, make them abject and contemptible; <hi>like the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113568:24"/>chaffe that the wind ſcattereth from the face of the earth: verſ.</hi> 13. Well, is he now fatisfied? no. All this doth but whet his ſpirits to ſharper imprecations. He now deſireth that the very floudgates of Gods wrath may be broken open upon them; and that the tempeſt of his indignation may rage at full againſt them: now he crieth out to God to conſume them without mercy, yea, and that in two terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manners. One naturally, <hi>As the fire burneth up the wood.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miraculouſly, <hi>As the flame conſumeth the mountaines: verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Perſecute them even ſo,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with thy tempeſt, and make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid with thy ſtorme. Make their faces aſhamed. O Lord, that they may ſeek thy name. Let them be confounded and vexed ever more and more, let them be put to ſhame and periſh. verſ.</hi> 15, 16, 17. How ſhould the wit of man diſcover and proſecute a ſin in more vehement and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner? Or, what ſhall make us to abſtaine from ſuch haughty ſinnes, if all this prevaile not? Well, if to take the houſes of God <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poſſeſſion</hi> be thus, take them that will for mee.</p>
            <p>You ſee how <hi>David</hi> in this his ſacred fury,<note place="margin">The zeale of our Saviour to the houſe of God. And of the parts of the Temple.</note> was admirably carried againſt this ſinne. Well therefore might he ſay: <hi>The zeale of thine houſe hath eaten me up, Pſal.</hi> 69.9. Yet, he ſpake it not of himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: but in the perſon alſo of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; who in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of <hi>Davids</hi> zeale, did that in this caſe, that he never did at any time elſe in all his life. In all other caſes he ſhewed himſelfe like the Paſchall Lambe, that every body did eat and devoure at pleaſure; and like the ſheepe that was dumbe before the ſhearer, even when his very life was taken from him. But when he ſaw the golden fleece to be taken from the <hi>houſe of God:</hi> that is, when he ſaw the Church his beloved <hi>ſpouſe,</hi> deprived and ſpoiled of the honour, reverence, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ornament, that belonged to her: Then, as <hi>David</hi> did, he groweth into a ſacred fury; he leaveth the mildneſſe of the Paſchall Lambe, and taketh upon him the fierceneſſe of the Lion of <hi>Juda.</hi> Then he beginneth to beſtirre him, and to lay about him. He whippeth out them that prophaned it; driveth out their ſheepe and their oxen, though they were for the ſacrifice: &amp; overthroweth the tables of the money changers: <hi>John</hi> 2.14. He would by no meanes indure ſuch trumpery to be in his Fathers houſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.12: Mar. 11.17. Luke 19.45.</note> nor his Fathers houſe to be made an houſe of Merchandiſe; but, much leſſe then, that merchandiſe ſhould be made of his Fathers houſe it ſelfe. O fearefull and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane ſinne! <hi>horreſco referens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113568:25"/>
            <p> But e're I depart from this place of Scripture; let mee note one thing more out of it, for the greater reverence of Churches: that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our Lord be here ſaid, to have caſt theſe things out of the Temple; yet, in truth, they were not in the Temple it ſelfe, but in the outward court or yard thereof. For within the inward parts of the Temple, (namely, the firſt, and ſecond Tabernacles) did no man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the <hi>Levite Prieſts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 18.5. Ebr. 9.2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c.</note> and of them alſo, none into the ſecond <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> but the High Prieſt. Therefore, although our Saviour Chriſt, were a Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck:</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was not a <hi>Prieſt of Levi:</hi> but of the Tribe of <hi>Juda</hi> (of which Tribe <hi>Moſes ſpake nothing touching the Prieſthood: Heb.</hi> 7.14. I take it, that<note n="a" place="margin">Chriſt came to fulfill the Law, and not to breake it. Therefore (doubtleſſe) he obſerved the rules thereof, and the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Tribe.</note> he never came within theſe parts of the Temple: nor where the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> was, but frequented onely<note n="b" place="margin">See the forme of the Temple in <hi>Arias Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan: Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Judaic. l. Ariel.</hi> and in the <hi>Geneva</hi> Bible, 1. <hi>King. cap.</hi> 6. and marke well both it, and the notes upon it; for I find them (above others) moſt agreeable to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not upon the figure of the Temple in <hi>Adricomius</hi> without good examination; for I perceive he hath miſplaced ſome things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</note> 
               <hi>Atrium populi,</hi> the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court from the Temple. For into this onely the<note n="c" place="bottom">See the note (a) among the notes aforeſaid.</note> people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted: to worſhip, pray, and heare the word of God expounded, not preſſing further towards the Temple: and in the middeſt whereof (the<note n="d" place="bottom">2. Chron. 6.13.</note> braſen ſtage which <hi>Solomon</hi> praied upon) was erected. Yet, this very place, this court, or outward yard, would not our Saviour permit to be prophaned; neither with market matters, nor with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying ſo much as a burthen or veſſell through it, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.16. For though it were not ſo <hi>Levitically</hi> holy, as the Temple: yet it was dedicated to God, with the Temple: And taken often in the new Teſtament, for the Temple: as in the places before alleadged. And <hi>Acts</hi> 3.2, 3. By which reaſon the very Church-yards themſelves (being Dedicated with the Churches, and the principall ſoile there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:<note n="*" place="bottom">Stat. Ne Rectores proſternant arbores in Coemiterio.</note> as an old Statute witneſſeth) ſeeme alſo to have in them a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine kind of <hi>Sanctification:</hi> and are not therefore to be abuſed to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and baſe imployments: as not onely the Ancient Fathers, by the Canons of the Church: but the preſent Lawes of the Land, have well provided for them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But ſome will ſay, that the <hi>ſanctification</hi> of the Temple was <hi>Leviticall,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">More of that matter and how farre the ſanctification of the Temple is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: or remaineth to our Churches.</note> and therefore aboliſhed, and not to be applied to our Churches. I anſwer, the Temple was ſanctified unto <hi>three functions;</hi> which alſo had <hi>three</hi> ſeverall places aſſigned to them. The <hi>firſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the <hi>Divine preſence;</hi> and had the cuſtody of the <hi>Holieſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113568:25"/>Types</hi> thereof; the <hi>Oracle,</hi> the <hi>Arke,</hi> the <hi>Mercy ſeat, &amp;c.</hi> And was therefore called <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> or the <hi>Holieſt of all.</hi> The <hi>ſecond,</hi> was for <hi>ceremoniall worſhip</hi> and <hi>attonement:</hi> namely, by ſacrifice, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and other <hi>Leviticall</hi> rites; the place thereof being the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> (wherein were the <hi>Holy veſſels</hi>) and the Court of Prieſts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Altar of burnt ſacrifice did ſtand. The <hi>third,</hi> was for ſimple worſhip, praier, and doctrine (without any pompe or ceremony:) and the place of this, was the <hi>outward Court,</hi> (called,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Chr. 4.9. &amp; 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Atrium po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 31.1.</note> 
               <hi>Solomons porch;</hi>) which therefore had in it no <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> implement at all.</p>
            <p>The <hi>two</hi> firſt of theſe functions, with the places belonging to them; were indeed particularly appropriat to the Law. For, they were <hi>Ceremoniall, Myſticall, Secret, Leviticall, Judaicall,</hi> and <hi>Temporall, Ceremoniall,</hi> as celebrated with much worldly pompe. <hi>Myſticall,</hi> as figurating ſome ſpirituall things. <hi>Secret;</hi> as either performed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the Veile or Curtaine: or elſe ſequeſtred and remote from the people. <hi>Leviticall;</hi> as committed onely to the adminiſtration of that <hi>Tribe. Judaicall;</hi> as ordained onely for the ſalvation of that people. And <hi>Temporall;</hi> as juſtituted onely for a ſeaſon, and not to continue. But the <hi>Sanctification,</hi> of the third <hi>function,</hi> and of the place thereto appointed, was directly contrary in all the points alleadged to the former two. <hi>Firſt</hi> (as I ſaid before) it was for <hi>ſimple worſhip, Praier,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which were there to be performed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in all <hi>ſincerity,</hi> without any <hi>ceremony</hi> or <hi>ceremoniall</hi> implement uſed therein. <hi>Secondly,</hi> there was no matter of <hi>myſtery</hi> therein to be ſeene: but whatſoever was <hi>myſticall</hi> in the Law, or the Prophets, was there expounded. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> nothing there, was hidden or ſecret from the people, but acted wholly without the <hi>Veile,</hi> and publikely for every man. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> it was not appropriate to the <hi>Levites,</hi> but common alike to all the Tribes. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> not ordained for the <hi>Jewes</hi> particularly, but for all Nations in generall. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> not to endure for a time, (as thoſe other two of the Law) but to continne for ever: even after the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were called, as well as the <hi>Jewes:</hi> that is, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the Goſpell, as well as the Law. Therefore, ſaith God, by <hi>Iſaias</hi> the Prophet, <hi>cap.</hi> 56. 7. <hi>My houſe ſhall be called an houſe of Praier, to all Nations.</hi> He ſaid not, an <hi>Houſe of Sacrifice to all Nations:</hi> for the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> ended before the calling of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and ſo they could have no part thereof. Nor an <hi>Houſe of Praier</hi> for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113568:26"/>the <hi>Iewes</hi> onely, for then had the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (when they were called) beene likewiſe excluded. But an <hi>Houſe of praier to all Nations,</hi> that is, <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> indifferently: which therefore, muſt have relation to the times of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> And conſequently, the <hi>ſanctification</hi> of that houſe, and of that <hi>function,</hi> is alſo a <hi>ſanctification</hi> of the Churches of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>We read not therefore, that Chriſt reformed any thing in the other two functions of the <hi>Temple;</hi> for they were now, as at an end. But becauſe this third function was for ever to continue to his Church: therefore he purgeth it of that that prophaned it; reſtoreth it (as he did marriage) to the originall ſanctitie: And that the future world (which was the time of the Goſpell) might better obſerve it, then the precedent, and the time of the Law had done; he reporteth, &amp; confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the <hi>decree,</hi> whereby it was ſanctified: <hi>It is written,</hi> ſaith he, (as producing the record and words of the foundation) <hi>My houſe ſhall be called an houſe of praier to all people.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>My Houſe,</hi> as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all other, from having any property therein; for, God will be Ioynt-tenant with no man. And it ſhall be, <hi>An houſe of praier for all people:</hi> that is, publike for ever; not private, nor appropriate to any: nor a <hi>denne of theeves;</hi> that is, no place of Merchandiſe, or ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar buſineſſe, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> expoundeth it. It muſt not be an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation; no man can, or may hold it in that kind.</p>
            <p>The time alſo when our Saviour pronounced theſe words is much to the purpoſe, as it ſeemeth to me. For it was after he had turned out the oxen and doves; that is, the things for the <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> As though he thereby taught us, that when the <hi>Sacrificall</hi> function of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was ended, yet the <hi>ſanctification</hi> thereof, to be an houſe of prayer, for ever remained.</p>
            <p n="11">11.<note place="margin">Saint Paul maintaineth the reverence of the Church.</note> This doctrine of our Saviour, is continued unto us by Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> who ſeeing the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to profane the Church with eating and drinking in it: though much good might follow thereby, (being orderly done) as the encreaſing of amity, and the reliefe of the poor; yet becauſe it was againſt the reverence of the place: he not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth them for it, demanding if they had not houſes to eat and drinke in at home,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.12.</note> but skaring them alſo (by ſhewing the danger they were falling into) he ſpeaketh to them as with admiration: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ye the Church of God?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, is your religion now come unto that? or is that your Religion, <hi>To deſpiſe the place that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113568:26"/>God hath ſanctified unto himſelfe;</hi> by making it,<note place="margin">Comment, in <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Triclinium epularum,</hi> a banqueting houſe. God wondered in <hi>Malachy,</hi> that any ſhould <hi>ſpoile their gods.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt here wondereth, that <hi>any ſhould deſpiſe the materiall Church:</hi> for ſo Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> expoundeth it. Thus both of them wonder at one and the ſame thing: that any man ſhould be ſo irreligious, as to profane the reverence due unto God, and that that is his.</p>
            <p n="12">12. So preciſe therefore were the Ancient Fathers in this point,<note place="margin">The Zeale of ſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Church. <hi>Serm. de temp. tom.</hi> 10.234.</note> that, that meeke Saint of God, Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> would by no meanes endure that any ſhould uſe clamours, or dancing within the verge of the Church. Yea, he termeth them, <hi>Miſerable and wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men that did it.</hi> And denounceth againſt them, that <hi>If ſuch came Chriſtians to the Church, they went Pagans home.</hi> But when the Church it ſelfe came to be abuſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Oh, how Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it, even againſt the Emperour himſelfe, great <hi>Valentinian</hi> that required it for an <hi>Arian: O</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let him aske that is mine, my lands, my goods, and whatſoever I poſſeſſe, I will not deny them; yet are they not mine: but belong to the poore. Verùm ea quae divina ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſororem: Epiſt. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but thoſe things that are Gods, are not ſubject to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Emperour. If my lands</hi> (I ſay) <hi>be deſired, enter them a Gods name; if my body, I will carry it him; if he will have me to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yea unto death, it pleaſeth me well, I will not defend my ſelfe with multitude of people, neither will I fly to the Altar, deſiring my life; but with all my heart will die for the Altars.</hi> And after,<note place="margin">In fine eiuſdem Epiſt.</note> in ſpeaking of the impious Souldiers: <hi>O that God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>would turne their hands from violating the Church, and then let them turne all their weapons upon me, and take their fill of my bloud.</hi> And many ſuch excellent ſpeeches he hath for the ſanctity of the Church, and of the reverence due unto it, in his Oration, <hi>De Baſilicis tradendis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My purpoſe is to be ſhort; I will not therefore now enter any further into the authorities of the Fathers: or meddle with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and ancient Canons of the Church, which abound ſo in this kind of zeale, and have eſtabliſhed it (againſt the <hi>Enſtathians, Meſſalians,</hi> and <hi>Fratricelli,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heretikes which contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Churches.</note> heretikes: and all other the enemies thereof) with ſo many examples, admonitions, exhortations, precepts, threatnings, curſes, and excommunications: as it requireth a booke alone to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113568:27"/> 13.<note place="margin">Sacriledge not to be ſuffered in the leaſt things. <hi>Coment. in</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. <hi>tom.</hi> 9. <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 25.27.</note> It ſeemeth a ſmall thing to dance in the Church-yard, or to cate and drinke in the Church. But <hi>ſanctification</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hierome,</hi> ſpeaking on this matter) <hi>conſiſteth alſo even in the ſmall things.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> adviſeth us, that <hi>we give not the water paſſage, no not in a little.</hi> For he that openeth the waters but a little, knoweth not how great a breach they will make at length. So is it to make an entrance into ſinne, or to breake the reverence of holy things in trifles.</p>
            <p>Therefore God puniſheth ſeverely the petty offenders in this kind: not <hi>Corah</hi> onely and his company, that invaded the high function of the Prieſthood: but even him that gathered the ſtickes on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day: <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.34. And poore <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> himſelfe (whom <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſo much lamented) that did, as it were, but <hi>ſtay the Arke</hi> from ſhaking, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6. and 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.9.) and yet died for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his hand was not ſanctified to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">An admonition to them that meddle With holy things.</note> I conclude this point with the ſaying of <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 20.25. (and let all men conſider it:) <hi>It is a ſnare for a man to devoure that which is ſanctified, and after the Vowes, to enquire.</hi> A Snare hath <hi>three</hi> properties <hi>Firſt,</hi> to catch ſuddenly. <hi>Secondly,</hi> to hold ſurely. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> to deſtroy certainly. So was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> taken e're he was aware: he did but touch the <hi>Arke,</hi> and preſently he was catch't. King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> did but meddle with the incenſe, and preſently the <hi>Leprouſie was on his face:</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.19. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did but ſtretch out his hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prophet, and preſently it <hi>withered:</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.4. And as a man falleth ſuddenly into it: ſo is it as hard to get out. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> died in it preſently. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> languiſhed in it all his life, and then died in it alſo. <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> were no ſooner caught in this ſnare, but it held them ſo ſurely, as when all <hi>Iſrael</hi> elſe fled and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; they, and their companions (moſt miſerable men) were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it, to their notorious deſtruction.</p>
            <p>I might here take juſt occaſion to remember what hath happened to many in this Kingdome, that became unfortunate after they med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Churches, and Church-livings. But I will runne into no particularities, Let thoſe men, and thoſe families, which are <hi>unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate</hi> (as we tearme them) conſider, whether themſelves, their Fathers, or ſome of their Anceſtors, have not beene ſettered in this ſnare.</p>
            <p>And let the <hi>Proprietaries</hi> of Parſonages alſo well conſider theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113568:27"/>things. For, if <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> died, that did but touch the Arke to ſave it: what ſhall become of them that ſtretch out their hands againſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to deſtroy them? If the <hi>ſticke-gatherer</hi> was ſtoned, for ſo ſmall a prophanation of the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> what ſhall they looke for, that by deſtroying the Churches, deſtroy alſo the Sabbath it ſelfe, (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) as taking away the place appointed to the publicke ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. And if <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> offended ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly in medling with the things of the Leviticall Prieſthood, though they imployed them to the ſervice of God: what have they to feare that uſurpe the things of the Goſpell, and pervert them wholly to their own uſe, from the ſervice of God? Yea, that pollute his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and houſes of prayer to ſervile and baſe offices: leaving the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners uncertainly provided of divine ſervice, to the deſtruction both of the Prieſthood it ſelfe, and of the ſervice of God in generall?<note place="margin">A ſurmiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. But they will comfort themſelves with this: that though the Churches be ſanctified to ſome purpoſe, yet the ſanctity thereof differeth from <hi>Leviticall ſanctification:</hi> and that God doth not now kill any from heaven, for prophaning the things of the Goſpell, as he did then, for prophaning the things of the law. I anſwer: The ſanctity indeed of the one, differeth from the ſanctity of the other. For the <hi>Leviticall</hi> things were ſanctified by the hand of man, to be matter of Ceremony; but the churches of the Goſpell, are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by our Saviour himſelfe, to be houſes of prayer. Not that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is to be uſed onely in theſe places, but that theſe places are onely to be uſed for prayer. And we muſt not preſume that God ſleepeth becauſe he puniſheth not (now as he did of old) the contemners of his worſhip. For as the law conſiſted in viſible and temporall things, ſo the puniſhments therein, were for the moſt part viſible and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall. But the Goſpell concerneth things inviſible and eternall, and therefore the puniſhments aſſigned therein, are for the moſt part inviſible and eternall.</p>
            <p n="16">16. They have alſo another comfort, and that is,<note place="margin">Another ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe anſwered.</note> that though theſe things were once Spirituall, now they are made temporall by the Lawes of <hi>Diſſolution;</hi> and eſpecially by the <hi>Stat. of</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. It is true that thoſe Statutes apply divers Law-termes unto theſe things that properly belong to temporall inheritances: and that the Statute of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. hath made them <hi>demandable</hi> by originall Writs, and hath given certaine reall actions, and other courſes for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113568:28"/>recovering and conveying of them in Temporall Coruts: becauſe Lay-men could not in former times have ſued for things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in any Court of the Kingdome. But this proveth not the things themſelves to be therefore temporall,<note place="margin">Diſſero non aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſero.</note> (no more then that an Engliſh man is a French man, becauſe he ſaileth in a French bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome,) For upon the ſame reaſon the Statute giveth alſo other actions (for recovering of <hi>tithes</hi> and <hi>offerings</hi> withholden, &amp;c.) in the <hi>Courts ſpirituall.</hi> They then that out of the one part of the <hi>Statute</hi> will have them temporall, are by the other part inforced to confeſſe them ſtill Spirituall, and ſo to make them like a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taure, <hi>prolem biformem.</hi> It were very hard (in my underſtanding) to ground a point of ſo great conſequence, upon ſubtletie of words, and ambiguous implications, without any expreſſe letter of Law to that purpoſe, eſpecially, to make the Houſes and offerings of God, <hi>temporall</hi> Inheritances. But I ſee it is a Law queſtion in my Lord<note n="a" place="margin">Term. Paeſ. An. <hi>7.</hi> Edw. <hi>6.</hi> Aſſiſe fol. <hi>83.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dier</hi> whether <hi>tithes</hi> be made Lay or Temporall, by any word in thoſe Statutes. And therefore I muſt leave this point to my Maſters of the Law, who have the key of this knowledge only in their owne cuſtody. Yet I thinke I may be ſo bold, as to ſay thus much out of their owne<note n="b" place="margin">Doct. &amp; Stud. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> bookes, that <hi>a Statute directly againſt the Law of God, is void.</hi> If then <hi>Tithes</hi> be <hi>things ſpirituall,</hi> and due <hi>de jure divino,</hi> as many great<note n="c" place="margin">See <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 219. <hi>de Temp. Hoſtienſ.</hi> and moſt Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts. <hi>Concil. Montiſc.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 50. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Mogunt. cap</hi> 38. <hi>alias</hi> 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Clarkes, Doctors, Fathers, ſome Councells, and (that ever honourable Judge and Oracle of Law) my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> himſelfe in <hi>the ſecond part of his</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſmes ſont choſes ſpirituall, &amp; due</hi> de jure di vine Le Eveſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de Winch. caſe fol. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Reports</hi> affirme them to be; I cannot ſee how humane lawes ſhould make them <hi>Temporall.</hi> Of the ſame nature therefore that originally they were of, of the ſame nature do I ſtill hold them to continue: for <hi>manente ſubjecto, manet conſecratio, manet dedieatio. Time, Place,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> do not change them, as I take it, in this caſe.<note n="e" place="bottom">Neſcio quo faio fit; ut eadem temporit periodo (viz. an <hi>68</hi>) poſt ereptas per Nabuc. &amp; H. <hi>8.</hi>) res tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorum: ſtirps ut iſque regia extincta fit, imperium ſublatum, &amp; ad aliam gentem de volutum. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius igitur ſperemus, Cyrum noſtrum Jacobum regem (qui ſceptra diſsidentia compeſcuit) reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> etiam munus aliquanda aggreſſurum.</note> 
               <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> tooke the holy veſſels of the Temple, he carried them to <hi>Babylon,</hi> he kept them there all his life, and at laſt left them to his ſonne and grandchildren: but all this while, the veſſels ſtill remained <hi>holy.</hi> Yea though they were come into the hands of thoſe that were not tyed to the ceremonies of the law, and at length into the hands of them that had them by a lawfull ſucceſſion from their Fathers and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113568:28"/>Grandfathers: yet as ſoone as they beganne to abuſe them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane uſes; that very night <hi>Balſhazzar</hi> himſelfe died for it, the line of <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> (that tooke them from the Temple) was extinct, and the Kingdome tranſlated to another Nation: <hi>Dan,</hi> 5.2.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Happily alſo, <hi>Lay Approprietaries</hi> comfort themſelves,<note place="margin">A third ſurmiſe anſwered.</note> that they may hold theſe things by example of Colledges, Deanes and Chapters, Biſhops of the land, and of divers of our late Kings and Princes. Before I ſpeake to this point, I take it by proteſtation, that I have no heart to make an Apology for it. For I wiſh that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man might drinke the water of his owne well, eate the milke of his owne flock, and live by the fruit of his owne vineyard. I meane that every member might attract no other nutriment, but that which is proper to it ſelfe. Yet are they greatly deceived, that draw any juice of encouragement from theſe examples. For all theſe are either the Seminaries of the Church, or the Husbandmen of the Church, or the Fathers and Nurſes of the Church: all <hi>de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milia Eccleſiae,</hi> and conſequently, belonging to the care of the Church, and ought therefore to be ſuſteined by it: for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>He that provideth not for his owne, and namely for them of his houſe-hold, he denieth the faith, and is worſe then an Infidell:</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.<note n="a" place="margin">All Church revenues were at firſt paid to Biſhops, and by them diſtrin buted to the Preiſts, poore, &amp;c. after the Biſhops were to have a fourth part of all tithes. <hi>Per Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Aurelian. Mogunt. Tribur Hanet: &amp;c. Et per Conc. Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeon.</hi> the third part.</note> Therefore before the ſtatutes of <hi>ſuppreſſion of Abbies,</hi> thoſe that were not meerely Eccleſiaſticall perſons, yet if they were <hi>mixt,</hi> or had Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, they might by the Lawes of the Land, participate Eccleſiaſticall livings, and<note n="b" place="margin">Plowd. in Quare imper Grend. L. Coke Report. part. <hi>5.</hi> fol. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tithes</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly. And this ſeemeth to take ſome ground out of the word of God. For the provinciall <hi>Levites</hi> (as I may terme them) whom<note n="c" place="bottom">1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 26.30.32.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſevered from the Temple, and placed abroad in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to be rulers of the People, <hi>in matters pertaining to God, and the Kings buſineſſe,</hi> (that is, <hi>Spiritually and Temporally:</hi>) had their portions of <hi>tithes</hi> notwithſtanding, as well as the other <hi>Levites</hi> that miniſtred in the Temple. Now, that the King is<note n="d" place="bottom">Se Plowd. in Quar. Imp. Gren. Et L. Coke de Jure Regis Eccleſ. part. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Perſona mixta,</hi> endowed as well with Eccleſiaſticall authority, as with temporall. Is not only a ſollid poſition of the common Law of the Land, but confirmed unto us by the continuall practiſe of our anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Kings, ever ſince, and before the Conqueſt, even in hotteſt times of Popiſh fervency. For this cauſe at their Coronations, they are not onely crowned with the Diadem of the Kingdome,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113568:29"/>and girt with the ſword of Juſtice, to ſignifie their Temporall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but are anoynted alſo with the<note n="c" place="margin">Reges ſacro o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo uncti, ſunt ſpiritualis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictionis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paces <hi>33.</hi> Ed. <hi>3.</hi> tit. Aide de Roy <hi>103.</hi> Ex Dom. Coke Repor. part. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>oyle of Preiſthood,</hi> and clothed, <hi>Stolâ Sacerdotali,</hi> and <hi>veſte</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Dalmatia eſt veſtis qua modo utuntur omnes diaconi ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennitatibus. ut <hi>70</hi> diſtin. de jejunto. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitus tamen, ſine conceſsione Papae, nec Epiſ. copis, nec Dia conis licebat uti hac veſte. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. <hi>23.</hi> cap. Omnes filius, Prateus.</note> 
               <hi>Dalmaticâ,</hi> to demonſtrate this their Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, whereby the King is ſayd in the Law to be <hi>Supremus Ordinarius,</hi> and in regard thereof, amongſt other Eccleſiaſticall rights, and prerogatives belonging unto him, is to have all the<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>22.</hi> Edw. <hi>3</hi> lib. Aſsiſ. plac. <hi>75.</hi> L. Coke par. <hi>5.</hi> fol. <hi>15. a.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tithes</hi> (through the Kingdome) in places that are out of any Pariſh, for ſome ſuch there be, and namely, divers<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Inglewood &amp;c. ut patet an. <hi>18.</hi> Edw. <hi>1.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter petitiones coram domino Rege ad Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentum.</note> Forreſts. But for all this: O! that his Majeſtie would be pleaſed to remembet <hi>Sion</hi> in this point.</p>
            <p n="18">18<note n="*" place="bottom">The danger that Proprietaries of Parſonages ſtand in.</note> I grow too tedious, yet before I cloſe up this diſcourſe, let me ſay one thing more to the <hi>Approprietaries</hi> of Churches, that happily they hitherto have not dreamed of. And that is, that by having theſe Parſonages, they are charged with Cure of ſoules, and make themſelves Subject to the Burthen that lieth ſo heavily upon the head of every Miniſter: to ſee the ſervice of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the people inſtructed, and the poore releived. For to theſe three ends and the maintenance of Miniſters, were Parſonages inſtituted, as not only the Canons of the Church, but the bookes of the Law, and particularly the Statutes of 15, <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. And 4. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 12. do manifeſtly teſtifie. And no man may have them but to theſe purpoſes, neither were they otherwiſe in the hands of Monaſticall perſons, nor otherwiſe given to the King by the ſtatute of diſſolution, then<note n="a" place="bottom">See the extent of theſe words in L. <hi>Coke part.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 49. And note alſo that Parſonages appropriate, are not mentioned in that Statute of 27. H 8. and the word <hi>(tithes)</hi> there ſeemeth to be meant of <hi>tithes</hi> belonging to the bodies of the Monaſteries; not of Parſonage <hi>tithes. Ideo quaere</hi> how the King had them before the Statute of 31. <hi>Regneſui.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in as large and ample manner as the governours of thoſe Religious houſes had them,</hi> nor by him conveied otherwiſe to the Subjects. For, <hi>Nemo poteſt plus juris in alium transferre, quam ipſe habet: No man may grant a greater right unto another, then hee hath himſelfe.</hi> And therefore go where they will, <hi>tranſeunt cum onere,</hi> they carry their charge with them. Upon theſe reaſons <hi>Proprietaries</hi> are ſtill ſaid to be Parſons of their Churches,<note n="b" place="bottom">Parſonimperſonee.</note> and upon the matter, are as the incumbents<note n="c" place="bottom">For the Monaſticall perſons and Prioreſſes themſelves that could not performe the divine ſervice, were notwithſtanding the Incumbents of their Churches: and lay Approprietaries claiming under their right ought alſo to be ſubject to the ſame burthens.</note> thereof, and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113568:29"/>by reaſon of this their incumbency, are full and not void. For otherwiſe the<note n="d" place="margin">There is yet no expreſſe law made to take away the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions over Churches ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate, (that I can finde.) <hi>Ideoquare</hi> how it extendeth.</note> Biſhop might collate, or the King preſent a Clarke (as to other Churches) as it ſeemeth by the arguments of the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the caſe betweene <hi>Grendon</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> in Maſter <hi>Plowdens Coment.</hi> where it is alſo ſhewed, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbencie is a<note n="*" place="margin">See Dier Tren. <hi>36.</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi> fol. <hi>58.</hi> pl. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> ſpirituall function, and ought not to be conferred upon any but ſpirituall perſons, and ſuch as may themſelves do the divine Service, and miniſter the Sacraments. Therefore, <hi>Dier,</hi> L Cheife Juſtice of the Common Pleas, there ſaid, that <hi>it was an horrible thing,</hi> when theſe Appropriations were made to Prioreſſes and houſes of Nunnes, becauſe that (although they were religious perſons, yet) they could not miniſter the Sacraments and divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Implying by this ſpeech of his, that it was much more <hi>horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> for Lay-men to hold them, that neither could do theſe holy rites nor were ſo much as ſpirituall perſons to give them colour for hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſpirituall things.<note n="*" place="margin">Termes of the Law <hi>in verbo Appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</hi>
               </note> Therefore he that inlarged the <hi>Termes of law</hi> (firſt ſet forth by <hi>John Raſtall</hi>) alſo termeth it a <hi>Wicked thing</hi> complaining (in his time) that it continued ſo long, to the <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>of learning, the impoveriſhing of the Miniſtry, and to the infamy of the Goſpell, and profeſſors thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Coke</hi> alſo in the ſecond part of his <hi>Reports,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Leveſque de Wincheſters caſe, fol. <hi>44,</hi> b.</note> that it is recorded in Hiſtory, that there were (amongſt other) two grievous perſecutions, the one, under <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> the other under <hi>Julian,</hi> named the Apoſtata: for it is recorded, that the<note n="a" place="margin">Diocleſ. vide Euſeb. hiſt. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> Niceph. l. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> one of them intending to have rooted out all the Profeſſors and Preachers of the word of God, <hi>Occidit omnes Presbyteros.</hi> But this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Religion flouriſhed, for <hi>Sanguis Martyrum eſt ſemen Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae: The bloud of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church;</hi> and this was a cruell and grievous perſecution, but the perſecution under the<note n="b" place="margin">Juli. vide Theod. hiſb. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>6.</hi> &amp; Niceph. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> other, was more greivous and dangerous. <hi>Quia</hi> (as the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory ſaith) <hi>ipſe occidit presbyterium. He deſtroyed the very order of Preiſthood.</hi> For he robbed the Church, and ſpoiled ſpirituall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their revenues, and tooke all things from them whereof they ſhould live. And upon this, in ſhort time, inſued great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of true religion, and the ſervice of God, and thereby great decay of Chriſtian profeſſion. For none will apply themſelves or their ſons, or any other that they have in charge, to the ſtudy of Divinity, when after long and painefull ſtudy, they ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113568:30"/>whereupon to live. Thus farre my Lord <hi>Coke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alledge theſe legall authorities, and leave Divinity, becauſe the <hi>Approprietariet</hi> of Parſonages (which ſheild themſelves under the target of the Law) may ſee the opinion of the great Lawyers of our owne time and Religion, and what the bookes of the Law have of this matter, to the end, that we ſhould not hang our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences upon ſo dangerous a pinne, nor put too great confidence in the equity of Lawes, which we dayly ſee, are full of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, often amended, often altered, and often repealed. O how la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable then is the caſe of a poore <hi>Proprietary,</hi> that dying, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of no other account, but of that touching his <hi>Lay vocation,</hi> and then coming before the judgement ſeate of Almighty God, muſt anſwere alſo for this<note n="c" place="margin">It is ſaid in my L. <hi>Dier</hi> in the caſe of a common per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the ſervice or a cure is a ſpirituall adminiſtration and cannot be leaſed, and that the ſervice is not iſſuing out of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next unto the perſon. 36. H. 8. <hi>fol</hi> 58. <hi>b. pla.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirituall function.</hi> Firſt why he medled with it, not being called unto it. Then, why (<note n="*" place="margin">Proprietaries which have Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars endowed, thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereby diſcharged: but though the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car be the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deputy to do the divine Service, yet a ſuperiour care thereof reſteth ſtill upon the Parſon himſelfe, and the ſurpluſage of the profits belongeth to the poore, as appeateth by the whole body of Fathers, Doctors, Counſells &amp;c.</note> medling with it) be did not the duty that belonged unto it, in ſeeing the Church carefully ſerved, the Miniſter thereof ſufficiently maintained, and the poore of the Pariſh farthfully relerved. This I ſay, is the uſe whereto Parſonages were given, and of this uſe we had notice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we purchaſed them: and therefore, not only by the lawes of God and the Church, but by the law of the Land, and the rules of the Chancery, at this day obſerved in other caſes) we ought onely to hold them to this uſe, and no other.</p>
            <p n="19">19.<note n="†" place="bottom">That it is not benevolence but duty to reſtore Church livings.</note> It is not then a worke of bounty and benevolence to reſtore theſe appropriations to the Church, but of duty and neceſſity ſo to do. It is a worke of duty to give that <hi>unto God that is Gods, Matt.</hi> 32.2. And it is a worke of neceſſity towards the obtaining remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe ſinnes. For Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non remittetur pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum, niſi reſtituatur ablatum cum reſtitui poteſt: The ſinne ſhall not be forgiven, without reſtoring of that which is taken away, if it may be reſtored.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is duty, juſtice, and neceſſity, to give them backe unto God. For it <hi>Judae</hi> (who was the firſt preſident of this ſinne) were a theife as the holy Ghoſt<note n="d" place="bottom">Ad Macedonium Epiſt. <hi>54.</hi> tom. <hi>2.</hi> Joh. <hi>12.6.</hi>
               </note> termeth him, for imbeaſiling that which was committed unto him for the maintenance of Chriſt and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that is of the Church: by the ſame reaſon, muſt it alſo be thee-very
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113568:30"/>to withold theſe things which were given for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Church and Miniſters of Chriſt. And herein it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree above that ſinne of <hi>Judas,</hi> as robbery is above theft, for <hi>Iudas</hi> onely detained the money (delivered unto him) cloſely and ſecretly, but we and our fathers, have invaded Church livings, and taken them (as it were by aſſault) even from the ſacred body and perſon of the Church.</p>
            <p>It is a great ſinne to ſteale from our Neighbour; much greater (even ſacriledge) to ſteale from God. If it were ſo heinous a fact in <hi>Ananias</hi> to withold part of his owne goods, which he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he would give unto God, how much more is it in us, preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly to reave that from God, that others have already dedicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and delivered unto him. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith; <hi>He that robbeth his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his Mother, and ſaith it is no ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.24.</note> 
               <hi>is the companion of</hi> [a murtherer, or] <hi>him that deſtroieth.</hi> But he that purloineth the things of God, robbeth his Father, and he that purloineth the things of the Church, robbeth his Mother. And therefore that man is a companion of the deſtroier.</p>
            <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Synod. <hi>5</hi> Rom. <hi>218.</hi> Epiſcop. An. <hi>503.</hi> Conc. Val. An. <hi>855.</hi> ca. <hi>9.</hi> Con. Rom. <hi>100</hi> Epiſc. An. <hi>1063.</hi> Conc. Rom. <hi>5.</hi> Anno <hi>1078.</hi> Conc. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. An. <hi>1388.</hi> Conc. Oxon. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Aug. Anno <hi>1222.</hi>
               </note> Fathers, the Doctors, many great Councells, and ancient Laws of the Church, command that things taken from the Church, ſhould be reſtored. And the Church by her<note n="a" place="margin">A ſtrange change: h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> realite</hi> gave their owne goods ſo abundantly to the ſervice of God, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was forced toreſtraine them by proclamation: <hi>Exod.</hi> 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but now nothing can move us to give God that which is his already.</note> Preachers &amp; Miniſters continually entreateth, urgeth, and requireth all men to do it. They therefore that do it not, they refuſe to heare the Church: And then our Saviour Chriſt, by his owne mouth, denounceth them<note n="b" place="bottom">Qui ſub <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omine fideli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gunt opera infidelium. Hieron ibid.</note> to be as Heathens and Publicans, that is, excommunicate and prophane perſons. <hi>If he refuſeth</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>to heare the Church alſo, let him be unto thee as a heathen man, and a publican. Mat.</hi> 18.17.</p>
            <p>It is a fearefull thing not to heare the<note n="c" place="bottom">We thinke the Chuch doth not command it till we make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament law for it, but the law is made already by Chriſt himſelfe.</note> Church, but much more, not to heare Chriſt himſelfe, Chriſt hath given us a perpetuall law and Commandement, touching things belonging to God: <hi>That we ſhould give them to God.</hi> If we breake this Law, we breake a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Law then that of the <hi>Medes,</hi> and the<note n="d" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>Perſians:</hi> and therefore marke what the holy Ghoſt concludeth upon us; <hi>Every perſon that ſhall not heare this Prophet</hi> (Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed out of the people. Act.</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113568:31"/> 20 To conclude then,<note place="margin">The concluſion.</note> as the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> made haſt to ſend home the<note n="e" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.11.</note> Arke of God; and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to ridde themſelves of the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.31.</note> people of God: ſo let us ply our ſelves to render unto God his Lands, and Poſſeſſions with all ſpeed. Otherwiſe, as he ſtrucke the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> with <hi>Emrods</hi> ſecretly, and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> with manifold ſcourges openly; ſo only himſelfe knoweth, what he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined againſt us.</p>
            <p>And thus I end,<note place="margin">Cypr. Ser. <hi>5.</hi> de lapſ. in fine.</note> with the ſaying of the bleſſed Saint <hi>Cyprian, Nec teneri jam, nec amari Patrimonium debet, quo quis &amp; deceptus &amp; victus eſt. We muſt now neither hold that Patrimony, or living, (no) nor ſo much as take pleaſure therein, whereby a man is entrapped and brought to deſtruction.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Her. cit. per. Iſid.</note> And with that other of the noble Saint <hi>Auguſtine; With what face canſt thou expect an inheritance from Chriſt in Heaven, that defraudeſt Chriſt in thy inheritance here on Earth? Therefore</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.7.</note> and unto God the things that are Gods.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113568:31"/>
            <head>An Epilogue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ardon me good Reader, though I have neither ſatisfied thee, nor my ſelfe, in this little diſcourſe. It is hard to bring a great veſſell into a ſmall creeke, an argument of many heads and branches, of much weight, variety and difficulty, into a few pages. It may be thou thinkeſt the volume bigge enough for the ſucceſſe that Bookes of this nature are like to have. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject not thy judgement, yet would I not have others thereby diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from purſuing this <hi>cauſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10</hi> ult. verſ. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> for though <hi>Peter</hi> fiſhed all night and got nothing, yet he made a great draught unlooked for) in the morning. He that directed that net, give a bleſſing to all our labours. For my owne part (if I catch but one fiſh) I ſhall thinke mine well beſtowed. Howſoever, it ſhall content me, and I thanke God for it, that he hath girded me with ſo much ſtrength as to ſtrike one ſtroke (though a weake one) in his battell, and to caſt one ſtone (though a ſmall one) againſt the adverſaries of his Church.</p>
            <p>Some will ſay, I have uſed too much ſalt and vineger in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and that I have bent the great Artillery of Gods judgements and threatnings, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a peece of too light importance. I would the conſciences of men were ſuch as oyle and butter might ſupple them. But I ſee they are for the moſt part overgrowne with ſo hard a <hi>carnoſity,</hi> as it requireth ſtrong and potent corroſives to make an entrance into them. A Preacher may ſhake them now and then with a Sermon, as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Felix:</hi> but when the thunder and lightning are ceaſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.26. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> they are (like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) ſtill where they were. Yea ſome have <hi>conſcientias cauteria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> as the Apoſtle termeth them, conſciences <hi>ſeared with an hot Iron:</hi> ſo ſtupefied, that dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> may be raiſed, before they can be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113568:32"/>But God knoweth the heart of man, and bringeth water out of the hard rocke; therefore though I have ſpoken this (as being jealous of the <hi>cauſe,</hi>) yet in charity I will hope better even of the hardeſt of them. Onely let no man thinke it a light ſinne, to keepe open the paſſage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the wilde bore (of <hi>Barbariſme</hi>) enters the Lords vineyard, and whereby God is deprived of the honour due to his name,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>80.13.</hi> Pſal. <hi>96.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Now at the parting, it may be thou deſireſt to know what ſucceſſe this my labour had with the Gentleman to whom I ſent it. In truth neither that I deſired,<note place="margin">Auguſt 16. 1613.</note> nor that which I promiſed unto my ſelfe. For (ſo it pleaſed God) that even the very day, the meſſenger brought it into <hi>Norfolke,</hi> the partie died. Otherwiſe I well hoped, not to have ſhot this arrow in vaine. But becauſe it then miſſed the marke at which it was ſent, (and many thought not fit to looſe it;) I have now let it flie at randome with ſome notes and alterations, as the difference betweene private and publique things requireth: but ſtill deſiring that I might further have ſhewed my minde in many paſſages hereof, (and particularly touching tithes in <hi>quoto,</hi> and ſuch Parſonages as have Vicarages well endowed) which without making it almoſt a new worke I could not do; and therefore reſting upon thy courteous interpretation, I leave it to thee, (for this time) as it is.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:113568:32"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF SAINT AUGUSTINES touching rendring of Tithes.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The occaſion of this Sermon or Homily was miniſtred unto him by the time of the yeare, it being the <hi>12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Sunday after <hi>Trinity,</hi> that is about the beginning of Harveſt. The Scripture that he fitteth unto it is the <hi>18</hi> of <hi>Luke.</hi> Where the <hi>Phariſee</hi> boaſteth of his preciſe juſtice in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tithes.</hi> It is the <hi>219</hi> Sermon <hi>de Tempore:</hi> extant in the tenth Tome of his works, and there entituled:</p>
            </argument>
            <head>De reddendis decimis.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the mercy of Chriſt <hi>(moſt beloved brethren:)</hi> the daies are now at hand, wherein we are to reape the fruits of the earth: and therefore giving thanks to God that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth them, let us mindfull to offer, or rather to render backe unto him the tithes thereof. For God,<note place="margin">Decret <hi>16:</hi> Qua <hi>1</hi> cap. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimae</note> that vouchſafeth to give us the whole, vouchſafeth alſo to require backe againe the tenth, not for his owne, but for our benefit doubtleſſe.<note place="margin">Where you may ſee a great part of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cited for <hi>Auguſtines.</hi>
               </note> For ſo hath he promiſed by his Prophet, ſaying:<note n="*" place="margin">Mala. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Bring all the Tithe into my Barnes, that there may be meate in my houſe; and trie me, ſaith the Lord, in this point, if I open not the windowes of heaven unto you, and give you fruit without meaſure.</hi> Lo, we have proved how <hi>Tithes</hi> are more profitable unto us, then to God. <hi>O fooliſh men!</hi> What hurt doth God command, that he ſhould not deſerve to be heard? For he ſaith thus: <hi>The firſt fruits of thy threſhing floore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.29.</note> 
               <hi>and of thy Wine preſſe thou ſhalt not delay to offer unto me.</hi> If it be a ſinne, to delay the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: how much worſe is it, not to give at all? And againe, he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16</hi> Quae. <hi>1.</hi> ca. decima.</note> 
               <hi>Honour thy Lord thy God with thy juſt labours, and offer unto him of the fruits of thy righteouſneſſe that thy barnes may be filled with wheat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. <hi>3.9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and thy preſſes abound with wine.</hi> Thou doeſt not this, for <hi>God ha mercy,</hi> that by and by ſhalt receive it againe with manifold increaſe. Perhaps thou wilt aske, who ſhall have profit by that, which God receiveth, to give preſently backe againe? And alſo thou wilt aske
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113568:33"/>who ſhall have profit by that which is given to the poore? If thou beleeveſt, thy ſelfe ſhall have profit by it; but if thou doubteſt, then thou haſt loſt it.</p>
            <p>Tithes <hi>(deare Brethren)</hi> are a <hi>tribute</hi> due unto the <hi>needy ſoules.</hi> Give therefore this <hi>tribute</hi> unto the <hi>poore,</hi> offer this ſacrifice unto the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> If thou haſt no <hi>Tithes</hi> of earthly fruits: yet whatſoever the Husbandman hath, whatſoever Art ſuſtaineth thee, it is Gods, and he requires <hi>Tithe,</hi> out of whatſoever thou liveſt by: whether it be Warfare, or Traffique, or any other Trade, give him the <hi>tithe.</hi> Some things we muſt pay for the ground we live on, and ſomething for the uſe of our life it ſelfe. Yeild it therefore unto him <hi>(O man)</hi> in regard of that which thou poſſeſſeſt: yeild it (I ſay) unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath given thee thy birth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.12.</note> for thus ſaith the Lord: <hi>Every man ſhall give the redemption of his ſoule, and there ſhall not be amongſt them any diſeaſes or miſhaps.</hi> Behold, thou haſt in the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures the <hi>cautions</hi> of the Lord, upon which he hath promiſed thee, that if thou give him thy <hi>Tithe,</hi> thou ſhalt not onely receive aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of fruits, but health alſo of body. <hi>Thy barnes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall be filled with wheate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>and thy preſſes ſhall abound with wine, and there ſhall be in them, neither diſeaſes nor miſhaps.</hi> Seeing then, by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tithes,</hi> thou mayeſt gaine to thy ſelfe, both earthly and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly rewards: why doeſt thou defraud thy ſelfe of both theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings together?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> Quae. <hi>1.</hi> ca. decimae.</note> Heare therefore, <hi>(O thou zeale. leſſe mortality.)</hi> Thou knoweſt, that all things that thou uſeſt are the Lords, and canſt thou finde in thy heart, to lend him (that made all things) nothing backe of his owne? The Lord God needeth not any thing, neither deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth he a reward of thee, but honour; he urgeth thee not to render any thing that is thine, and not his. It pleaſeth him to require the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> and the <hi>Tithes</hi> of thy goods, and canſt thou deny them, <hi>(O covetous wretch?)</hi> What wouldſt thou doe, if he tooke all the <hi>nine</hi> parts to himſelfe, and left thee the <hi>tenth</hi> onely? And this in truth he doth, when by with-holding his bleſſing of raine, the drought maketh thy thirſty Harveſt to wither away: and when thy fruit, and thy vineyard, are ſtrucken with haile, or blaſted with froſt, where now is the plenty that thou ſo covetouſly didſt reckon upon? The <hi>nine</hi> parts are taken from thee, becauſe thou wouldſt not give him the <hi>Tenth.</hi> That remaines onely that thou refuſeſt to give, though the Lord required it. For this is a moſt juſt courſe, that the Lord hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113568:33"/>
               <hi>If thou wilt not give him the tenth, he will turne thee to the tenth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> Quae. <hi>1.</hi> ca. decimae.</note> For it is written, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Inſomuch as the Tithe of your ground, the firſt fruits of your Land are with you: I have ſeene it, but you thought to deceive me: havocke and ſpoile ſhall be in your Treaſurie, and in your houſes.</hi> Thus thou ſhalt give that to the unmercifull Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, which thou wouldeſt not give to the Prieſt.</p>
            <p>The Lord almighty alſo ſaith; <hi>Turne unto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>that I may open un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the windowes of Heaven, and that I may poure downe my bleſſing upon you; and I will not deſtroy the fruit of your Land, neither ſhall the vines of your field</hi> [or the trees of your orchards] <hi>wither away,</hi> [or be blaſted] <hi>and all nations ſhall ſay, that you are a bleſſed people.</hi> God is allwaies ready to give his bleſſings. But the perverſeneſſe of man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hindreth him. For he would have God give him all things, and he will offer unto God nothing, of that whereof himſelfe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be the owner.<note n="*" place="margin">This place is cited as out of <hi>Aug. Conſ. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ ca</hi> 13. <hi>An</hi> 895. and before that <hi>in concil. Mogunt. pri. c.</hi> 8. <hi>An.</hi> 874.</note> What if God ſhould ſay? The man that I made, is mine; the ground that thou tilleſt, is mine; the ſeed that thou ſo weſt, is mine; the cattle that thou wearieſt in thy worke, are mine, the ſhowers, the raine, and the gentle winds are mine; the heate of the Sunne, is mine; and ſince all the Elements where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou liveſt, are mine; thou that lendeſt onely thy hand, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt onely the <hi>tithe,</hi> or <hi>tenth</hi> part. Yet becauſe Almighty God doth mercifully feede us, he beſtoweth upon the labourer a moſt liberall reward for his paines, and reſerving onely the <hi>Tenth</hi> part unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hath forgiven us all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ingratefull and perfidious deceiver,</hi> I ſpeake to thee in the word of the Lord. Behold the yeare is now ended: give unto the Lord (that giveth the raine) his reward. Redeeme thy ſelfe, O Man, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thou liveſt. Redeeme thou thy ſelfe whilſt thou maieſt. Redeeme thy ſelfe (I ſay) whileſt thou haſt wherewith in thy hands. Redeeme thy ſelfe, leſt if greedy death prevent thee, thou then loſe both life and reward together. Thou haſt no reaſon, to commit this matter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to thy wife, who happily will have another husband. Neither haſt thou (O woman) any reaſon to leave this to thy husband, for his mind is on another wife. It is in vaine, to tie thy Parents, or thy kinsfolke, to have care hereof: no man after thy death, ſurely ſhall redeeme thee, becauſe in thy life, thou wouldeſt not redeeme thy ſelfe. Now then, caſt the burthen of <hi>covetouſneſſe</hi> from thy ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, deſpiſe that cruell <hi>Lady,</hi> who preſſing thee downe with her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113568:34"/>yoake, ſuffereth thee not to receive the yoake of Chriſt. For as the yoake of <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> preſſeth men downe unto hell, ſo the yoake of Chriſt raiſeth men up unto heaven. For <hi>tithes</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired as a debt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> Quae <hi>1.</hi> ca. decimae.</note> and he that will not give them, invadeth another mans goods. And let him looke to it, for how many men ſoever die for hunger in the place where he liveth (not paying his <hi>Tithes</hi>) of the murthering of ſo many men ſhall he appeare guilty before the triounall ſeate of the eternall Judge, becauſe he kept that backe to his owne uſe, that was committed to him by the Lord for the <hi>Poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He therefore that either deſireth to gaine a reward, or to<note n="*" place="margin">Promereri.</note> obtaine a remiſſion of his ſinnes, let him pay his <hi>tithe,</hi> and be carefull to give almes to the <hi>poore,</hi> out of the other nine parts: but ſo notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that whatſoever remaineth over and above moderate diet, and convenient apparell, be not beſtowed in riot and carnall pleaſure, but layed up in the treaſurie of Heaven, by way of <hi>Almes</hi> to the <hi>poore.</hi> For whatſoever God hath given unto us more then we have need of, he hath not given it unto us particularly, but hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it over unto us to be diſtributed unto others: which if we diſpoſe not accordingly, we ſpoile and rob them thereof. <hi>Thus farre Saint Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ERaſmus</hi> in a generall cenſure of theſe Sermons <hi>de Tempore,</hi> noteth many of them not to be Saint <hi>Auguſtines:</hi> ſo alſo doth Maſter <hi>Perkins,</hi> and divers other learned men, who having examined them all particularly, and with great adviſement, rejecting thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be adulterate or ſuſpected, admit this notwithſtanding as undoubted. And although <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſeemeth to make a little que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of it, yet he concludeth it to be, without doubt, an excellent worke: and either<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Forte non eſt Auguſtimiſte ſermot, amen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignis eſt ſine du, bio, &amp; antiqui alicujus Patris, zam inde tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ex Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine multa ſunt adſcripta in Decret. <hi>16.</hi> q <hi>1.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bellarm. lib. de clericis cap. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> owne, or ſome other anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers. But he ſaith, that many things <hi>are cited out of it as out of Auguſtine in Decret.</hi> 16. <hi>q.</hi> 1. And to cleare the matter further, I finde that ſome parts hereof are alleadged under the name of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, in Concil. Triburienſ.</hi> (which was in the yeare of our Lord, 895) <hi>cap.</hi> 13. And twenty yeare before that alſo, <hi>in Concil. Mogun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. So that Antiquity it ſelfe, and divers Councels, accept it for <hi>Auguſtines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not recite a great diſcourſe to the effect of this Sermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113568:34"/>the workes of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the Treatiſe, <hi>De rectitudine Chriſtianae religionis;</hi> becauſe <hi>Eraſmus</hi> judgeth that Treatiſe not to be <hi>Auguſtines.</hi> Yet ſeemeth it likewiſe to be ſome excellent mans, and of great antiquity. But if thou wouldſt heare more what <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith unto thee of this matter, take this for a farewell;<note place="margin">Homil. <hi>48.</hi> ex lib. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores noſtri ideo copiis omnibus abundabant, quia Deo decima dabant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ham. com. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;. Caeſari cenſum reddebant: modo autem quia diſceſſit devotio Dei, acceſſit</hi> indictio fiſci. <hi>Noluimus partiri cum Deo decimas, modò au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem totum tollitur. Hoc tollit</hi> fiſcus, <hi>quod non accipit Chriſtus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>An Appendix by the Author.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Have beene often ſollicited within theſe two yeares, both to reim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print this little Treatiſe, and alſo to publiſh a greater worke much of the ſame Argument. Some eſpeciall reaſons have made me unwilling to doe either. Not that I doe, <hi>aut clypeum abjicere, aut cauſam deſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re:</hi> But I find my arme too feeble for ſo great an attempt: and in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſuch weight and conſequence, a better oportunity is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, then is yet afforded. I deſire therefore not to be haſtned herein, though he that publiſhed my Booke in <hi>Scotland</hi> (out of his zeale to the cauſe) taketh that for one of his<note n="*" place="margin">In his Epiſt. Dedicatory,</note> 
                  <hi>Motives.</hi> When I did firſt let it go forth: I did it onely in covert manner: not thinking it worthy of the bread eye of the World, nor holding it fit to have that which was done in a corner, <hi>preached upon the houſe top:</hi> or that which paſſed privately betweene me and my friend, to fly (in this ſort, at once) to both the <hi>Poles</hi> of the <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Hereupon I hitherto by entreaty with-held it from a reimpreſſion. But I being in the Country, and <hi>it</hi> being now to me as <hi>filius emancipatus,</hi> and out of my power: the Printer hath taken advantage of his liberty, and in my abſence printed it againe with the former infirmities.</p>
               <p>I wiſh, ſince it muſt needes be thus: that I had overrun it with a new hand: aſwell to explaine it in ſome things, as to helpe and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it in other. For the Argument hath many adverſaries, not of the <hi>Laity</hi> only: but amongſt the <hi>Church-men</hi> themſelves. All are not pleaſed with this forme of<note n="*" place="margin">Tithes</note> 
                  <hi>Maintenance:</hi> others are not ſatisfied how it is due. Some alſo conceive Scriptures in this manner, ſome in that: and where one is beſt pleaſed, there another findeth moſt exception. Thus he that cometh upon the Stage, is the Object and Subject of every mans opinion. Yet muſt I herein confeſſe my ſelfe beholding unto many:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113568:35"/>for I underſtand that this ſmall Eſſay hath given them good likeing.</p>
               <p>To ſatisfie all I labour not: but to the worthier ſort I would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what I could. Being therefore enformed (about a yeare almoſt ſince) that ſome particular Divines of learning and judgement, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveing well of my Booke, ſuppoſed that I had departed from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moderne interpreters in applying the <hi>12.</hi> verſe of the <hi>83.</hi> Pſ. <hi>onely to the ſanctified things of the Jewes, which (they ſaid) was ſpoken of all their houſes and Cities in generall.</hi> I did then unto them (as I thought is fit) <hi>reddere rationem &amp; fidei &amp; facti.</hi> And in like manner (becauſe the booke goeth forth againe upon a new adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and may encounter with the like objections,) I held it now as neceſſary to adde ſomething unto it in that point being ſo materiall. Yet muſt I ſignifie unto you, that they which tooke that exception, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted both my argument and whole diſcourſe the ſtronger (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) <hi>Ex conſequente:</hi> as namely, that if it were ſo heinous a ſinne to invade the temporall things of the Jewes, much more muſt it needes be to invade the ſpirituall. So that no man is either freed or caſed by this ſuggeſtion, but rather the more enſnared and overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Nevertheleſſe (I underſtand) that which followeth, hath cleared this point unto them: and I hope ſo ſhall it alſo do unto others (which ſeparate not themſelves from our Church) if cauſe require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant that many moderne and ſome Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Interpreters underſtand the body of the 83 <hi>Pſal.</hi> of the taking of the <hi>houſes</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> in generall, not onely of the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Synagogues,</hi> nor onely of the Cities of the <hi>Levites:</hi> for the very <hi>hiſtoricall</hi> texture of the <hi>Pſalme</hi> diſcovers as much. But that branch of it, whereon I faſtened my anchor, and where I cheifly inſiſted, namely the 12 <hi>verſe,</hi> touching the <hi>taking of the houſes of God in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,</hi> (which indeed is the <hi>center</hi> of the Pſalme: what interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever it receiveth) moſt of them interpret it primarily and poſitively for the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Holy things,</hi> then <hi>per tranſiationem</hi> for <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and by conſequence, for all <hi>Judea,</hi> (and the people of God) in reſpect that they were there planted.</p>
               <p>For though we following <hi>Genebrard, Calvin</hi> and <hi>Arias Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> tranſlate it literally, <hi>Take the houſes of God in poſſeſſion;</hi> yet the <hi>Septuagint</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> interpret it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And <hi>Hierom</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113568:35"/>in the Latin Vulgar accordingly, <hi>Sanctuarium Dei:</hi> in his other tranſlation called <hi>Hebraica veritas,</hi> (which alſo agreeth with that elder, cited by <hi>Lucius</hi> in the primer ages of the Church) <hi>Pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem Dei: Pellican, electiſſima:</hi> all of them by ſuch denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as are moſt proper to the <hi>Temple</hi> and holy things. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church in all former ages and for the moſt part yet alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, even in the reformed parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> retaineth that interpretation of <hi>Sanctuarium Dei,</hi> as beſt agreeing with the intent of the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> which <hi>Hierom</hi> in the Preface to his tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on profeſſeth confidently (by many witneſſes) that he hath chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in nothing.</p>
               <p>I alleage all this, but to ſhew, that by what variety of words ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the tranſlators expreſſe the originall <hi>Hebrew,</hi> yet they all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with this as the Fountaine and <hi>ſtandard;</hi> that <hi>primâ intentione,</hi> it aimeth at the holy things, though in <hi>ſecunda</hi> it be carried unto temporall.</p>
               <p>Our ſelves alſo in our owne Engliſh tranſlation, underſtand <hi>the houſes of God,</hi> for places dedicated to the ſervice of God. And therefore in the 9. verſe of the 74. Pſalme, where our <hi>Church Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaith, <hi>burnt up all the houſes of God in the Land:</hi> the <hi>Geneva</hi> and the Kings Edition report it, <hi>burnt up all the Synagogues of God in the Land.</hi> So likewiſe in the 1 verſe of the 84. Pſal. <hi>The dwellings of God</hi> are expreſly ſpoken of his <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> and holy habitations, not of his <hi>Temporall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet do I not deny; but (as I ſay) <hi>Secundâ intentione,</hi> the words <hi>Sanctuarium, or Houſes of God,</hi> in the 83. Pſalme are truely carried to all <hi>Judaea</hi> and the people of God, howbeit <hi>Hierome</hi> noteth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly no ſuch matter upon it: neither could <hi>Auguſtine</hi> find it in the literall or <hi>hiſtoricall</hi> ſence of the text: and therefore he deduceth it to the people of God by way of <hi>Tropology,</hi> uſing the <hi>metaphor</hi> of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Sanctuarium:</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Templum dei ſanctum eſt, quod eſtis vos.</hi> And <hi>Lyra</hi> accordingly, <hi>Sanctuarium, id eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Hieruſalem, in quae erat Templum Dei: &amp; per conſequens, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Judaeae, cujus metropolis erat Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnobius</hi> likewiſe of the Ancients taketh it firſt for the Temple and the holy veſſell: then extenſively, for the people &amp; Land of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell.</hi> As for <hi>Cyprian, Origen, Tertullian, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome, Gregory,</hi> they meddle not with it, that I can finde, nor <hi>Hierome</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then as I have mentioned.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113568:36"/>
               <p> But admit that at this day moſt do expound it for the <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> as well as for their <hi>Leviticall</hi> and <hi>Sanctified</hi> things; What doth this contradict my application of this Pſalme againſt <hi>Spoilers</hi> of Churches? or wherein is my erreur? I affirme the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> of one of the <hi>membra dividentia,</hi> and they upon both. I upon one not <hi>excluſive,</hi> and they upon both <hi>copulative.</hi> Do not they then themſelves affirme my aſſertion? Let <hi>Schoolemen</hi> be Judges. Yea do they not juſtifie and enforce it? For if <hi>God loveth the gates of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more then all the dwellings of Jacob,</hi> Pſal. 87.2. that is, <hi>the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and petty things of his Church,</hi> more then all the ſtately <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralties</hi> of his <hi>Lay people,</hi> yea, if he loveth <hi>Jacob</hi> but for <hi>Sion,</hi> that is, the <hi>People</hi> but for the <hi>Church,</hi> then <hi>Ex neceſſario conſequente,</hi> when the <hi>Prophet</hi> denounceth ſuch heavy things againſt them, that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naced Gods <hi>Lay people,</hi> and their <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi> how much the rather, doth he it againſt ſuch as with great fury and impiety afflict his more peculiar and choſen ſervants, his <hi>Clergy,</hi> his <hi>Levites,</hi> his <hi>firſt borne?</hi> Againſt thoſe I ſay, that forbeare not to violate the things more deare unto him: His <hi>Temple,</hi> his <hi>Oracle,</hi> his <hi>holy myſteries,</hi> that is, things belonging to his honour and divine ſervice, things &amp; means, ordained to the propagation of his bleſſed word? For this is the conſequence of deſtroying our Churches: this killeth the bird in the ſhell: &amp; to a perſon offending in this nature, wrote I my Book</p>
               <p>By like reaſon, it may alſo be ſaid; that this <hi>Pſalme</hi> was framed againſt Heathens and Infidells, (which in open hoſtility aſſailed the Church and people of God with fire and ſword) not againſt ſuch as be our owne brethren, and of the family of the Church, though (in ſome ſort) they do injury unto it. I anſwere that the <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> and <hi>Moabites</hi> were alſo of the kindred of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> yea, the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites,</hi> and <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> of the linage of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as well as the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> themſelves: yet when they joined with them that ſought the deſtruction of the Church; the curſes of the <hi>Prophet</hi> went as freely and as fiercely againſt them, as the reſt. So if our Church be ſpoiled by her brethren, her children, or kindred, the ſentence is all one againſt them, as againſt Heathens and Infidells, yea, and that alſo more juſtly and deſervedly by the judgement of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> who accounteth the treachery of a <hi>familiar freind</hi> much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, then the <hi>violence</hi> of an <hi>open Enemy. Pſal.</hi> 55.12.</p>
               <p>But ſay I have erred (which indeed is too common with me, though it be <hi>humanum</hi>) and doth the more eaſily befall me, having
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113568:36"/>ſaluted the <hi>Shoole</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> onely <hi>a longè</hi> and <hi>a limine:</hi> I am therefore ready with <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to put it amongſt my retractations, if there be cauſe why. yet (as he ſaid of <hi>Romulus</hi>)
<q>Sed tamen errorem quo tueatur habet.</q> For I am not the Author of this expoſition, neither is it my owne weapon, but borrowed, and put into my hand by others of elder time. I confeſſe that as they which go to battell, <hi>whet their ſwords, and bend their bowes:</hi> ſo I ſharpened both the edge and the point of it to my purpoſe. For all <hi>ſpirits</hi> are not caſt out by ordinary power, nor all <hi>humours</hi> perſwaded by ordinary reaſon. Knowing therefore what was neceſſary in particular for the party to whom I wrote, I applyed my ſelfe, &amp; my pen to that particular neceſſity: yet, not with <hi>Zidkiah</hi> to ſeduce him by untruths,<note place="margin">1 R. 22.17.</note> but as a faithfull <hi>Michaiah</hi> to leave nothing untold that belonged to his danger.</p>
               <p>See then what I have to defend my ſelfe withall, both of Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and later <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Church: the firſt applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as I take it) that ever was made of this <hi>Pſame,</hi> was (only to the purpoſe I alledge it) by <hi>Lucius</hi> a devout <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the bloody age of the Primitive Church, about 225. yeares after Chriſt; of whom (to let paſſe <hi>Cyprian</hi>) <hi>Bale,</hi> a man of our owne,<note place="margin">Epiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> giveth this teſtimony; <hi>That he was a faithfull ſervant in the Lords houſe,—and enriched his Church with healthfull doctrine, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward being purified in the Lambes blood, he peirsed the heavenly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, being put to death at Valentinian's commandement, Anno</hi> 255. This <hi>Lucius</hi> (as I noted in the margent of my Booke, <hi>pag.</hi> 39.) in an <hi>Epiſtle of his</hi> to the Biſhops of <hi>Gallia</hi> and <hi>Spaine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See bere p. <hi>60.</hi>
                  </note> having deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined many things touching the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſomewhat alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>ſpoilers</hi> and <hi>defrauders</hi> thereof (concluding them by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Judas</hi> to be <hi>theeves</hi> and <hi>ſacrilegious</hi> perſons) he proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with them in this manner: <hi>De talibus, id eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>qui fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultates Eccleſiae rapiunt, fraudant, &amp; auferunt: Dominus commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans omnibus per prophetam loquitur, dicens: Deus ne taceas tibi: ne ſileas, &amp;c.</hi> Reciteing the whole 83 <hi>Pſalme</hi> every word, as you may ſee, <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Concil. of Binius</hi> edition. <hi>pa.</hi> 180. <hi>col.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>I tooke this reverend Father and great Doctor of the Church; living in the purity of religion, in the times of perſecution, and ſo neare the ages of the Apoſtles, to be a faithful direction to my pen. Yet, leſt he ſhould ſeeme like a <hi>Sparrow alone on the houſe top,</hi> I will ſhew you the opinion of others in the after ages.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113568:37"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Petrus Damianus</hi> a <hi>Cardinall,</hi> whileſt that title was rather a name of <hi>Miniſtry</hi> then of <hi>Dignity,</hi> and long before it became mounted and purpurate, a <hi>ſtarre</hi> of his time, now almoſt 600. yeers old, underſtandeth this <hi>Pſalme</hi> alſo of Church <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi> and <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> and out of it doth vehemently confute the Chaplaines, of <hi>Duke Gothifred,</hi> which held it no ſimony to buy Biſhopricks and Prieſts places, ſo they paid nothing for the <hi>impoſition</hi> of hands (an opinion too common at this day) and he applieth againſt them the interpretation of the names of the Heathen Princes there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and concludeth them to be <hi>haereditario quodam jure San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarii poſſeſſores,</hi> as you may ſee in his <hi>Specula Mor. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Ep.</hi> 13. <hi>ad Capellan. Gothif.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rupertus</hi> who flouriſhed about 500. yeares ſince; expoundeth it <hi>contra omnes Eccleſiae hoſtes, falſes Chriſtianos, haereticos, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great <hi>Hugo Cardinalis,</hi> the firſt <hi>Poſtillator</hi> of the Bible, (who flouriſhed Anno 1240. a little alſo, before that order was diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed with the <hi>Horſe and Red Hat,</hi> and a man to whom all the Preachers of Chriſtendome are more beholden, then many of them are aware: for much of that good juice that ſweetneth the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they read, dropt from his pen, though now like rivers falling into other channels, it hath loſt his name) in his worthy Coment upon the <hi>Pſalter,</hi> applieth the words, <hi>haereditate poſſideamus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarium Dei,</hi> againſt thoſe that ambitiouſly ſeeke Church <hi>livings</hi> and dignities, deſpiſing the <hi>curſes</hi> of this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> as well among the great men of the Clergy as them of the <hi>Laity,</hi> which by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or favour obtaine Eccleſiaſticall promotions: and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt ſuch men of the Church, as conferre Prebends and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon their Nephews and kindred, <hi>building</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>Sion in</hi> (their <hi>blond, and Jeruſalem in iniquity.</hi> Neither ſpareth he the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelves, but chargeth them alſo that they <hi>poſſeſſe Gods Sanctuary,</hi> by way of <hi>inheritance,</hi> in that they keepe the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Papacy</hi> among ſuch as be only of the <hi>Romane nation.</hi> And much more to this purpoſe, which were here too long to recite: but (concluding that the Prophet hath levelled at them all in this <hi>Pſalme</hi>) he ſaith, <hi>De omnibus iſtis ſequitur: Deus meus pone eos ut rotam, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joannes Vitalis,</hi> (who lived above 300. yeares ſince, and for his fame and learning, was alſo called to be a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> ere that this dignity was yet at the higheſt pitch) vehemently enforceth this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113568:37"/>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> againſt the <hi>great men</hi> that prey upon the Church, applying the interpretation of the names therein mentioned very bitterly unto them. And ſaith further, that they poſſeſſe <hi>the Sanctuary of God by inheritance,</hi> which enter into it unworthlly, or in ſucceſſion to their unckles, nephews, and parents, and they alſo which give Benefices in that manner, waſting thereby as it were <hi>Chriſts</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary patrimony; with much more to this effect, <hi>Speculo morale tit. Principes ſaeculares. fol.</hi> 229. <abbr>d.</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicolaus de Lyra,</hi> who flouriſhed about the ſame time, our own country-man, (though of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Parents) a ſtarre alſo in that age of the firſt magnitude, for his learning; and exquiſit above all in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> (it being his mother tongue, and elaborate by him) whoſe judgement I the rather eſteeme, for that <hi>Luther</hi> loved him and preferred him above all interpreters, as <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in the 2 and 9 <hi>chap. of Geneſts.</hi> He (I ſay, as before I have noted) expoundeth it: firſt, and properly for the <hi>Temple</hi> (under which I underſtand all things dedicated unto God) then for <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>the Temple was there:</hi> and laſtly by <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> (for that is his owne word) <hi>for the Land of Judaea, whoſe cheife City Jeruſalem was.</hi> So that he maketh the <hi>Temple</hi> and things belonging to God, to be the maine part whereat the Prophet aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the City and Countrey to follow but by inferance and implication.</p>
               <p>Come to the later Writers, <hi>Genebrard</hi> noteth upon <hi>Sanctuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Dei;</hi> that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word is, <hi>Habitacula,</hi> and for the <hi>poſtill</hi> ſaith; <hi>Generaliter de divinis omnibus templis, urbibus, locis, &amp; oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis populi Dei.</hi> So that if he had beene queſtioned further; how he underſtood <hi>Habitacula, ſpecialiter,</hi> it is then like he would have anſwered, <hi>de divinis omnibus templis tantùm:</hi> that is, <hi>only of Churches.</hi> But be it as it is, he ſetteth them in the firſt place, as the proper ſignification, and the reſt in conſequence, as <hi>analogicall,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and our Country-man <hi>Lyranus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Luther,</hi> he expoundeth not this <hi>Pſalme</hi> himſelfe, that I can finde; but you ſee what he attributeth to <hi>Lyra's</hi> judgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pellican</hi> a great <hi>Hebritian,</hi> tranſlateth it <hi>Poſſideamus nobis ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſſima Dei,</hi> and expoundeth it in like manner as before, <hi>Templum, eivitatem, vaſa, populum Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pomeranus</hi> interpreteth it of them that did ſeeke to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Lords and heires of the Temple.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113568:38"/>
               <p> To conclude, becauſe the neweſt things are moſt acceptable with many. The laſt man that hath written upon the <hi>Pſalter, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> a Jeſuit, (and therefore I will not preſſe his authority) yet to doe him right, very well eſteemed amongſt great Clerkes of our owne Church for much good learning (though in matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, full enough of Romiſh leaven) reciteth ſomewhat more breifly the former interpretations of <hi>Petrus Damianus, Hugo Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalis,</hi> and <hi>John Vitalis,</hi> and approving thoſe their applications, putteth them ſtill on into the world, as truly conſonant to the tenor of the Pſalme, which notwithſtanding I doubt not hath alſo many other expoſitions, as herbes have uſually divers virtues and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. But thus the eldeſt and neweſt expoſitors are wholly for me, many alſo (and of the beſt of them) of the middle ages, none that I know againſt me. For although <hi>Muſculus, Bucer, Calvin, Marlorat, Mollerus,</hi> expoundeth this Pſalme hiſtorically of the Countrey and Nation of the Jewes, yet when they apply it to the Church of Chriſt (as otherwiſe there were no uſe of it) they make that application by way of figure and <hi>analogy;</hi> And then is there no cauſe to raiſe an <hi>antitheſis,</hi> or contrariety betweene them and me. For to reconcile the matter, Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> in his entrance into the expoſition of this Pſalme, telleth us, that we may expound it figuratively of the Church (which I underſtand in matters of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, gouernment, doctrine,) <hi>or hiſtorically of the people of the Jewes and nations</hi> about them. And though <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelfe purſueth for the moſt part the hiſtoricall interpretation, yet when he commeth to the 12. verſe, he ſaith; <hi>Iterum accuſat profanos homines ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gij, quòd praedatoriâ licentiâ involant in ipſam Dei haereditatem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much, and too much touching this point. As it is ſaid in the end of the <hi>Macchabees: If I have done well, and as the ſtory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, it is the thing that I deſired: but if I have ſpoken ſlenderly and barely, it is that I could.</hi> Let no man therefore rely upon me, but learne of them that are bound to teach; <hi>For the Preiſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the law at his mouth: for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts. Mal.</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p>Other things there be, wherein I would willingly have enlarged my ſelfe a little: but as <hi>Papilius in Livy</hi> deſcribing a circle about <hi>Antiochus</hi> enforced him to anſwere before he ſtept out of it. So the Printer (having printed all to the laſt Sheet before I knew it) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth me, <hi>ad articulum temporis,</hi> within which accordingly I muſt needs end.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
